<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OC 18/49 : 1-24-33 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© In the public domain.  
© Transcription Christoph Hust, 2008.
© Translation Ian Bent, 2008
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary Christoph Hust 2007.
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>This document is deemed to be in the public domain as of January 1, 2006.  Any claim to intellectual rights should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1933-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-1938) - -Oster, Ernst (1938-c.1939)—New York Public Library (c.1939-)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: In the public domain; Image: New York Public Library, New York; Transcription, Commentary, Footnotes: Christoph Hust, Translation, Summary: Ian Bent.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 01/24/1933 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: &quot;Furtw&#195;&#164;ngler ~ H+JSchenker&quot;,&quot;Furtw&#195;&#164;ngler ~ HSchenker&quot;,&quot;Karpath ~ HSchenker&quot;,&quot;MarxJ ~ HSchenker&quot; --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Schenker to Furtwängler, dated January 24, 1933</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2008-05-02</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Schenker has received a letter from Karpath, and alerts Furtwängler that he will be hearing from him about the proposed letter to the newspaper;  Schenker reports on recent visit by Joseph Marx re the adaptation of Harmonielehre;  Schenker would now be willing to associate with the Akademie, but appointments there come about only by intrigue.  

</dc:description><dc:subject> Schenker, Heinrich;  Furtwängler, Wilhelm;  Karpath, Ludwig;  Vienna;  Marx, Joseph;  Akademie für Musik und darstellende Kunst;  Vienna Conservatory;  Harmonielehre;  Theory of Harmony;  Hoboken, Anthony van;  Urlinie;  Zusammenhang;  freie Satz, Der;  Pernter, Hans</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - - </marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Schenker to Furtwängler, dated January 24, 1933
= Sbb 55 Nachl 13, <tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn8"> However, the book did not come out before Schenker's death. </tei:note></tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Verehrtester, lieber Herr <tei:hi rend="italic">D^r^ Furtwängler</tei:hi>!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  For record of writing this letter, see &lt;a href="../../../../diary/oj<tei:hi rend="italic">46</tei:hi>p<tei:hi rend="italic">3806</tei:hi>12433.html"&gt;OJ 4/6, p. 3806, January 24, 1933&lt;/a&gt;.  For background to this letter, see &lt;a href="../../../../diary/oj<tei:hi rend="italic">46</tei:hi>p<tei:hi rend="italic">3802</tei:hi>1233.html"&gt;OJ 4/6, p. 3802, January 2&lt;/a&gt;;  &lt;a href="../../../../diary/oj<tei:hi rend="italic">46</tei:hi>p<tei:hi rend="italic">3802</tei:hi>1333.html"&gt;OJ 4/6, p. 3802, January 3&lt;/a&gt;;  &lt;a href="../../../../diary/oj<tei:hi rend="italic">46</tei:hi>p<tei:hi rend="italic">3804</tei:hi>11433.html"&gt;OJ 4/6, p. 3804, January 14&lt;/a&gt;;  &lt;a href="../../../../diary/oj<tei:hi rend="italic">46</tei:hi>p<tei:hi rend="italic">3804</tei:hi>11633.html"&gt;OJ 4/6, p. 3804, January 16, 1920&lt;/a&gt;;  &lt;a href="../../../../diary/oj<tei:hi rend="italic">46</tei:hi>p<tei:hi rend="italic">3805</tei:hi>11833.html"&gt;OJ 4/6, p. 3805, January 18&lt;/a&gt; (account of meeting with Marx); &lt;a href="../../../../diary/oj<tei:hi rend="italic">46</tei:hi>p<tei:hi rend="italic">3806</tei:hi>12133.html"&gt;OJ 4/6, p. 3806, January 21&lt;/a&gt;.  </tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Soeben erhalte ich einen Brief von Hofrat <tei:hi rend="italic">Karpath</tei:hi>,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  Ludwig Karpath: [create profile and link].  </tei:note> worin er mir mitteilt, daß er <tei:hi rend="italic">gleichzeitig</tei:hi> <tei:hi rend="italic">an</tei:hi> <tei:hi rend="italic">Sie</tei:hi> wegen der gewissen Instruktion schreibe!  Seine erste Urgierung habe ich damit abgewandt, daß ich sagte, es sei Ihnen vielleicht peinlich, mich den Wienern erst durch die Ztg bekannt zu machen, wo ^ich^ doch außerhalb Wiens sehr gut bekannt bin als der, der ich bin.</tei:p><tei:p>Nun aber begab sich, daß vor ein paar Tagen Hofrat <tei:hi rend="italic">D^r^ Marx</tei:hi>,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  Click on <ref cRef="marx_joseph">Joseph Marx</ref>.  In his obituary for Schenker ("Der Musikforscher Heinrich Schenker", <tei:hi rend="italic">Neues Wiener Journal</tei:hi>, February 3, 1935, p. 8, ed. in <tei:hi rend="italic">Betrachtungen eines romantischen Realisten. Gesammelte Aufsätze, Vorträge und Reden über Musik</tei:hi>, ed. Oswald Ortner (Vienna: Gerlach &amp; Wiedling 1947), pp. 405–409, quotation from p. 408), Marx recalls: "Some time ago I had visited him and admired his unstinting capacity for work.  He was actually thinking of promoting his system by way of several short guides;  those principal works were too comprehensive and therefore time-consuming."  (Vor einiger Zeit hatte ich ihn besucht und seine ungebrochene Arbeitskraft bewundert. Er dachte eben daran, sein System durch einige kurze Leitfäden zu fördern; jene Hauptarbeiten waren zu umfangreich und daher kostspielig.)</tei:note> der Direktor unserer <tei:hi rend="italic">Akademie</tei:hi>,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4"> i.e. the Akademie für Musik und darstellende Kunst (= Vienna Conservatory). </tei:note> bei mir war, um Näheres zur Bearbeitung meiner <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> Harmonielehre (<tei:hi rend="italic">Bd I</tei:hi>) festzusetzen.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  See Robert W. Wason, "From Harmonielehre to Harmony: Schenker's Theory of Harmony and Its Americanization," in <tei:hi rend="italic">Schenker-Traditionen. Eine Wiener Schule der Musiktheorie und ihre internationale Verbreitung / A Viennese School of Music Theory and Its International Dissemination</tei:hi>, ed. Martin Eybl and Evelyn Fink-Mennel (Vienna, Cologne, Weimar: Böhlau 2006), Wiener Veröffentlichungen zur Musikgeschichte 6, pp. 171–201. </tei:note>  [<tei:hi rend="italic">cued from lower margin:</tei:hi> Ob die „<tei:hi rend="italic">U. E</tei:hi>“ ^die Kosten^ wird tragen wollen oder gar können, wird sich zeigen.]  Bei dieser Gelegenheit sprach er auch von seiner Absicht, auch andere Stücke von mir zum Gegenstand besonderer Vorlesungen zu machen.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6"> Cf. Schenker's letter to Oswald Jonas, January 26, 1933 (OJ 5/18, [22]). </tei:note>  Nun weiß <tei:hi rend="italic">D^r^M</tei:hi>. ganz gewiß, daß es Sitte ist, wenn Verfasser von Lehrbüchern selbst als Erste ihren Stoff lehren, auch zweifle ich nicht, daß <tei:hi rend="italic">M</tei:hi>. bei mir mit der Sitte einverstanden wäre, wenn er nur Ahnung hätte, daß ich ^heute^ wegen widriger Umstände mich der <tei:hi rend="italic">Akademie</tei:hi> ^anzuschließen bereit wäre^ &lt;strike&gt;anschlöße&lt;/strike&gt;.  Aber .  . er hält mich für reich, unabhängig, u. – „<tei:hi rend="italic">Hoboken</tei:hi>“<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7">  Click on <ref cRef="hoboken_anthony_van">Anthony van Hoboken</ref>.  Hoboken was a independently wealthy.   </tei:note>!</tei:p><tei:p>Daraufhin schrieb ich an <tei:hi rend="italic">Karpath</tei:hi>, daß sich eine ganz <tei:hi rend="italic">natürliche</tei:hi> <tei:hi rend="italic">Veranlassung</tei:hi> zur sehr ehrenvollen Berufung ergäbe, <tei:hi rend="italic">wenn</tei:hi> meine Lehre in die <tei:hi rend="italic">Akademie</tei:hi> mit <tei:hi rend="italic"><tei:hi rend="italic">Hmlehre</tei:hi></tei:hi>, Urlinie, der Lehre vom Zusammenhang ein- <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> zöge.  Und doch kommt <tei:hi rend="italic">Karp</tei:hi>. auf seine unglückliche Idee zurück!  Der gute Mensch weiß nicht, daß er mir nur schaden würde, wenn er mich durch den Koth eines Wiener Mitleids zerrte; so überflüssig übrigens, wenn schon meine Lehre ohnehin anzieht.</tei:p><tei:p>Vielleicht entrinnen Sie ihm, wenn Sie ihm für <tei:hi rend="italic"><tei:hi rend="italic">post festum</tei:hi></tei:hi> einen <tei:hi rend="italic">Aufsatz</tei:hi> <tei:hi rend="italic">zusagen</tei:hi>, in dem Sie Ihrer Genugtuung über meine Berufung Ausdruck geben.</tei:p><tei:p>Sagte mir doch <tei:hi rend="italic">D^r^ Marx</tei:hi>, daß alle Berufungen nur durch Beziehungen, <tei:hi rend="italic">Intriguen</tei:hi>, geheime Machenschaften erfolgen!  Warum müßte gerade ich beleidigt werden? Es ist ja nur <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> ein Misverständnis;  ich gelte den Wienern für reich.  O! Könnte ich es nur so machen, wie die Engländer u. Franzosen, die den Anderen Geld aus der Tasche ziehen u. es Währungspolitik u. sonstige Politik nennen.</tei:p><tei:p>Hätte ich das verlorene Ersparnis wieder, ich säße auch schon an anderen Stoffen. Vorläufig &lt;strike&gt;gesch&lt;/strike&gt; gedeiht der „fr. S.“ immer weiter, weiter.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn8"> However, the book did not come out before Schenker's death. </tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Und schließlich, wenn <tei:hi rend="italic">Kp</tei:hi>. schreibt:  „Ein Mann wie <tei:hi rend="italic">Pernter</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn9">  Hans Pernter:  [create profile and link].</tei:note> (Sektionschef), benötigt die <tei:hi rend="italic">Autorität</tei:hi> eines Furtwängler, um das zu glauben, was ich ihm viel leichter auseinandersetzen könnte“, würde ^er^ sich &lt;strike&gt;aber Kp.&lt;/strike&gt; nicht zufrieden geben, wenn Sie vorschlügen, den Bf direkt an <tei:hi rend="italic">Pernter</tei:hi> zu schreiben?  (Mit Umgehung der Öffentlichkeit.)  Verzeihen Sie, daß ich so heftig schreibe, aber <tei:hi rend="italic">Kp</tei:hi>'s Bf an Sie zwingt mich!</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">in upper margin, inverted:</tei:hi>]
Mit allerbesten Empfehlungen von uns Beiden 
Ihr
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] <tei:hi rend="italic">H Schenker</tei:hi>
24.1.33</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Schenker to Furtwängler, dated January 24, 1933
= Sbb 55 Nachl 13, <tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn8"/></tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Most honored, dear Dr. Furtwängler,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/></tei:p><tei:p>I have just received a letter from Court Counsellor Karpath<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> in which he informs me that he is writing <tei:hi rend="italic">to you</tei:hi> <tei:hi rend="italic">at the same time</tei:hi> regarding the instruction discussed previously!  I deflected his first pressing request by saying that it would perhaps be embarrassing for you to acquaint the Viennese with me first through the newspaper, when ^I^ am very well known outside of Vienna (which is indeed the case).</tei:p><tei:p>Now, it so happened that Court Consellor Dr. Marx,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> the Director of our Academy,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> was with me a few days ago to settle the details of the adaptation of my <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> <tei:hi rend="italic">Theory of Harmony</tei:hi> (vol. I).<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/>  [<tei:hi rend="italic">cued from lower margin:</tei:hi> whether or not UE is going to want, or be able, to bear ^the costs^, we shall see.]  On this occasion, he spoke also of his plan to take other works of mine as the topics of special lectures.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/>  Now, Dr. Marx knows very well that it is customary for authors of textbooks to be the first to teach their [own] material, and I do not doubt that Marx would agree to follow that custom in my case if he had any inkling that I were prepared ^today^ to affiliate myself with the Academy on account of adverse circumstances.   But . . . he thinks I am wealthy, independent, and – "Hoboken"!<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/></tei:p><tei:p>On the strength of this, I wrote to Karpath that a wholly <tei:hi rend="italic">natural opportunity</tei:hi> would present itself for a very honorable appointment, <tei:hi rend="italic">if</tei:hi> my theory were to be taken up by the Academy, with my <tei:hi rend="italic">theory of harmony</tei:hi>, Urlinie, [and] the theory of connection. <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> At that, Karpath reverted to his hapless idea!  The good fellow does not realize that he would do me nothing but harm if he were to drag me through the mire of Viennese pity.  And so unnecessary, what is more, if my theory is in any case already attracting attention.</tei:p><tei:p>Perhaps you might escape his clutches if you <tei:hi rend="italic">promise</tei:hi> [him] an <tei:hi rend="italic">article</tei:hi> for <tei:hi rend="italic">after the event</tei:hi>, in which you express your satisfaction at my appointment.</tei:p><tei:p>Dr. Marx actually told me that all appointments come about only by personal contacts, intrigues, [and] behind-the-scenes wire-pulling!  Why must I, too, be insulted?  It is really only <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> a misunderstanding;  the Viennese take me for a rich man.  Oh!  If I could only do as the English and French do, and take money from the pockets of others, calling it "monetary policy" or some other kind of politicking.</tei:p><tei:p>If only I had my lost savings back, I would already be hatching other things.  For the time being, <tei:hi rend="italic">Free Composition</tei:hi> goes on from strength to strength.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn8"/></tei:p><tei:p>And lastly, when Karpath writes "A man such as Pernter<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn9"/> (departmental head) needs the authority of a Furtwängler in order to believe that which I could much more easily explain to him," would ^he^ not rest content if you were to suggest writing the letter direct to Pernter  (thereby avoiding the publicity)?  Forgive me for writing so passionately, but Karpath's letter to you drives me to do so!</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">in upper margin, inverted:</tei:hi>]
With all the best wishes from us both, 
Yours, 
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] H Schenker
24.1.33</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>