<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OC 18/37&#226;&#128;&#147;38 : 12-10-32 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© Heirs of Wilhelm Furtwängler, published with kind permission.
© Transcription Christoph Hust, 2008.
© Translation Ian Bent, 2008.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary Christoph Hust, 2008
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>Heirs of Wilhelm Furtwängler, permission to publish granted on February 2, 2005.  Any claim to intellectual rights on this document should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1932-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-1938) - -Oster, Ernst (1938-c.1939)—New York Public Library (c.1939-)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: Heirs of Wilhelm Furtwängler, permission to publish granted on February 2, 2005. Image: New York Public Library, New York; Transcription, Commentary, Footnotes: Christoph Hust;  Translation, Summary: Ian Bent.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 12/10/1932 05:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: &quot;Furtw&#195;&#164;ngler ~ H+JSchenker&quot;,&quot;Furtw&#195;&#164;ngler ~ HSchenker&quot; --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Furtwängler to Schenker, dated December10, 1932</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2008-04-30</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Furtwängler shares Schenker's assessment of Ludwig Karpath, and has not written a letter for publication.  —He has been exploring possibilities for Schenker in Berlin, particularly taking over a masterclass at the Akademie der Künste, with additional lectures at the Stern'sches Conservatory. —He has heard from Hans Weisse. —He encloses a review by Herman Roth, and comments on the latter's character.  

</dc:description><dc:subject>Furtwängler, Wilhelm;  Schenker, Heinrich;  Karpath, Ludwig;  Vienna;  Berlin;  Akademie der Künste;  Hochschule für Musik;  Kestenberg, Leo;  Ministry of Education;  Graener, Paul;  Weisse, Hans;  Roth, Herman;  Hamburg;  Stein, Fritz;  Muck, Carl;  Bruckner</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN"> Potsdam</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Furtwängler to Schenker, dated December 10, 1932</tei:hi>
<tei:hi rend="bold">= Sbb 55 Nachl 13, <tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  The Akademie der Künste in Berlin, which had since 1869 included a Hochschule für Musik the Director of which was from 1920 to 1932 Franz Schreker, and from 1932 Georg Schünemann.   The idea came to nothing because of residential eligibility (diary entry March 2, 1933).  </tei:note></tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="italic">Potsdam</tei:hi>, 10. XII. 32.</tei:p><tei:p>Lieber verehrter Herr <tei:hi rend="italic">Schenker</tei:hi>,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  For record of the receipt and summary of this letter, see Schenker's diary, &lt;a href="../../../../diary/oj<tei:hi rend="italic">46</tei:hi>p<tei:hi rend="italic">3798</tei:hi>121632_1.html"&gt;OJ 4/6, p. 3798, December 16, 1932&lt;/a&gt;.  </tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Erst heute habe ich ein ruhiges Stündchen, um Ihnen zu antworten.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  If a letter from Schenker, then none is known to survive.  For part of the background to this letter, see Schenker's diary, &lt;a href="../../../../diary/oj<tei:hi rend="italic">46</tei:hi>p<tei:hi rend="italic">3792</tei:hi>111832.html"&gt;OJ 4/6, p. 3792, November 18, 1932&lt;/a&gt;.</tei:note>  Zunächst:  Was Karpath<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  Ludwig Karpath: [create profile and link]. </tei:note> betrifft, so hatte ich schon bei meinem Besuch bei ihm am vorletzten Tage meines <tei:hi rend="italic">Wiener</tei:hi> Aufenthaltes einen ähnlichen Eindruck, wie Sie ihn mir von sich aus mitteilen.  Nämlich den, daß er nur versucht, die ganze Angelegenheit in seine journalistischen Kanäle zu leiten und das ihm viel wichtiger ist als die Sache selbst, zu der er offenbar gar kein Verhältnis hat.  Außerdem hat mir diesmal seine allzusehr auf Schritt und Tritt hervortretende Eitelkeit während des Gesprächs einen etwas unseriösen Eindruck gemacht;  auch scheint mir, daß <tei:hi rend="italic">de facto</tei:hi> in letzter Zeit sein Einfluß sehr nachgelassen hat.  Jedenfalls bin ich darin durchaus Ihrer Meinung, daß ein Brief von mir über Sie, an ihn zur Veröffentlichung geschickt, schließlich praktisch gesehen nicht das gewünschte Ergebnis <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> haben dürfte. Ich habe einen solchen daher auch nicht geschrieben.  Hier habe ich inzwischen Erkundigungen einzuziehen versucht.  Die Verhältnisse sind – oder waren – durch die beständigen Regierungskrisen sehr kompliziert.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  1932 was the last year of the Weimar Republic.</tei:note>  Immerhin scheint mir eine Möglichkeit, daß man Ihnen eine sog. „Meisterklasse“ für Komposition [<tei:hi rend="italic">cued from left margin:</tei:hi> von der Akademie aus!] anbietet, die im September 1933 frei wird.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  The Akademie der Künste in Berlin, which had since 1869 included a Hochschule für Musik the Director of which was from 1920 to 1932 Franz Schreker, and from 1932 Georg Schünemann.   The idea came to nothing because of residential eligibility (diary entry March 2, 1933).  </tei:note>  Das wäre, wenn <tei:hi rend="italic">Kestenberg</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  Click on <ref cRef="kestenberg_leo">Leo Kestenberg</ref>. </tei:note> noch seine frühere Stellung im <tei:hi rend="italic">Ministerium</tei:hi> innehätte, ohne weiteres zu realisieren gewesen;  wieweit das unter den jetzt veränderten Verhältnissen der Fall ist, weiß ich noch nicht genau, ich werde aber versuchen, mir darüber noch vor Weihnachten Klarheit zu verschaffen.  Dies würde Ihnen materiell eine Existenzgrundlage geben können. Sonstige Vorlesungen – entweder in der Hochschule oder bei <tei:hi rend="italic">Gräner</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7">  Click on <ref cRef="graener_paul">Paul Graener</ref>.  </tei:note> (der sich über Sie begeistert aussprach) [–] von deren befruchtender Wirkung ich mir unter Umständen allerlei verspräche, könnten <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> dann leicht angeschlossen werden.  Ich werde jedenfalls bald Ihnen mehr sagen können, als ich jetzt weiß;  es geht das jedoch vielleicht nicht ganz so schnell, einmal wegen der wirklich im Moment sehr unübersichtlichen Verhältnisse hier, und dann weil ich auch nicht immer die nötige Zeit habe.</tei:p><tei:p>Von <tei:hi rend="italic">Weisse</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn8">  Click on <ref cRef="weisse_hans">Hans Weisse</ref>.  Weisse lived in New York at this time. See David Carson Berry, "Hans Weisse (1892–1940)," in <tei:hi rend="italic">Schenker-Traditionen. Eine Wiener Schule der Musiktheorie und ihre internationale Verbreitung / A Viennese School of Music Theory and Its International Dissemination</tei:hi>, ed. Martin Eybl and Evelyn Fink-Mennel (Vienna, Cologne, Weimar: Böhlau 2006), Wiener Veröffentlichungen zur Musikgeschichte 6, pp. 91–103, see also Schenker's letter to Furtwängler sketched in his diar, OJ 5/11, [1], vsns 1 and 2.</tei:note> habe ich einen kurzen Brief bekommen.  Es geht im gut, und er hat offenbar – wenn man die Verhältnisse bedenkt, unter denen er wirkt – viel Erfolg, was mich sehr freut.  
Ich schreibe Ihnen bald wieder. Für heute mit den herzlichsten Grüßen wie immer – auch an Ihre Frau –</tei:p><tei:p>Ihr
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] <tei:hi rend="italic">Wilhelm Furtwängler</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Anbei eine Kritik Ihres Schülers Roth<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn9">  Click on <ref cRef="roth_herman">Herman Roth</ref>.</tei:note> aus Hamburg.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn10">  Perhaps Hermann Roth, "Bekenntnis zu Schenker," <tei:hi rend="italic">Hamburger Nachrichten</tei:hi>, September 17, 1931, a clipping of which appears in Schenker's scrapbook on OC 2/p.84, though one would have expected Schenker to have encountered this long before now.    </tei:note>   Er ist auch einer von jenen deutschen Intellektuellen – ohnedies eine von Neid nicht freie, in sich wenig wohlwollende Natur – die plötzlich anders zuhören, wenn einer das zweifelhafte Glück hat, „berühmt“ zu sein.  Die letzte Bemerkung heißt doch geradezu:  möge die Welt endlich über ihre falsche <tei:hi rend="italic">Furtwängler</tei:hi>-Begeisterung aufgeklärt werden.  Und sowas muß man sich gefallen lassen!  Charakteristisch [<tei:hi rend="italic">in the left margin:</tei:hi>] auch was er lobt: den dirigierenden <tei:hi rend="italic">Fritz Stein</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn11">  Click on <ref cRef="stein_fritz">Fritz Stein</ref>. </tei:note>, den „Bruckner“ <tei:hi rend="italic">Muck'</tei:hi>s<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn12">  Click on <ref cRef="muck_carl">Carl Muck</ref>. </tei:note>!!</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Furtwängler to Schenker, dated December 10, 1932</tei:hi>
<tei:hi rend="bold">= Sbb 55 Nachl 13, <tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/></tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Potsdam, December 10,  1932.</tei:p><tei:p>Dear, honored Mr. Schenker,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/></tei:p><tei:p>Today is the first time I have had a quiet moment in which to answer you.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/>  First:  as concerns Karpath,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> I had a similar impression to that which you convey to me, when I visited him on the penultimate day of my stay in Vienna.  Namely that he is only trying to divert the whole matter into his journalistic channels, and that that is much more important to him than the matter itself, for which he clearly has no affinity.  In addition, his overweening vanity, which came out at every turn during our conversation, this time gave me the impression perhaps of untrustworthiness.  It also seems to me that his influence has <tei:hi rend="italic">de facto</tei:hi> very much diminished in recent times.  At any rate, I am thoroughly of one mind with you that a letter from me about you, sent to him for publication, would not seem ultimately, from a practical point of view, to yield the desired outcome.  <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> Accordingly, I not written such a letter.  I have meanwhile been trying to do some exploration here.  Conditions as a result of constant government crises are—or were—very complicated.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/>  There seems to me to be at least a possibility that you may be offered a so-called "masterclass" in composition [<tei:hi rend="italic">cued from left margin:</tei:hi> emanating from the Academy!], which would fall vacant in September 1933.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/>  That could have been achieved without more ado, if Kestenberg<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/> still had his earlier post at the Ministry;  to what extent that is the case under the present, altered conditions, I can't exactly say, but I will try and clarify the matter by Christmas.  This could give you a financial basis for existence.  Other lectures—either at the Highschool or with Gräner<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/> (who declared himself enthusiastic about you)—of the inspiring impact of which I would give sundry assurances should the occasion arise, could <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> then easily be added.  I will at any rate soon be able to tell you more than I know now;  things may however perhaps not go as fast as we would like, firstly because conditions here are really very unclear at the moment, secondly because I may not always myself have the necessary time.</tei:p><tei:p>I have had a short letter from Weisse.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn8"/>  He is doing well, and has clearly—bearing in mind the conditions under which he is working—had much success, which pleases me greatly.</tei:p><tei:p>I shall write to you again soon.  For today, with most cordial greetings as ever—and to your wife,</tei:p><tei:p>Yours,
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] Wilhelm Furtwängler</tei:p><tei:p>Enclosed [is] a review by your pupil Roth<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn9"/> from Hamburg.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn10"/>  He is also one of those German intellectuals—anyway, a personality in itself not all that benevolent, not devoid of envy—who suddenly pay attention differently when one has the dubious fortune of being "famous."  With this last remark, I really mean to say:  may the world at long last be enlightened over its false enthusiasm for Furtwängler.  And one has to put up with that sort of thing!  [<tei:hi rend="italic">in the left margin:</tei:hi>] What he praises is characteristic, too:  Fritz Stein<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn11"/> as a conductor, [and] the Muck's<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn12"/> Bruckner!!</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>