<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 10/4 : 1-26-16 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© In the public domain.
© Transcription Ian Bent, 2006.
© Translation Ian Bent, 2006.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary Ian Bent 2006
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>This document is deemed to be in the public domain.  Any claim to intellectual rights on this document should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1916-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1955) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1955-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: In the public domain; Image: University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: Ian Bent.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 01/26/1916 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "DeutschS ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Deutsch to Schenker, dated January 26, 1916</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-09-07</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>SD places money at HS's disposal for publication of his future works; the bequest betokens undying gratitude to him.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Deutsch, Sofie; Sophie;  Schenker, Heinrich;  bequest;  publishing costs;  gratitude</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  Vienna I, Albrechtsgasse 3</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN"> Vienna</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Sofie Deutsch to Schenker, dated January 26, 1916</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="italic">Wien 26. 1. 1916</tei:hi>
<tei:hi rend="italic">Herrn Doctor Heinrich Schenker</tei:hi>
<tei:hi rend="italic"><tei:hi rend="italic">Wien</tei:hi></tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  An incomplete copy of paragraph 1 of this document with slight variants appears in HS’s hand on OC 1/23v, upside down within a draft in JS’s hand of a letter to Siegfried Türkel dated March 17, 1917.  It reads as follows:  “Mit Freuden mache ich Ihnen Mitteilung von meinem / Entschluß, Ihnen zu Zwecken der Herausgabe weiterer / Arbeiten den Betrag von 10.000 MK (zehn- / tausend Mark) zur Verfügung zu stellen, die / Ihnen in Teilbeträgen gegen Vorweisung von / Verlegerrechnungen eben an die Verleger von meinem / Bankhaus angewiesen werden.  Der ^Von dieser Summe steht^ Betrag / Ihnen bis zur Höhe von 1500 MK auch / ohne Vorweisung von Belegen zur fr. Verf, / zur Deckung von Nebenkosten.  Das / Bankhaus erhält gleichzeitig diesbez. / Instrukt. von mir.“ (It is with joy that I inform you of my decision to place at your disposal, for the purpose of publishing future works, the sum of 10,000 Marks (ten thousand Marks), which will be remitted in installments upon presentation of publishers’ accounts to the managers[?] of my banking house.  ^Of this total sum^, [an] amount of up to fifteen hundred Marks is also freely at your disposal without presentation of documentation in order to cover incidental costs.  My banking house is receiving instructions from me to this effect at the same time.)</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Mit großer Freude mache ich Ihnen Mitteilung von meinem Entschlusse Ihnen zu Zwecken der Herausgabe Ihrer weiteren Arbeiten den Betrag von <tei:hi rend="italic">zehntausend Mark</tei:hi> in Jahresentnahmen bis cirka  dreitausend Mark zur Verfügung zu stellen, die in Teilbeträgen gegen Vorweisung von Verlegerrechnungen an die Verleger von meinem Bank- <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> haus „<tei:hi rend="italic">Wiener Bankverein X, Keplerplatz</tei:hi>[„] angewiesen werden.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  Federhofer, <tei:hi rend="italic">Nach Tagebüchern ...</tei:hi>, p.38, reports: “Mrs. Deutsch left Schenker a yearly legacy of 3,000 Marks, which was to make possible the publishing of the second half-volume of <tei:hi rend="italic">Counterpoint</tei:hi> (diary January 28, 1916), and in addition a foundation for needy artists, whom Schenker had the exclusive authority to name (diary January 13 and April 12, 1917).”  [Footnote 58:  “When S. Deutsch died as early as January 1917 in a Vienna sanatorium, Schenker—as she was a widow and childless—sent his condolences to her brother Fritz Mendl (diary January 6, 1917): ....;   Schenker gave up the office of juror as soon as two years later (diary December 28, 1919).   From this foundation, he caused higher payments to be made to A. Halm and the German Legation in Vienna of German Aid in favor of Penurious Composers.   ...”]</tei:note>  Von dieser Gesammtsumme steht Ihnen indessen der Betrag bis zur Höhe von fünfzehnhundert Mark auch ohne Vorweisung von Belegen zur freien Verfügung.  Mein Bankhaus erhält gleichzeitig die diesbezügliche Instruction von mir.</tei:p><tei:p>Ich danke Ihnen, hochverehrter Meister, daß Sie mir Gelegenheit geben Ihnen einen kleinen Beweis meiner unvergänglichen Dankbarkeit zu erbringen, und wünsche Ihnen für Ihre selbstlose Arbeit im Interesse Ihrer heiligen Kunst den so wolverdienten vollen Erfolg.</tei:p><tei:p>In herzlicher Freundschaft Ihre dankbare Schülerin</tei:p><tei:p>[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] Sofie Deutsch
I. Albrechtgasse 3</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Sofie Deutsch to Schenker, dated January 26, 1916</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Vienna January 26, 1916
Dr. Heinrich Schenker,
<tei:hi rend="italic">Vienna</tei:hi>|<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/></tei:p><tei:p>It is with great joy that I inform you of my decision to place at your disposal, for the purpose of publishing your future works, the sum of <tei:hi rend="italic">ten thousand Marks</tei:hi> in annual withdrawals of up to circa three thousand Marks, which will be remitted in installments upon presentation of publishers’ accounts to the managers[?] of my banking <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> house, the Vienna Banking Association, [Vienna] X, Keplerplatz.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/>  Of this total sum, an amount of up to fifteen hundred Marks is meanwhile also freely at your disposal without presentation of supporting documentation.  My banking house is receiving instructions from me to this effect at the same time.</tei:p><tei:p>I thank you, highly revered master, for giving me the opportunity to furnish some small proof of my undying gratitude, and to wish you well-earned unalloyed success with your selfless work in the interests of your sacred art.</tei:p><tei:p>In heartfelt friendship, your grateful student,</tei:p><tei:p>[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] Sofie Deutsch
[Vienna] I, Albrechtgasse</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>