<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 11/16, [12] : 9-22-32 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© Heirs of Wilhelm Furtwängler, published with kind permission.
© Transcription Christoph Hust, 2008.
© Translation Ian Bent, 2008.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary Christoph Hust, 2008
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>Heirs of Wilhelm Furtwängler, permission to publish granted on February 2, 2005.  Any claim to intellectual rights on this document should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1932-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935- c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1955) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1955-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: Heirs of Wilhelm Furtwängler;  Image: University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: Christoph Hust; Translation: Ian Bent.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 09/22/1932 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: &quot;Furtw&#195;&#164;ngler ~ H+JSchenker&quot;,&quot;Furtw&#195;&#164;ngler ~ HSchenker&quot; --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Furtwängler to Schenker, dated September 22, 1932</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2008-04-28</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Furtwängler was prevented from visiting Schenker in August by having to go into the Cottage Sanatorium, Vienna.  He hopes to see Schenker during the winter, and asks whether he might like to do the ceremonial address for the Brahms Centenary.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Furtwängler, Wilhelm;  Schenker, Heinrich;  Igls;  Switzerland;  Cottage Sanatorium;  Vienna;  Deutsche Brahms-Gesellschaft;  German Brahms Society;  Brahms Festival</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  Berlin</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Furtwängler to Schenker, dated September 22, 1932</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>22. IX. 32.  Berlin<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1"> For the diary entry recording this letter, click on &lt;a href="../../../../../diary/oj<tei:hi rend="italic">45</tei:hi>p<tei:hi rend="italic">3776</tei:hi>92632.html"&gt;OJ 4/5, p. 3776&lt;/a&gt;.  The letter is part-transcribed in Federhofer, <tei:hi rend="italic">Heinrich Schenker nach Tagebüchern und Briefen ...</tei:hi> (Hildesheim:  Georg Olms, 1985), pp. 128f.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Lieber verehrter Herr Dr. Schenker,</tei:p><tei:p>Meine Absicht, Sie im Laufe des Sommers in Igls<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  Click on <ref cRef="igls">Igls</ref>.  For his earlier plan to visit Schenker in Igls, see OJ 11/16, [11], August 2, 1932.  </tei:note> zu besuchen, konnte ich leider nicht ausführen, weil ich in letzter Stunde, entgegen meinem Vorhaben, nicht in die Schweiz und daher auch nicht in Ihre Nähe gekommen bin. Ich fühlte mich auffallend wenig wohl längere Zeit hindurch (Schlaflosigkeit) und mußte mich entschließen, die von meinen Ferien noch übrigbleibende Zeit zu Kuren zu verwenden, die schließlich darin endeten, daß ich [<tei:hi rend="italic">deletion</tei:hi>] nach einiger Zeit zu guterletzt nach <tei:hi rend="italic"><tei:hi rend="italic">Wien</tei:hi></tei:hi> ins <tei:hi rend="italic">Cottage</tei:hi>-<tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> Sanatorium<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  The Cottage Sanatorium, Vienna XVIII, Sternwartestrasse 74, where Anthony van Hoboken was to stay eight months later (OJ 5/18, 30, June 11, 1933).  </tei:note> gegangen bin, um mich nach allen Regeln der Kunst und dem neuesten Stande der medizin. Wissenschaft untersuchen zu lassen. Man fand nicht viel, erklärte mich für einen sehr „leichten“ Fall: Trotzdem bereue ich diesen Aufenthalt weniger als schon manchen früheren in <tei:hi rend="italic">Wien</tei:hi>; ich befinde mich jetzt wieder wohl und arbeitskräftig.</tei:p><tei:p>Daß ich Sie nicht gesehen habe, ist mir sehr leid. Ich hoffe, daß Sie mit Ihrer Erholung  zufrieden sind, und hoffe Sie bei meinem nächsten Aufenthalt in <tei:hi rend="italic">Wien</tei:hi> wieder wie das letztemal besuchen zu dürfen. Ich werde übrigens im kommenden Winter öfters nach <tei:hi rend="italic">Wien</tei:hi> kommen, u. a. zu dem <tei:hi rend="italic">Brahms</tei:hi>-Fest der ^Deutschen^ <tei:hi rend="italic">Brahms</tei:hi>-Gesellschaft<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4"> The Deutsche Brahms-Gesellschaft had been founded in Berlin in 1906.  On the festival, see Schenker’s diary entries of May 16 and 20, 1933 (OJ 4/6, pp. 3833–34, 3835);  Furtwängler gave the ceremonial address himself;  for the text of this, click on &lt;a href="../../../../../article/furtwangler_brahms.html"&gt;Furtwängler:Brahms&lt;/a&gt;.   </tei:note>.  Wissen Sie jemanden, der anläßlich dieses Festes den Fest-Vortrag halten kann? (Oder würden Sie <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> gar selber so etwas tun wollen?)<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  Schenker evidently took this suggestion seriously, as can be seen from the diary entry recording this letter, and also diary entries &lt;a href="../../../../../diary/oj<tei:hi rend="italic">45</tei:hi>3777<tei:hi rend="italic">92632.html"&gt;OJ 4/5, p. 3777, September 26&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href="../../../../../diary/oj</tei:hi>46<tei:hi rend="italic">p</tei:hi>3281_10432.html"&gt;OJ 4/6, p. 3281, October 4, 1932&lt;/a&gt;.  </tei:note> [<tei:hi rend="italic">two words deleted</tei:hi>]</tei:p><tei:p>Mit vielen guten und herzlichen Wünschen, und der Bitte mich auch Ihrer Frau<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  Click on <ref cRef="schenker_jeanette">Jeanette Schenker</ref>.  </tei:note> bestens zu empfehlen, bin ich</tei:p><tei:p>Ihr ergebener
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] Wilhelm Furtwängler</tei:p><tei:p>Ich bitte Sie, die Güte zu haben, beiliegenden Brief an den Adressaten<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7">  The letter to be forwarded was to Hans Weisse: see diary entry OJ 4/5, p. 3776.</tei:note>, dessen gegenwärtige Adresse mir unbekannt ist, weiterleiten zu wollen. Besten Dank im Voraus!</tei:p><tei:p>Wie geht es Ihren Arbeiten?</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Furtwängler to Schenker, dated September 22, 1932</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>September 22, 1932  Berlin<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/></tei:p><tei:p>Dear, honored Dr. Schenker,</tei:p><tei:p>Sadly, I was unable to execute my plan to visit you in Igls<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> during the course of the summer, because at the last moment, contrary to my intentions, I failed to get to Switzerland, nor, thus, [was I] ever within reach of you.  I had been feeling surprisingly less than well for a good while (insomnia), and was obliged to resolve to spend the remainder of my vacation undergoing treatment, the upshot of which was that shortly afterwards I finally went into the Cottage <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> Sanatorium<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> in <tei:hi rend="italic">Vienna</tei:hi> to have a thorough-going check-up according to the very latest of medical science.  They did not find much, and proclaimed me a very "mild" case.  Nevertheless, I regret this sojourn in Vienna less than many earlier ones;  I am now feeling well and ready for work again.</tei:p><tei:p>I am very sorry not to have seen you.  I hope you are pleased with your vacation, and I hope to be able to pay you a visit again during my next stay in Vienna, as last time.  I will at any rate be in Vienna frequently during the coming winter, among other reasons for the Brahms Festival of the German Brahms Society.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/>  Do you know of anyone who can give the ceremonial address on the occasion of this Festival?  (Or would you care to do so <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> yourself?<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/>)</tei:p><tei:p>With cordial best wishes;  in asking you to remember me to your wife,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/> I remain,</tei:p><tei:p>Yours truly, 
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] Wilhelm Furtwängler</tei:p><tei:p>[P.S.]  Please be so kind as to forward the enclosed letter to its addressee,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/> whose present address is unknown to me.  My thanks in anticipation!</tei:p><tei:p>[P.P.S.]  How is your work going?</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>