<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 11/16, [7] : 8-30-29 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© Heirs of Wilhelm Furtwängler, published with kind permission.
© Transcription Christoph Hust, 2008.
© Translation Ian Bent, 2008
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary Christoph Hust, 2008
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>Heirs of Wilhelm Furtwängler, permission to publish granted on February 2, 2005.  Any claim to intellectual rights on this document should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1929-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935- c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1955) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1955-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: Heirs of Wilhelm Furtwängler;  Image: University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: Christoph Hust; Translation: Ian Bent.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 08/30/1929 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: &quot;Furtw&#195;&#164;ngler ~ H+JSchenker&quot;,&quot;Furtw&#195;&#164;ngler ~ HSchenker&quot; --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Furtwängler to Schenker, dated August 30, 1929</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2008-03-11</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Furtwängler acknowledges a [non-extant] letter from Schenker, assures the latter that he has recommended him as much as he could, and regrets that no regular appointment has materialized for him;  he rejoices at the prospect of a monograph on the Eroica Symphony;  regrets that he has not seen Schenker recently, and intends to do so in the coming Fall.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Furtwängler, Wilhelm;  Schenker, Heinrich;  Curtius, Ludwig Michael;  Heidelberg;  Vienna;  concerts;  Hotel Imperial;  Schenker, Jeanette</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  St. Moritz (Engadin)</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Furtwängler to Schenker, dated August 30, 1929</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>30. VIII 1929  St. Moritz (Engadin)</tei:p><tei:p>Sehr verehrter Herr Schenker,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1"> Transcribed in Federhofer, <tei:hi rend="italic">Heinrich Schenker nach Tagebüchern und Briefen</tei:hi> (Hildesheim:  Georg Olms Verlag, 1985), p. 120.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Ich freue mich sehr, so überraschenderweise von Ihnen zu hören.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  The letter referred to here is not known to survive.  It is noteworthy that Furtwängler jotted down points at the head of Sbb 55 Nachl 13, [2], July 3, 1927:  while two of those points (Curtius; Beethoven) relate to the present letter, the other (Straube) does not.  </tei:note> Über die Heidelberger Geschichte<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  Perhaps Schenker had hoped, with Furtwängler's help, to procure a regular appointment in Heidelberg, but had been disappointed.  </tei:note> werden Sie ja wohl von Prof. Curtius<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  Probably Ludwig Michael Curtius who had been teaching in Heidelberg since 1920.</tei:note> mehr und Genaueres gehört haben, als ich Ihnen sagen kann. Ich habe Sie hier, wie auch an andern  Orten, so wie [ich] es nach meiner Einsicht für meine Pflicht halte, empfohlen. Daß es niemals zu einem realen Antrag an Sie kam, habe ich stets sehr bedauert;  ob Sie es denn angenommen hätten, und eine feste Stellung Ihrem freien Schriftstellerdasein vorgezogen hätten, wäre Ihre Sache gewesen, zu entscheiden.  Jedenfalls ist sicher, daß Sie auch so sich und der großen Sache, die Sie vertreten, Gehör verschaffen werden.</tei:p><tei:p>Auf eine Monographie der <tei:hi rend="italic">Eroica</tei:hi> haben wir alle Grund, uns zu freuen.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5"> The essay “Beethovens Dritte Sinfonie zum erstenmal in ihrem wahren Inhalt dargestellt,“ <tei:hi rend="italic">Das Meisterwerk in der Musik</tei:hi>, vol. III (Munich: Drei Masken Verlag, 1930), pp. 25–101 and graphs, Eng. trans. by Derrick Puffett and Alfred Clayton in <tei:hi rend="italic">The Masterwork in Music</tei:hi>, vol. III (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1997), pp. 10–68 and graphs.</tei:note>  Mir tut es leid, daß Sie manchmal Schwierigkeiten hatten um meine Wiener Konzerte – die ich jedenfalls nächstes <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> Jahr noch durchführe – zu hören. Ich wußte übrigens garnicht, daß Sie überhaupt mit einer gewissen Regelmäßigkeit Konzerte hören. Ich habe es während des ganzen Winters vermißt, nicht mit Ihnen zusammen zu kommen, und werde mich diesmal, sobald ich Zeit habe, bestimmt bei Ihnen melden.  (Ich wohnte das ganze Jahr über im Hotel Imperial,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6"> Hotel Imperial in the Ringstraße was Furtwängler's favorite hotel in Vienna.</tei:note> und werde es zunächst auch so weiter halten). So darf ich sagen, auf Wiedersehen im Herbst!  Mit den besten Grüßen, auch an Ihre verehrte Gattin<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7">  Click on <ref cRef="schenker_jeanette">Jeanette Schenker</ref>.</tei:note> und von der meinen, bin ich</tei:p><tei:p>herzlichst
Ihr
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] Wilhelm Furtwängler</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Furtwängler to Schenker, dated August 30, 1929</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>August 30, 1929     St. Moritz (Engadin)</tei:p><tei:p>Dear Mr. Schenker,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/></tei:p><tei:p>I am delighted to hear from you so unexpectedly.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/>  You will no doubt have heard more, and in greater detail than I can say, from Professor Curtius<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> on the Heidelberg story.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/>  I have recommended you here, as also elsewhere, as much as in my judgement I consider it my duty.  That nothing positive has ever materialized for you has been a constant source of great regret to me.  Whether you would then have accepted it, and would have preferred a regular position to your free existence as a writer would have been a matter for you to decide.  At any rate, it is certain that by those means you will obtain a hearing both for yourself and for the great cause that you represent.</tei:p><tei:p>We all of us have good reason to rejoice at a monograph on the <tei:hi rend="italic">Eroica</tei:hi> [Symphony].<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/>  I am sorry to hear that you have sometimes had difficulties over my Vienna concerts—which at any rate I shall still be doing next <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> year.  By the way, I had no idea whatsoever that you attend concerts with any degree of regularity.  I have missed getting together with you throughout the whole winter, and this time shall, as soon as I have time, definitely get in contact with you.  (I have stayed the whole year round at the Hotel Imperial,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/> and shall for the time being continue to do so.)  So perhaps I can say "until we meet" in the Fall!  With warmest greetings, and to your wife<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/> as well, and from mine.  I remain</tei:p><tei:p>Cordially,
Yours,
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>]  Wilhelm Furtwängler</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>