<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 9/31, [13] : 10-2-06 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© Heirs of Heinrich Schenker; reproduced here by kind permission of the Deutsches Literaturarchiv, Cotta-Archiv (Stiftung der Stuttgarter Zeitung), Marbach am Neckar.
© Transcription Ian D. Bent 2005.
© Translation Ian D. Bent 2005.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary Ian D. Bent 2005
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>Permission granted by the Cotta Archiv of the Schiller-Nationalmuseum/Deutsches Literaturarchiv, 07-20-05</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance> Schenker, Heinrich (1906-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1955) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1955-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: In public domain; reproduced here by kind permission of the Deutsches Literaturarchiv, Cotta-Archiv (Stiftung der Stuttgarter Zeitung), Marbach am Neckar; Image: University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: Ian D. Bent.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 10/02/1906 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Cotta ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Cotta to Schenker, dated October 2, 1906</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2005-06-10</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>[NMTP = Harmonielehre:] Acknowledges CA 41-42; if the Afterword is to be incorporated into the volume it must be shortened, or sales will be exacerbated; late delivery would risk the book's being lost sight of in the Christmas book sales.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Cotta, J. G.; Schenker, Heinrich;  NMTP; Harmonielehre; Theory of Harmony; Afterword; Niedergang; retail price; marketing; Christmas; Easter book fair; deadlines</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN"> Stuttgart and Berlin</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN"> Vienna</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Cotta to Schenker, dated October 2, 1906</tei:hi>
<tei:hi rend="bold">= CA 43</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  = Cotta's carbon copy, with "5/544" written in crayon top center, not in Schenker's hand.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">Cotta letterhead</tei:hi>]
STUTTGART, den 2. Oktober 1906.</tei:p><tei:p>Herrn <tei:hi rend="italic">Dr. Heinrich Schenker</tei:hi>,
<tei:hi rend="italic"><tei:hi rend="italic">Wien.</tei:hi></tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Sehr geehrter Herr!</tei:p><tei:p>Ihrem gefl. Briefe vom 1. d. M. haben wir entnommen, daß Sie das Nachwort in unmittelbarem Anschluß an das Hauptwerk “Theorien und Phantasien” und in einem Band mit diesem veröffentlichen wollen.  Wir gestatten uns aus diesem Anlaß, unsere Bitte vom 31. <tei:hi rend="italic">Mai</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  = OJ 9/31, [8] = CA 26.</tei:note> zu wiederholen : den Umfang des Nachwortes nach Möglichkeit einzuschränken, nicht sowohl um durch einen erträglichen Preis den Absatz nicht zu erschweren – als vielmehr auch im Interesse der rechtzeitigen Fertigstellung vor Weihnachten.  Namentlich  der letzten Grund ist inzwischen noch zwingender geworden !  Wenn wir dem Buche den Antragung <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> in der Flut der Weihnachts-Geschenkliteratur ersparen wollen, so muß es in der ersten Novemberwoche versandt werden.  Alsdann ist es Mitte November in den Händen der Sortimentsbuchhändler und kann gerade noch vor Einsetzen des Weihnachtsgeschäftes den Interessanten zugänglich gemacht werden.  Was von wissenschaftlichen Novitäten Ende November oder gar erst im Dezember herauskommt, bleibt in der Mehrzahl der Sortimentsgeschäfte unbeachtet bis nach Weihnachten liegen und tritt, da kurz nach Weihnachten schon die Vorbereitungen für die bevorstehende Ostermeß-Abrechnung beginnen, mitunter schon zur nächsten Messe den Rückweg zum Verleger an.</tei:p><tei:p>Wir bitten Sie überzeugt zu sein, daß unser Drängen nur in der Absicht erfolgt, den Interessen des Buches, soweit dies in unserer Macht liegt, zu dienen.  Wir geben uns der Hoffnung hin, gemäß Ihrem gefl. Briefe, das noch fehlende <tei:hi rend="italic">Manuscript</tei:hi> in aller Kürze zu erhalten und zeichnen</tei:p><tei:p>mit vorzüglicher Hochachtung
Ihr ergebenen
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] J. G. Cottasche Buchhandlung Nachf.</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Cotta to Schenker, dated October 2, 1906</tei:hi>
<tei:hi rend="bold">= CA 43</tei:hi>|<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">Cotta letterhead</tei:hi>]
STUTTGART, October 2, 1906</tei:p><tei:p>Dr.  Heinrich  Schenker,      
<tei:hi rend="italic">Vienna</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Dear Sir,</tei:p><tei:p>From your est’d letter of the 1st inst we understand that you wish your Afterword to be published directly in conjunction with the main work, <tei:hi rend="italic">Theories and Fantasies</tei:hi>, and in one volume with the latter. Permit us to take this opportunity of repeating our request of May 31:<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> to restrict the extent of the Afterword as far as possible, not only so as not to exacerbate sales by necessitating an intolerable price, but also in the interests of completion well before Christmas.  The latter reason in particular has in the meantime become still more urgent!  If we wish to spare the book from being submerged <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> in the flood of literary Christmas gift-items, then it must be sent in the first week of November.  That way, it reaches the retail booksellers in mid-November and can be made available to interested readers just before the onslaught of the Christmas trade. Any new scholarly items that appear at the end of November or even as late as December, languish unnoticed in the majority of the retail stores until after Christmas, and, since shortly after Christmas we begin the run-up to the impending Easter book fair accounting, may at the next fair be returned to the publisher.</tei:p><tei:p>Rest assured that our urgings are made solely with a view to serving the interests of your book to the full extent in our powers.  In accordance with your est’d letter, we hope to receive with all haste the manuscript still lacking, and remain</tei:p><tei:p>With kind regards,
Yours truly,
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] Heirs to J. G. Cotta’s Bookdealership</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>