<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 9/31, [23] : 6-1-09 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© In the public domain; reproduced here by kind permission of the Deutsches Literaturarchiv, Cotta-Archiv (Stiftung der Stuttgarter Zeitung), Marbach am Neckar.
© Transcription Ian D. Bent 2005.
© Translation Ian D. Bent 2005.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary Ian D. Bent 2005
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license> </dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance> Schenker, Heinrich (1909-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1955) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1955-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR:  In public domain, reproduced here with kind permission of the Deutsches Literaturarchiv Marbach, Cotta-Archiv (Stiftung der Stuttgarter Zeitung), Marbach am Neckar; Image: University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: Ian D. Bent.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 06/01/1909 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Cotta ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Cotta to Schenker, dated June 1, 1909</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2005-07-28</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>[ NMTP II/1 = Kontrapunkt I:] Acks CA 96-98, notes the adoption of Ornamentik at the Vienna Conservatory, and agrees to the publication of vol. II in two separate half-volumes; recommends a publication date of early October , proposes a deadline of August for submission of all material, and estimates the extent of the volume.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Cotta, J. G.; Schenker, Heinrich;  NMTP; vol.II; Kontrapunkt; Counterpoint; division; half-volumes; installments; publication date; deadline; extent; Neue Freie Presse</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  Stuttgart</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN"> Vienna III, Reisnerstraße 38</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Cotta to Schenker, dated June 1, 1909</tei:hi>
<tei:hi rend="bold">= CA 99–101</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  i.e. Cotta’s carbon copy.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>[Cotta letterhead]
STUTTGART, den 1. Juni 1909</tei:p><tei:p>Herrn  
<tei:hi rend="italic">Dr.  Heinrich  Schenker</tei:hi>
<tei:hi rend="italic"><tei:hi rend="italic">Wien. III</tei:hi></tei:hi>
Reisnerstr. 38</tei:p><tei:p>Sehr geehrter Herr Doktor!</tei:p><tei:p>Wir empfingen Ihren gef. Brief vom 26. d.M.,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  CA 96–98.</tei:note> von dessen Inhalt wir mit Interesse Kenntnis genommen haben.  Zu der Anerkennung, die Ihrem Werke “Ein Beitrag zur Ornamentik” durch die Aufnahme in den Lehrplan der K. K. Akademie für Musik in Wien<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  i.e. the Vienna Conservatory of Music, newly reconstituted as a state institution: see WSLB 31 (December 22, 1908), in which, in declining an invitation to edit Book II of the <tei:hi rend="italic">Well-tempered Clavier</tei:hi> for use at the Academy, S remarks: “It is with [vol. II] that I hope to do a sufficiently great service to the teachers and students even of our Academy ...”</tei:note> zu Teil geworden ist, verfehlen wir nicht, Ihnen unsern besten Glückwunsch auszusprechen.</tei:p><tei:p>Freudig würden wir es begrüßen, wenn das gesteigerte Interesse, welches sich für Ihr Wirken und Ihre Werke bekundet, durch den ”Neuen musikalischen Theorien und Phantasien” <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> zu Gute kommen würde und wir sind gerne bereit, soweit es uns möglich ist, die nach Ihrer Darstellung gegenwärtig besonders günstige Konjunktur auszunutzen.</tei:p><tei:p>Deshalb und weil wir mit Ihnen der Ansicht sind, daß es möglichst vermieden werden sollte, einen allzu starken und demgemäß teuren zweiten Band herauszubringen, haben wir uns dafür entschieden, Ihrem Vorschlag der Teilung dieses Bandes in zwei Halbbände zuzustimmen.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  Cotta had previously advised against this in OJ 12/27, [9] = CA 86, October 9, 1908; S touched on the matter again in CA 87, October 13, 1908, to which Cotta replied in OJ 9/31, [20] = CA 88, October 15, 1908, confirming that the work would be published as a single volume.</tei:note>  Von einer Ausgabe in vier Lieferungen möchten wir dagegen nach eingehender Überlegung entschieden abraten.</tei:p><tei:p>Als günstigsten Zeitpunkt für das Erscheinen des ersten Halbbandes würden wir den Herbst d.J., etwa die erste Oktoberhälfte, erachten. Um dieses Ziel zu erreichen, müßten wir allerdings bis Ende August im Besitz des gesamten <tei:hi rend="italic">Druck-</tei:hi><tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi><tei:hi rend="italic">fertigen</tei:hi> Materials für diesen Halbband sein.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  We know that Sections 1 and 2 of <tei:hi rend="italic">Kontrapunkt</tei:hi> I were in Cotta’s hands by October 15, 1908 (OJ 9/31, [20]), S having indicated on April 24, 1908 that delivery of his materials was imminent (letter cited in OJ 9/31, [18], April 25, 1908).  S himself says that he was “forced to break off work on completion of vol. II” in his letters to Hertzka, WSLB 8 (June 16, 1908) and WSLB 9 (June 23, 1908), but whether this was Sections 1 and 2, or whether the continuation of those, is unclear.  It is in any case likely that Cotta had materials by October 9, to judge from discussion of the details of publication in two non-surviving letters of October 9, 1908 (H–S) and October 13, 1908 (S–H) cited in the October 15 letter.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Das der Druckerei bis jetzt vorliegende Material wird von derselben auf <tei:hi rend="italic">ca</tei:hi> 25 Druckbogen geschätzt, von denen indes erst 9 gedruckt. bezw. druckfertig sind.  Inwieweit noch eine Vermehrung dieser Bogenzahl durch Einfügung von Notenbeispielen eintreten wird, vermögen wir nicht zu beurteilen, indes nehmen wir an, daß weiteres Text-Manuskript für diesen Teil nicht hinzukommt.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  <tei:hi rend="italic">NMTP</tei:hi> II/1, as eventually published, comprises 28 gatherings + 2 ½ gatherings of prelims.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Wir hoffen, daß es Ihnen möglich sein wird, Ihre Arbeit an dem Werke so zu fördern, daß der vorgenannte zweckmäßige Erscheinungstermin für den ^ersten^ Halbband eingehalten werden kann und zeichnen, Ihren geschätzten Nach-<tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi>richten gern entgegensehend</tei:p><tei:p>in vorzüglicher Hochachtung
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] J.G. Cotta’sche Buchhdlg.Nachf.</tei:p><tei:p>P.S.  Den freundl. eingesandten Ausschnitt aus der <tei:hi rend="italic">Neuen Freien Presse</tei:hi> fügen wir mit verbindlichem Danke hier wieder bei.</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Cotta to Schenker, dated June 1, 1909</tei:hi>
<tei:hi rend="bold">= CA 99–101</tei:hi>|<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/></tei:p><tei:p>[Cotta letterhead]
STUTTGART, June 1, 1909</tei:p><tei:p>Dr. Heinrich Schenker 
<tei:hi rend="italic">Vienna,  III</tei:hi>
Reisnerstr. 38</tei:p><tei:p>Dear Doctor,</tei:p><tei:p>We are in receipt of your est’d letter of the 26th of [last] month,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> and have noted with interest its contents.  We hasten to offer you our warmest congratulations on the recognition that has been accorded your work <tei:hi rend="italic">Ein Beitrag zur Ornamentik</tei:hi>, in part through its adoption in the syllabus of the Imperial- Royal Academy for Music in Vienna.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/></tei:p><tei:p>We would welcome it with open arms if the increased interest that is being shown in your activities and [published] works <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> were to benefit your <tei:hi rend="italic">New Musical Theories and Fantasies</tei:hi>, and we will be glad insofar as is possible to capitalize on what you portray as the present especially propitious business outlook.</tei:p><tei:p>For this reason, and because we share your view that publishing an excessively large and correspondingly expensive vol. II should if at all possible be avoided, we have decided to agree to your proposal that the volume be divided into two half-volumes.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> After careful deliberation, we should like to advise strongly against publication in four installments.</tei:p><tei:p>We would consider the Autumn of this year, perhaps the first half of October, the optimum time for the appearance of the first half-volume.  In order to meet this goal, we would certainly have to have all the <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> material in our hands and <tei:hi rend="italic">ready for printing</tei:hi> by the end of August.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/></tei:p><tei:p>The material already on hand at the printers is estimated by the latter at ca. 25 print-gatherings, of which nine are already printed, or are print-ready.  We are not in a position to judge how great an increase in this gathering count will be incurred by the interpolation of music examples; but we assume that no additional text manuscript will be forthcoming for this Part.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/></tei:p><tei:p>We hope it will be possible for you to expedite your work on this book so that the scheduled deadline given above for publication for the ^first^ half-volume can be adhered to; and, <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> in looking forward keenly to your est’d response, we remain</tei:p><tei:p>With kind regards
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] Heirs of J.G. Cotta’s Bookdealership</tei:p><tei:p>P.S.  Enclosed, we return to you with thanks the cutting from the <tei:hi rend="italic">Neue Freie Presse</tei:hi> that you kindly sent.</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>