<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 9/31, [12] : 9-24-06 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© Heirs of Heinrich Schenker; reproduced here by kind permission of the Deutsches Literaturarchiv, Cotta-Archiv (Stiftung der Stuttgarter Zeitung), Marbach am Neckar.
© Transcription Ian D. Bent 2005.
© Translation Ian D. Bent 2005.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary Ian D. Bent 2005
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>Permission granted by the Cotta Archiv of the Schiller-Nationalmuseum/Deutsches Literaturarchiv, 07-20-05</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance> Schenker, Heinrich (1906-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1955) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1955-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: In public domain; reproduced here by kind permission of the Deutsches Literaturarchiv, Cotta-Archiv (Stiftung der Stuttgarter Zeitung), Marbach am Neckar; Image: University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: Ian D. Bent.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 09/24/1906 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Cotta ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Cotta to Schenker, dated September 24, 1906</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2005-06-07</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>[NMTTP I = Harmonielehre:] Urges return of gatherings 22-29; expresses concern that the book be released before Christmas; warns of overrun in costs to Schenker, and raising of retail price.  Asks for title-page and publicity copy.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Cotta, J. G.; Schenker, Heinrich;  NMTP; Harmonielehre; Theory of Harmony revised proofs; gatherings 22-29; publication date; costs; retail price; title-page; advertising copy; blurb</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN"> Stuttgart</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN"> Vienna</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Cotta to Schenker, dated September 24, 1906</tei:hi>
<tei:hi rend="bold">= CA 40</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  CA 40 = Cotta's carbon copy.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">Cotta letterhead</tei:hi>]
STUTTGART, den [<tei:hi rend="italic">handwritten:</tei:hi>] 24. Septemb 1906.</tei:p><tei:p>Herrn <tei:hi rend="italic">D&lt;sup&gt;r.&lt;/sup&gt; Heinrich Schenker</tei:hi>
<tei:hi rend="italic"><tei:hi rend="italic">Wien</tei:hi></tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Sehr geehrter Herr!</tei:p><tei:p>Anknüpfend zu unserem Brief vom <tei:hi rend="italic">30. August</tei:hi> gestatten wir uns heute, unsere damalige Bitte um beschleunigte Erledigung der Revisionen ergebenst zu wiederholen.  Sie sind augenblicklich noch im Besitz der Revisionsbogen 22–29 (Schluß),<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  gatherings 22–29 = pp.337 to [464] of the published book.</tei:note> die Sie  in der Zeit vom <tei:hi rend="italic">30. August</tei:hi> bis <tei:hi rend="italic">17. September</tei:hi> erhielten.  Da die Versendung und Erledigung der Superrevision<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  <tei:hi rend="italic">Superrevision</tei:hi>: presumably the proofs sent out in expectation of imprimatur; but it is clearly not a complete set submitted at a single time.</tei:note> ohnehin eine weitere Verzögerung verursacht, wäre es uns umsomehr erwunscht, möglichst umgehend in den Besitz der rückständigen Revisionen zu gelangen, damit wir Ihnen – soweit notwendig – baldigst Superrevision dieser Bogen zugehen lassen können.  Sehr angenehm wäre es uns allerdings, wenn Sie im Interesse des aüßerst <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> wunschenswerten baldigen Erscheinens, wenn irgend möglich, auf letztere verzichten könnten. Die Möglichkeit, das Buch noch in diesem Jahre rechtzeitig von Weihnachten herauszubringen wird anderenfalls ernstlich in Frage gestellt.</tei:p><tei:p>Wir halten uns ferner verpflichtet, Sie schon jetzt darauf aufmerksam zu machen, daß infolge des auf re. 29 Bogen erweiterten Umfanges, namentlich aber infolge der außergewöhnlich zahlreichen und umfangreichen Korrekturen, die stellenweise (wie in Bogen 21<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  gathering 21 = pp.321–336 of the published book.</tei:note>) einem Neusatz nahezu gleich kommen, die Ihnen 1. Zt. genannte Summe der von Ihnen zu erstattenden Kosten ganz erheblich überschritten wird.  Auch eine Erhöhung des ursprünglich beabsichtigten Preises ist unter diesen Umständen nicht zu vermeiden.</tei:p><tei:p>Noch bitten wir bei dieser Gelegenheit, uns auch das Manuscript zum Titelblatt baldgefl. einsenden zu wollen, sowie uns als Unterlage für die buchhändlerische Anzeige des Werkes einige den Inhalt desselben characterisierende Zeilen zur Verfügung zu stellen.</tei:p><tei:p>Mit vorzüglicher Hochachtung
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] J. G. Cottasche Buchhandlung Nachf.</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Cotta to Schenker, dated September 24, 1906</tei:hi>
<tei:hi rend="bold">= CA 40</tei:hi>|<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">Cotta letterhead</tei:hi>]
STUTTGART, [<tei:hi rend="italic">handwritten:</tei:hi>] September 24, 1906</tei:p><tei:p>Dr. Heinrich Schenker,      
<tei:hi rend="italic">Vienna</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Dear Sir,</tei:p><tei:p>Further to our letter of August 30, we take the liberty today most respectfully of repeating our request for expeditious handling of the revised proofs.  You currently still have in your possession revised proofs for gatherings 22–29 (end),<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> which you have retained throughout the period August 30 to September 17.  Since dispatching and dealing with the second revised proofs<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> in any case give rise to a further delay, it would be all the more desirable for us to have the overdue proofs back in our hands if at all possible by return, so that we can—insofar as necessary—have the second revised proofs of these gatherings sent to you as soon as possible.  It would in any case be very welcome to us if, in the interests of the extreme <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> desirability of the book’s appearing soon, you could, if at all possible, forgo the latter.  The feasibility of still releasing the book the right side of Christmas this year will otherwise be seriously called in question.</tei:p><tei:p>We are further obliged to draw to your attention at this point the fact that, in consequence of the increase in extent to 29 gatherings, but more particularly as a result of the extraordinarily numerous and extensive corrections that in places (e.g. in gathering 21<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/>) are tantamount to their having to be reset from scratch, the figure quoted to you in the initial allocation of the costs to be reimbursed by you will be quite considerably exceeded.  Moreover, an increase in the price originally envisioned is under these circumstances unavoidable.</tei:p><tei:p>We take this opportunity to ask you also please to send the manuscript of the title-page as soon as possible, and at the same time to supply us with a few lines characterizing the content of the work, to form the basis for the book’s announcement to the book trade.</tei:p><tei:p>With kind regards,
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] Heirs of J. G. Cotta’s Bookdealership</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>