<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 12/17, [1] : 9-20-23 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
©  Under inquiry
©  Transcription Michaela Searfoorce, 2008
©  Translation Michaela Searfoorce, 2008
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary Michaela Searfoorce 2008
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>Under inquiry.  Any claim to intellectual rights on this document should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1923-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1945) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1945-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: Under inquiry; Image: University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: Michaela Searfoorce.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 09/20/1923 03:02:58 PM --><!-- MT Tags: "Komorn ~ H+JSchenker","Komorn ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Komorn to Heinrich Schenker, dated September 20, 1923</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2009-01-31</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Komorn has spoken with Hans Weisse, thanks Schenker for taking her on as a pupil, asks for time to attend and choice of pieces.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Komorn, Maria; Schenker, Heinrich;  Weisse, Hans;  lessons;  Beethoven;  rondo;  Rameau;  gavotte;  variations</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN"> Vienna] IX, Bleichergasse 15 </marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Komorn to Heinrich Schenker, dated September 20, 1923</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Hochverehrter Herr Doktor,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  Receipt of this letter is recorded in Schenker's diary on September 21 (OJ 3/4, p. 2571).  </tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>unserer Vereinbarung gemäß teile ich Ihnen mit, dass ich mit D^r^ Weisse gesprochen habe.  Ich sagte ihm ganz gleicherweise wie Ihnen, dass der Grund, der mich bestimmte, Sie um Aufnahme zu bitten, <tei:hi rend="italic">nicht</tei:hi> der wäre, dass <tei:hi rend="italic">er</tei:hi> mir nicht gut genug ist, sondern dass ich die Überzeugung hätte, nur Sie könnten mir aus der rein klavieristisch-technischen Krise, in der ich mich gegenwärtig befinde, heraushelfen. Er freute sich sehr, dass mir die Möglichkeit gegeben ist, &lt;del&gt;nun&lt;/del&gt; bei Ihnen zu arbeiten<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  Schenker reports a conversation with Weisse in his diary for September 25 (OJ 3/4, p. 2574):  "he is offended at Mrs. Komorn's departure, feels 'relieved,' although neither he nor his wife planned to turn her away;  until 100,000 Kronen in fees [were paid], he had decided, despite disinclination, to keep her on.  That at least is true.  He asks me why I am taking her on.  I answer that I had no prima facie reason to deny her instruction just so long as she set squared the matter with him [...]."    (er ist über den Abgang der Frau Komorn beleidigt, fühlt sich „erlöst", obgleich weder er noch seine Frau vor hatten, sie wegzuschicken, bis 100000 Kronen Honorar war er sie trotz Abneigung zu behalten entschlossen.  Das allein ist richtig.  Er fragt micht, warum ich sie annehme?  Ich gab zur Antwort, daß ich keinen Grund hatte, gerade ihr den Unterricht zu verweigern, sofern sie nur die Angelegenheit mit ihm in Ordnung gebracht hat [...])</tei:note> und ich bitte Sie nun recht sehr um die Güte, mir die Stunde bekannt zu geben, wann ich das erste Mal zu kommen habe.  Alles Nähere werde ich Ihnen auf Ihr Befragen jederzeit mündlich sagen.</tei:p><tei:p>Sehr dankbar wäre ich, wenn Sie die Liebenswürdigkeit hätten, mir 2 oder 3 nicht zu große Stücke zu nennen, die ich mir <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> unterdessen besorgen, ein wenig ansehen und eines davon auswählen und mitbringen könnte.  Mir wäre am liebsten etwas, was inhaltlich schön und gleichzeitig für mich technisch günstig &lt;sup&gt;&lt;!--add--&gt;wäre&lt;/sup&gt;, etwa &lt;del&gt;des&lt;/del&gt; &lt;sup&gt;&lt;!--add--&gt;in der Art&lt;/sup&gt; des Rondos über den velorenen Groschen,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  Beethoven: Rondo a capriccioso "Rage over a Lost Penny," Op. 129.  Komorn is not recorded as playing this work in the first season, but is at her lesson on November 3, 1924.</tei:note> der Gavotte mit Variationen von Rameau oder derlei.  Aber das überlasse ich natürlich vollkommen Ihrer Bestimmung, da ich ja viel zu wenig an Literatur kenne.</tei:p><tei:p>Indem ich Ihnen, sehr verehrter Herr Doktor[,] meinen aufrichtigen Dank für Ihre Bereitwilligkeit, mich zu unterrichten, ausspreche, bin ich mit den besten Empfehlungen an Sie und die verehrte gnädige Frau</tei:p><tei:p>Ihre wahrhaft ergebene
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] Maria Komorn</tei:p><tei:p>20. 9. 23			
IX Bleichergasse 15
Telefon 5014/VIII</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Komorn to Heinrich Schenker, dated September 20, 1923</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Dear Dr. [Schenker],<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/></tei:p><tei:p>I wish to inform you in accordance with our agreement that I have spoken with Dr. Weisse.  I told him, exactly as you did, that the reason why I decided to ask you to take me on was <tei:hi rend="italic">not</tei:hi> that <tei:hi rend="italic">he</tei:hi> is not good enough, but rather that I was convinced that you alone were able to help me out of the purely pianistic-technical crisis in which I currently find myself. He was delighted that I had been given the opportunity to work with you.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/>  Please now be so very kind as to notify me of the hour at which I have to come for the first time.  I will tell you all the details that you wish to know in person then.</tei:p><tei:p>I should be very grateful if you would be so kind as to identify two or three not too large pieces to me that I <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> could procure for myself in the meantime, look at a little, and select one of them and bring along. Preferable to me would be something beautiful in content and at the same time technically favorable for me, for instance &lt;sup&gt;&lt;!--add--&gt;of the sort&lt;/sup&gt; of the rondo over the lost penny,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> the gavotte with variations by Rameau, or the like.  But naturally I leave this completely up to you, since I after all know much too little about repertory.</tei:p><tei:p>In expressing to you, dear Dr. [Schenker], my sincere thanks for your willingness to teach me, I am, with the best regards to you and your very dear wife,</tei:p><tei:p>Your truly devoted
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] Maria Komorn</tei:p><tei:p>September 20, 1923
[Vienna] IX, Bleichergasse 15
Telephone 5014/VIII</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>