<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 11/29, [5] : 12-1-10 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© Published by kind permission of the heirs of Karl Grunsky. 
© Transcription Lee Rothfarb 2007.
© Translation Lee Rothfarb 2007.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary Lee Rothfarb, 2007.
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license> This document is published with the permission of the heirs of Karl Grunsky, March 8, 2007.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1910-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1945) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1945-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: Heirs of Karl Grunsky; Image: University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: Lee Rothfarb.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 12/01/1910 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Grunsky ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Grunsky to Schenker, dated December 1, 1910</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2007-03-18</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Acks receipt of S's edition of Bach's Chromatic Fantasy &amp; Fugue and comments;  would like to discuss his forthcoming book on piano technique with S. —Criticizes S's use of polemic.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Grunsky, Karl; Schenker, Heinrich;  Bach, J. S.;  Chromatic Fantasy &amp; Fugue;  pedagogy;  Beethoven;  Stuttgart;  piano technique;  Technik des Klavier-Auszugs, Die;  Polemik;  polemics</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  Stuttgart, Stitzenburgstrasse i/I</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Grunsky to Schenker, dated December 1, 1910</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Stuttgart, d. 1. Dez. [/] 1910
Stitzenburgstr. i^I^</tei:p><tei:p>Verehrter Herr Doctor!</tei:p><tei:p>Es drängt noch, Ihnen für den Bach<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  S’s edition of J. S. Bach’s <tei:hi rend="italic">Chromatic Fantasy &amp; Fuge</tei:hi> was received from the printers on October 21, 1910, and G was included in S’s list of recipients of complimentary and review copies (&lt;a href="../../../../../schenker/correspondence/wslb<tei:hi rend="italic">6667</tei:hi>101910.html"&gt;WSLB 66/67&lt;/a&gt;, October 19, 1910), the mailing out of copies taking place around October 28 (&lt;a href="../../../../../schenker/correspondence/oc<tei:hi rend="italic">5259</tei:hi>102810.html"&gt;OC 52/59&lt;/a&gt;).  </tei:note> besonders zu danken.  Ich werde auf ihn aufmerksam machen, im Unterricht, und wo ich nur kann.  Ihre Bemerkungen erquicken und belehren!  S. 41 unten<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  “Die meiste Schuld daran tragen ohne Zweifel neben den durchaus mangelhaften Lehrbüchern die unzulänglichen Lehrer:  selbst nur ein Minimum an Durchempfindung und künstlerischer Erkenntnis besitzend, begehen sie an der Jugend ein schweres Verbrechen, indem sie gerade nur dieses Minimum fortgeben und fortpflanzen.” (“Incompetent teachers undoubtedly share the blame with altogether deficient textbooks.  Such teachers, themselves possessing minimal insight and minimal artistic perception, do the younger generation a grave injustice by imparting and implanting only this bare minimum.” – Eng. trans. Hedi Siegel, <tei:hi rend="italic">J. S. Bach’s Chromatic Fantasy and Fugue</tei:hi> (New York: Longman, 1969), p. 61.)</tei:note> – da musste ich laut lachen. Ich dachte daran, wie vom hiesigen grossen Klaviervirtuosen einer zu mir sagte: er vermeide Beethoven im Unterricht aus pädagogischen Gründen!  Glückliches Stuttgart!</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> Hinsichtlich der Klaviertechnik wäre ich sehr glücklich, Ihnen meine Technik auseinandersetzten zu dürfen.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  Presumably G’s forthcoming <tei:hi rend="italic">Die Technik des Klavier-Auszugs entwickelt am 3. Akt von Wagners „Tristan“</tei:hi> (Leipzig: Breitkopf &amp; Härtel, 1911).  Many years later (1934), G published a small book entitled <tei:hi rend="italic">Musikalische Erziehung am Klavier</tei:hi> (Esslingen: Burgbücherei).</tei:note>  Aber das könnte nur persönlich geschehen.  Kommen Sie nicht vielleicht nach Stuttgart?</tei:p><tei:p>Darf ich eine kritische Bermerkung machen, so möchte ich nicht verfehlen ein gewisses Übermaass an Polemik zu tadeln.  Ruhiger Vortrag des Sachlichen genügt:  die polemische Gesinnung muss das +Ergebnis+ beim Leser sein!  Zuviel Absicht schadet.  An sich ist ja Ihre Polemik durchaus berechtigt.</tei:p><tei:p>Mit bestem Grusse
Ihr ergebener + dankbarer
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] K. Grunsky.</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Grunsky to Schenker, dated December 1, 1910</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Stuttgart, December 1, 1910
Stitzenburgstrasse i/I</tei:p><tei:p>Dear Doctor,</tei:p><tei:p>I must yet thank you especially for the Bach.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/>  I will refer to it in teaching and wherever I can.  Your comments refresh and instruct!  Page 41, at the bottom<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/>—I had to laugh out loud at that point.  I thought of how one of the local piano virtuosos told me that he avoids Beethoven in teaching for pedagogical reasons!  Lucky Stuttgart!</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> With regard to piano technique, I would be very happy to be able to discuss my <tei:hi rend="italic">Technique</tei:hi> with you.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/>  But that could happen only in person.  Are you perhaps coming to Stuttgart?</tei:p><tei:p>If I may make a critical comment, I don’t want to miss faulting a certain excess of polemics.  An even-tempered presentation of the objective is sufficient:  a polemical attitude must be the +result+ on the reader’s part!  Too much deliberateness inflicts damage.  In itself, your polemics are absolutely justified.</tei:p><tei:p>With best wishes, 
Yours truly and thankfully,
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] K. Grunsky</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>