<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 11/29, [1] : 5-3-08 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© Published by kind permission of the heirs of Karl Grunsky. 
© Transcription Lee Rothfarb 2007.
© Translation Lee Rothfarb 2007.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary Lee Rothfarb, 2007.
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license> This document is published with the permission of the heirs of Karl Grunsky, March 8, 2007.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1908-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1945) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1945-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: Heirs of Karl Grunsky; Image: University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: Lee Rothfarb.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 05/03/1908 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Grunsky ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Grunsky to Schenker, dated May 3, 1908</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2007-03-13</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Acks letter;  thanks S for divulging his authorship of Harmonielehre;  enlarges on his objection to undue citation of piano repertory;  asks S's views on Bruckner.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Grunsky, Karl; Schenker, Heinrich;  Harmonielehre;  review;  piano repertory;  orchestral repertory;  chamber music repertory;  Bruckner</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  Stuttgart, Stitzenburgstrasse i/I</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Grunsky to Schenker, dated May 3, 1908</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Stuttgart, d. 3. Mai 1908
Stitzenburgstr i^I^</tei:p><tei:p>Hochgeehrter Herr Doctor,</tei:p><tei:p>Verzeihen Sie, dass ich bis jetzt so taub geblieben bin, da Sie mich doch durch Lüftung Ihres Incognitos<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  Presumably the identification was given by Cotta, since it does not occur in any surviving draft letter from S.  The titlepage of the first edition of S’s <tei:hi rend="italic">Harmonielehre</tei:hi> (Stuttgart: J. G. Cotta, 1906) identifies authorship merely as „von einem Künstler.“  As early as January 7, 1907, Cotta asked if they might divulge his name, and S forbade it “for the time being” (OJ 12/27, <tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  Karl Grunsky, <tei:hi rend="italic">Musikästhetik</tei:hi> (G.J. Göschen, 1907).</tei:note>; CA 64, January 8, 1907).  On December 12, 1907, Cotta forwarded to S a letter from G envisaging a review in the <tei:hi rend="italic">Schwäbischer Merkur</tei:hi>, and inquiring the name of the author (OJ 12/27, [10]);   recorded his suspicions as to G’s motives in his diary (OJ 1/5, pp. 53–54, December 13).  On December 16, S wrote to Cotta still withholding permission but stating “I have really come to value the seriousness of his works, the bulk of which I believe I know,” and instructing them to ask G to be patient a while longer (CA 71; OJ 9/31, [17], December 18).  S recorded receipt of G’s review in his diary on January 6, 1908 (OJ 1/7, p. 58).  There are no diary entries between April 8 and June 30, so no further information is available leading up to the present letter.  On June 2, Cotta asked whether they might reveal his name to Rudolf Breithausen, and S agreed to make his name public, stating his intention to place his name on the titlepage of <tei:hi rend="italic">Kontrapunkt</tei:hi> (OJ 9/31, [19] = CA 78; CA 79, June 5).    </tei:note> [<tei:hi rend="italic">cued from left margin:</tei:hi> das ich natürlich streng aufbewahre] und durch Ihren freundlichen Brief<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  Possibly the finished letter of which OJ 5/15, [1] is the draft.</tei:note> sehr zu Dank verpflichtet haben. Auch heute bin ich leider nicht in der Lage, Ihnen ausführlich zu erwidern.   <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi>  Ich habe für Göschen eine 2. Auflage meiner Musikgeschichte des 19. Jahrhunderts zu besorgen, und arbeite alles gründlich um.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  Karl Grunsky, <tei:hi rend="italic">Musikgeschichte Seit beginn des 19. Jahrhunderts</tei:hi> (Leipzig: G.J. Göschen, 1902, 1908).</tei:note>   So bleibt für Korrespondenzen keine Zeit übrig.</tei:p><tei:p>Mit dem Einwand gegen die Klavierlitteratur wollte ich auf ein gewisses Werturteil abzielen. Glauben Sie nicht, dass für ein Orchester ^und Kammermusik^ (im allgemeinen Wertvolleres da ist? Allerdings hält sich der Laie an die Klaviermusik, und es ist schwer, ihm mit dem Unbekannten zu kommen.</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> Darf  ich Sie um Ihre sachliche Ansicht über Bruckner bitten?    Warum sind seine Orgelpunkte schlecht gemacht?  Ich bin Ihnen vielleicht als Brucknermann unsympatisch. Das soll Sie nicht abhalten, mir <tei:hi rend="italic">alle</tei:hi> Bedenken offen klarzulegen.   Ich bin für jeden Widerspruch und Einwand dankbar.</tei:p><tei:p>Auch wäre es mir lieb wenn Sie sich gelegentlich <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> über meine Formen-Auffassung in meiner Musikästhetik<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  Karl Grunsky, <tei:hi rend="italic">Musikästhetik</tei:hi> (G.J. Göschen, 1907).</tei:note> äussern würden. Ich bin kein Parteimensch; will nur von den Meistern lernen und habe grossen Respekt vor der Arbeit früherer Geschlechter.</tei:p><tei:p>Entschuldigen Sie diese kargen Zeilen mit meiner knappen Zeit!</tei:p><tei:p>Stets zu Diensten
Ihr hochachtungsvoll
ergebener
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] K Grunsky</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Grunsky to Schenker, dated May 3, 1908</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Stuttgart, May 3, 1908
Stitzenburgstrasse i/I</tei:p><tei:p>Dear Doctor,</tei:p><tei:p>Forgive me that I have been so silent up until now, since you have very much obligated me to thanks through the revealing of your concealed identity<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/> [<tei:hi rend="italic">cued from left margin:</tei:hi> which I will of course keep strictly to myself] and through your friendly letter.  Even today I am not in the position of replying to you extensively. <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> For Göschen, I need to provide a second edition of my <tei:hi rend="italic">Music History of the Nineteenth Century</tei:hi>, and am thoroughly revising everything.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/>  There remains therefore no time for correspondence.</tei:p><tei:p>I was aiming at a specific value judgment with the objection to piano literature.  Don’t you think that in general there are more valuable things for orchestra ^and chamber music^?  Of course laypeople stick to piano music, and it is difficult to approach them with the unfamiliar.</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> May I ask you for your objective view on Bruckner?  Why are his organ points poorly executed?  As a Brucknerite, I am perhaps not in sympathy with you.  That should not hold you back from openly laying out <tei:hi rend="italic">all</tei:hi> reservations.  I am grateful for every contradiction and objection.</tei:p><tei:p>I would also appreciate it if you would at some point <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> address my conception of form in my <tei:hi rend="italic">Music Aesthetics</tei:hi>.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/>  I am not a partisan person; I just want to learn from the masters and have great respect for the work of earlier generations.</tei:p><tei:p>Pardon these meager lines with my scant time!</tei:p><tei:p>Always at your service.
With kind regards,
Yours,
[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] K. Grunsky</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>