<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 11/29, [3] : 9-10-08 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© Published by kind permission of the heirs of Karl Grunsky. 
© Transcription Lee Rothfarb 2007.
© Translation Lee Rothfarb 2007.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary Lee Rothfarb, 2007.
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license> This document is published with the permission of the heirs of Karl Grunsky, March 8, 2007.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1908-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1945) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1945-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: Heirs of Karl Grunsky; Image: University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: Lee Rothfarb.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 09/10/1908 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Grunsky ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Grunsky to Schenker, dated September 10, 1908</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2007-03-18</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Acks receipt of Beitrag and two letters;  finds the oppositeness of their views on Bruckner remarkable and argues his case;  invokes Halm's writings. —Invites discussion about Brahms;  without Bülow, Brahms would not have risen so high.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Grunsky, Karl; Schenker, Heinrich;  Beitrag zur Ornamentik;  Contribution to Ornamentation;  Bruckner;  Noli me tangere;  Wagner;  Parsifal;  Vorspiel;  Prelude;  Übergang;  transition;  sonata form;  rhythm;  syncopation;  Neue Musikzeitung;  Halm, August;  Harmonielehre;  Manual of Harmony;  Orgelpunkt;  pedal point;  chromaticism;  Beethoven;  ecstasy;  passion;  Kretzschmar, Hermann;  Ländler;  Brahms;  Bülow, Hans von</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  Stuttgart, Stitzenburgstraß i/I</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Grunsky to Schenker, dated September 10, 1908</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Stuttgart, den 10. September [/]1908.
Stitzenburgstr. i^I^</tei:p><tei:p>Sehr geehrter Herr Doktor!</tei:p><tei:p>Ich danke Ihnen vielmals für Ihre fabelhaft interessante Zusendung, die Ornamentik.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  S instructed UE on July 22, 1908 to send G a copy of the second, enlarged edition of his <tei:hi rend="italic">Ein Beitrag zur Ornamentik</tei:hi> (1908) when published, and included his name in the list of people to receive complimentary or review copies on August 19 (&lt;a href="../../../../../schenker/correspondence/wslb<tei:hi rend="italic">12</tei:hi>72208.html"&gt;WSLB 12&lt;/a&gt;;  &lt;a href="../../../../../schenker/correspondence/oc<tei:hi rend="italic">52397</tei:hi>81108.html"&gt;OC 52/397&lt;/a&gt;, August 11; WSLB 14).  UE received copies from the printer on August 24, 1908, and began distributing shortly after August 26 (&lt;a href="../../../../../schenker/correspondence/oc<tei:hi rend="italic">5225</tei:hi>82608.html"&gt;OC 52/25&lt;/a&gt;).  </tei:note>  Mit Ungeduld sehe ich der Zeit entgegen, da ich sie genauer durchnehmen kann.  Ihre beiden freundlichen Briefe<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  Presumably OJ 5/15, [2], c. June 1, 1918, and OJ 5/15, <tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  “Do not touch me”:  John 20:17.</tei:note>, probably between June 6 and September 9, 1908.</tei:note> haben mich ebenfalls so stark interessiert, dass ich sie nun – freilich nicht in verdientem ausführlichen Maass[<tei:hi rend="italic">sic</tei:hi>] – erwidern möchte.  Vor allem aber stellen Sie sich mich nicht als einen Menschen vor, der Geld hat und dem die Unabkängigkeit leicht geworden wäre.  <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> Im Gegenteil, ich bin durch alle Demütigungen hindurchgegangen, bis ich meine Unanhängigkeit errungen habe.</tei:p><tei:p>Es freut mich, dass es doch heutzutage möglich ist über vieles in der Musik zu reden, was man früher als Noli me tangere<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  “Do not touch me”:  John 20:17.</tei:note> der Empfindung unangetastet und undebattiert liess.  Freilich hebt diese Möglichkeit den Eindruck keineswegs auf, dass z.B. unsere entgegengesetzten Ansichten auf einer grundverschiedenen Art des Fühlens beruhen;  also kann es sich nur um ungewollte Anregungen unter uns handeln, nicht um exakt begründbare Sätze!</tei:p><tei:p>Ist es nicht seltsam, dass ich in der Anerkennung Ihrer Bruckner-Beobachtungen mit Ihnen übereinstimme – dass mein Fühlen jedoch eine ganz andere Deutung erzwingt?  Ihr Haupteinwand ist, wenn ich gut verstehe:  <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> Br.s Disposition ist zu einfach;  seine Betonung guter Taktteile zu wenig mannigfach.  Ich sehe meinerseits in beiden Vorzüge.</tei:p><tei:p>1) inbezug auf die Form.  Wenn die Setzung der ^bekannten^ Folge im Sonatensatz einen klaren Sinn hat, so kann es nur der sein:  über den Eintritt neuer Themen, über den Ort der durchgeführten Themen, über die Wiederkehr + Rückkehr, zu orientieren.  Dies thun die Einschnitte bei Br. mit gewünschter Ehrlichkeit.  Darum ist seine Form klar und verständlich, wie das Parsifal Vorspiel.  Übergänge u. alles was das Gerippe als Fleisch gleichsam umkleidet – das ist ja, soweit notwendig da.  Wenigstens sehe ich es, und getraue mir’s jeden sehen zu lassen, von der 1. Sinfonie an.</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> Dass man die Form vor lauter Fluss nicht klar erkennt, das halte ich für ein Merkmal der embryonalen Sonatenform.  Oder für ein Kennzeichen übertriebener Technik ^welche^ ohne gemütvolle Unterlage bleibt.  Ist es nicht fast lächerlich, wie verschieden wir denken?</tei:p><tei:p>2) Einsatz auf gute Taktteile (wenigstens mit Vorliebe;  Ausnahmen immerhin <tei:hi rend="italic">zahlreich!</tei:hi>):  ist ebenso ein +gutes+ Zeichen für mich!  Das Nähere kann ich erst in einer Arbeit über die Rhythmik zeigen.  Vielleicht haben Sie bemerkt, wie ketzerisch ich über den Rhythmus denke.  Der reich ist an Harmonie, bevorzugt gute Taktteile überhaupt, und wendet Synkopierung massvoll an, ja sparsam.  Wiederum sehen Sie, wie vollständig entgegengesetzt ich urteile.</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{5}</tei:hi> Um nicht ganz in Scham vor Ihren Kenntnissen vergehen zu müssen, berufe ich mich auf August Halm,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  August Halm (1869–1929), German composer and writer on music, supporter of Bruckner, author of <tei:hi rend="italic">Von zwei Kulturen der Musik</tei:hi> (Munich: Georg Müller, 1913), <tei:hi rend="italic">Die Symphonien Anton Bruckners</tei:hi> (Munich: Georg Müller, 1914), <tei:hi rend="italic">Von Grenzen und Ländern der Musik: Gesammelte Aufsätze</tei:hi> (Munich: Goerg Müller, 1916) and many other books and articles.  Halm and S conducted a vigorous correspondence between 1916 and 1929.  </tei:note> von dem Sie notwendig lesen müssen den Aufsatz über Bruckner Neue Musikzeitg 1902, 13, 14, 16, 17 glaube ich.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  <tei:hi rend="italic">Neue Musikzeitung</tei:hi> 23 (1902), pp. 170-174, 196-198, 211-214, 227-228.  The first section of the essay (pp. 170-174) appeared in modified form in <tei:hi rend="italic">Der Kunstwart</tei:hi> 18 (1905), 242-247, as “Bruckner als Melodiker.”</tei:note>  Wenn es nicht gar zu ernst ware, müsste man lachen darüber, dass zwei theoretisch so fein durchgebildete und praktische Musikkenner wie Sie und Halm so diametral entgegengesetzt urteilen können (Halm begründet alles ins technische Detail!)  Da werden Sie finden, wie das Fmoll (bei Wiederholung Gmoll) des 2. Themas der V. ins Gute zu deuten, u.s.w.  Ebenso in Halms Harmonielehre die Stelle D-E im 1. Satz der VII.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  Halm, <tei:hi rend="italic">Harmonielehre</tei:hi> (Berlin: Göschen’sche Verlag, 1905), pp. XXIX–XXXI. </tei:note>  Die Handlung des E als Orgelp. in[<tei:hi rend="italic">corr</tei:hi>] der Coda (W) ist doch harmlos:  Die Chromatik ist kurzer Abstieg;  im Grunde nur eine Korrektur des F nach E, die für mich viel Stimmung hat.</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{6}</tei:hi> Im übrigen, was Stimmung betrifft, wieder ganz andere Auffassung auf meiner + Ihrer Seite.  Mir ist Br. besonders dadurch von andern unterschieden:  dass seine Verarbeitungen (jeder Art) wahr, echt ^sind^, und die Stimmung festhalten, d.h. steigern, vertiefen.  Technisch -gewendet- ^geredet^, die alten Mittel sind auf neue Weise überzeugend angewendet.  Selbst ein leiser Unterschied von Beeth. + Wagner, die oft (ja nicht immer) mit blossemWillen, Zeitmass etc steigern, während bei Br. jede erregende Wirkung einen bestimmten, inhaltspendenden Kunstmittel entspricht.  Z.B. im Adagio der VIII ist die Stelle, -da- wo durch Nachahmungen gesteigert wird, herrlich;  namentlich der Einsatz im Bass. (Partitur S. 57 ff)  Das Pathos ist vielmehr ein Ethos bei Br.  Die Ekstase im eigentli[chen] Sinn beginnt in der Durchführung.  Die Erfindung selbst, die Plastik der Themen <tei:hi rend="bold">{7}</tei:hi> verrät mir Ruhe + Besonnenheit in der Leidenschaft, also im Grund das Gegenteil von Ekstase.  Wiederum kann ich eben nur meine Ansicht aussprechen, die der Ihrigen wieder ganz entgegengesetzt ist!</tei:p><tei:p>Ländler-Stimmung?  Giebt es auch, wie Kretzschmar<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7">  Hermann Kretzschmar (1848–1924), German writer on music, Director of the Hochschule für Musik in Berlin from 1909 to 1920.   He was notable for his advocacy of music hermeneutics, the theory of which he developed in two articles entitled “(Neue) Anregungen zur Förderung musikalischer Hermeneutik,” ((New) Stimuli to the Promotion of Hermeneutics of Music), <tei:hi rend="italic">Musikbibliothek Peters für 1902</tei:hi>, 9 (1903), 45–66, and 1905, 12 (1906), 73–86), and which he practised in his multi-volume concert guide, <tei:hi rend="italic">Führer durch den Konzertsaal</tei:hi> (Leipzig: Liebeskind, 1888–90), which went through many volumes.  He was a frequent butt of S’s criticism, most notably in the monograph <tei:hi rend="italic">Beethovens Neunte Sinfonie</tei:hi> (1912), in the secondary literature sections of which he constantly attacked Kretzschmar’s remarks about the Ninth Symphony in vol. I of the Führer. </tei:note> meint, Ländler im 4/4 Takt?  Sind nicht Bruckners Tanzweisen die natürliche + notwendige Ergänzung seines Ernstes?  Sind sie nicht weit vornehmer als die Ungarischen etc bei Brahms?</tei:p><tei:p>Gewiss könnte mündliche Aussprache auch über Brahms manches bei mir ändern.  In der 2. Aufl. meiner Musikgeschichte, die dieser Tage erscheint,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn8">  Presumably Grunsky’s <tei:hi rend="italic">Musikgeschichte des 19. Jahrhunderts</tei:hi> (Leipzig: Göschen, 1902).</tei:note> glaube ich einen Fortschritt gemacht zu haben in der Gerechtigkeit gegen Brahms.</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{8}</tei:hi> Über eine tiefe Antipathie komme ich nicht hinweg.  Ich deute „absolute" Musik gern, willig, und wie ich glaube, annährend richtig.  Aber ich stehe vor vielem bei Brahms unmutig da, weil das Herz nicht mitklingen will.  Auch der Ausspruch über Bülow<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn9">  Hans von Bülow (1830–94), German conductor, pianist, and editor. Von Bülow was one of the collaborating editors of Cotta’s <tei:hi rend="italic">Instruktive Ausgabe klassischer Klavierwerke</tei:hi>; in particular, vols 4 and 5 of <tei:hi rend="italic">Beethoven’s Sonaten und andere Werke</tei:hi> in that series were edited by von Bülow. His editions were a frequent target of S's polemical attacks.</tei:note> scheint mir nicht edel gedacht:  ohne Bülow wäre Brahms nicht emporgekommen.  Sachlich genommen erscheint mir Bülow immer unsympatischer für einen nach Charakter strebenden Menschen:  was Sie in der neuen Auflage bestätigt finden werden durch schärferes Urteil.  Sie wissen und ich danke Ihnen dafür, dass ich keiner Partei diene und mein Fühlen nur dem ^Tondichter^ erschliesse, der es beglückt und sättigt.  Verzeihen Sie nur diesen ungeheuerlich langen Brief, und regen Sie mich bald wieder zum Widerspruch an!</tei:p><tei:p>In aufrichtiger Hochschätzung
bleibe ich Ihr ergebener  
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] K Grunsky</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Grunsky to Schenker, dated September 10, 1908</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Stuttgart, September 10, 1908
Stitzenburgstraße i/I</tei:p><tei:p>Dear Doctor,</tei:p><tei:p>Thank you very much for your fabulously interesting mailing, the <tei:hi rend="italic">Ornamentation</tei:hi>.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/>  With patience, I foresee the time when I can go through it more thoroughly.  Your two cordial letters<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> also interested me so greatly that I would like to respond to them—naturally not in the elaborate scope that they merit.  However, above all you don’t strike me as a person who has money and for whom independence would come easily.  <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> On the contrary, I went through all manner of humiliations until I achieved my independence.</tei:p><tei:p>I am pleased that it is certainly possible nowadays to talk about much in music that previously was left untouched and undiscussed as a <tei:hi rend="italic">Noli me tangere</tei:hi>|<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> of perception.  Of course that possibility in no way cancels out the impression that our opposed views are based, for example, on a fundamentally different type of feeling.  So it can just be a matter of unintended challenges between us, not of definitely substantiated principles.</tei:p><tei:p>Is it not odd that in the acknowledgment of your observations about Bruckner I agree with you, but that my feelings impose an entirely different interpretation?  If I understand correctly, your main objection is <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> that Bruckner’s organization is too simple, his accentuation of strong beats not sufficiently diverse.  For my part, I see advantages to both.</tei:p><tei:p>1)  With regard to form, when the arrangement of the ^familiar^ succession in a sonata-form movement has a clear logic, it can only be this:  to orient us to the entry of new themes, to the location of developed themes, to recapitulation and return.  The caesuras in Bruckner do this with the desired forthrightness.  His form is therefore clear and comprehensible, like the <tei:hi rend="italic">Parsifal</tei:hi> Prelude.  Transitions and everything that, as flesh, clothes the skeleton, so to speak—that is certainly present, as far as necessary.  Or so I see it at least, and believe I can get anyone to see it, from the First Symphony onward.</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi>  I consider it a trait of embryonic sonata form that we don’t recognize the form because of pure fluidity.  Or for a characteristic of exaggerated technique ^which^ remains without emotional underpinning.  Is it not almost ridiculous how differently we think?</tei:p><tei:p>2) Entry on strong beats (at least by preference;  exceptions are <tei:hi rend="italic">numerous</tei:hi>, anyway!) is also a +good+ sign for me.  I can only show details in a work on rhythm.  You have perhaps noticed how heretically I think about rhythm.  Whoever is rich in harmony prefers strong beats in general, and uses syncopation moderately, even sparingly.  Here again you see how completely oppositely I make judgments.</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{5}</tei:hi> In order not to have to shrink completely in shame before your knowledge, I refer to August Halm,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> whose essay on Bruckner, <tei:hi rend="italic">Neue Musikzeitung</tei:hi> (1902), [Nos.] 13, 14, 16, 17, I think, you absolutely must read.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/>  If it were not so serious, we would have to laugh at how two theoretically so well trained and practically oriented music experts as you and Halm can reach such diametrically opposed judgments (Halm substantiates everything in technical detail!).  There, you will find how to interpret favorably the F minor tonality (at the repetition, G minor) of the second theme in the Fifth, etc.  Also, in Halm’s <tei:hi rend="italic">Manual of Harmony</tei:hi> the passage from D to E in the first movement of the Seventh.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/>  The treatment of E as a pedal point in the coda (W) is certainly inoffensive.  The chromaticism is a brief descent, in principle merely a correction of F toward E, which for me has a lot of character.</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{6}</tei:hi> By the way, regarding character, understood, again, completely differently from your perspective and mine.  To me, Bruckner is especially differentiated from others in that his treatments of materials (of every type) ^are^ true, genuine and maintain the character, i.e. escalate, intensify.  -Formulated- ^Speaking^ technically:  the old means are applied convincingly in a new way.  Even a faint difference from Beethoven, Wagner, who often (not always, of course) escalate with pure will, tempo, etc, while with Bruckner every actuating effect corresponds to a specific artistic means that bestows content.  In the Adagio of the Eighth, for instance, the passage that escalates by means of imitations, marvelous; notably the entrance in the bass (score, pp. 57ff).  The pathos is more an ethos in Bruckner.  Ecstasy in the actual sense begins in the development section.  The invention itself, the vividness of the themes <tei:hi rend="bold">{7}</tei:hi> discloses to me tranquility and reflectiveness in the passion, thus at bottom the opposite of ecstasy.  Again, I can only express my view, which is again entirely opposite to yours!</tei:p><tei:p>Ländler-character?  Are there also, as Kretzschmar<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/> says, Ländlers in 4/4 time?  Are not Bruckner’s dance tunes the natural, necessary complements of his seriousness?  Are they not far more refined than the Hungarian tunes, etc., in Brahms?</tei:p><tei:p>Certainly, a face-to-face discussion on Brahms could change some things in my thinking.  In the second edition of my music history, which will appear in the next few days,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn8"/> I believe I have made progress in the fairness toward Brahms.</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{8}</tei:hi> I cannot get past a deep antipathy.  I interpret “absolute” music gladly, willingly and, as I believe, ever more correctly.  But I am annoyed by much in Brahms because my heart will not resonate.  The statement about Bülow,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn9"/> too, seems to me not graciously conceived.  Without Bülow, Brahms would not have risen so high.  Considered objectively, Bülow seems to me always more disagreeable as a person striving for character, which you will find confirmed in the new edition [of my music history] through keener judgement.  You know, and I thank you for it, that I serve no party, and reveal my feelings only to that ^tone poet^ who delights and satisfies those feelings.  Pardon this enormously long letter, and challenge me soon again to opposition!</tei:p><tei:p>In genuine admiration, 
I remain
Yours truly,
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] K. Grunsky</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>