<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 6/4, [] : 9-18-06 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© Heirs of Heinrich Schenker.
© Transcription Ian D. Bent, with the assistance of John Rothgeb, 2005.
© Translation Ian D. Bent, with the assistance of John Rothgeb, 2005.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary Ian D. Bent 2005.
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license> All reasonable steps have been taken to locate the heirs of Heinrich Schenker. Any claim to intellectual rights on this document should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Violin, Moriz (1906-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1955) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1955-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: Heirs of Heinrich Schenker; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: Ian D. Bent.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 09/18/1906 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Violin ~ H+JSchenker","Violin ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Schenker to Violin, dated September 15 or 18, 1906</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2005-08-04</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>[Niloff: Instrumentations-Tabelle:] The financial arrangement with Stritzko and Doblinger is a catastrophe.  S has no money.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Schenker, Heinrich;  Violin, Moriz; Floriz; Florizello; Niloff; Instrumentations-Tabelle; Instrumentation Table; Redlich; Schenker, Julia; money; Stritzko; Doblinger; contract</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  Wien, XIV., Sechshauserstraße 128</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Schenker to Moriz Violin, dated September 15 or 18,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1"> "5" and "8" are superimposed, so this could have been written on the 8th and then changed to the 15th by overwriting "5" upon "8" and inserting a "1" before, or more likely (since the previous letter is dated the 12th and the following letter the 22nd) the "8" has been overwritten upon "5" changing the 15th to the 18th.</tei:note> 1906</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>15/18. 9. 06</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="italic">Florizello!</tei:hi>  Nach dem Sprichwort dürfte „Gottes Hilfe“ irgendwo am nächsten sein : jetzt muß sie es schon sogar.  Denn :</tei:p><tei:p>am 19ten. [:] 10 fl der Bediener[i]n</tei:p><tei:p>für 19. (jüdische Feiertage)<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  The holy days in question would presumably have been Rosh Hashanah and Yom Kippur.</tei:note> [:] der <tei:hi rend="italic">Mama</tei:hi> ein paar Gulden, Tempelsitze, etc.</tei:p><tei:p>[am] 16te. [:] 10 fl Unfallversich.</tei:p><tei:p>und ich habe keinen Groschen bei mir.  Meinetwegen versprich 8–10o<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  <tei:hi rend="italic">versprich 8–10o</tei:hi> : the meaning of this phrase cannot be determined from this message.</tei:note>, aber mir ist alles lieber, als zu H.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  It is probably too early for this to be Emil Hertzka, who is not mentioned in any of the related diary entries of this time, but who just possibly might have been working at Doblinger a this point.  He came to Universal Edition (which not yet in the picture regarding the <tei:hi rend="italic">Instrumentations-Tabelle</tei:hi> ) in 1907.</tei:note> zu gehen, der immer tut, als müßte er zuvor alle Tanten seiner u. <tei:hi rend="italic">Redlich’s</tei:hi> Familie<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  Probably Friedrich (Fritz) Redlich (1868-1921), leading Austrian industrialist  (owner of a sugar refinery and other businesses in the region of Göding), politician, and patron of the arts; father of Hans Ferdinand Redlich (1903-68), Austrian musicologist.  Fritz is known to have been a friend of Gustav Mahler and his family.  </tei:note> anhaltiren, bevor er das paar Gulden herleiht.</tei:p><tei:p>Und für die <tei:hi rend="italic">Katastrophe – Stritzko-Dobl.</tei:hi> kann ich auch nichts.  Niemals wäre es mir auch nur möglich geschienen, daß &lt;strike&gt;xxx&lt;/strike&gt; ^&lt;strike&gt;xxx&lt;/strike&gt;^ 55[ <tei:hi rend="italic">corr</tei:hi> ] Exemplare verkauft sein [müßten], u. <tei:hi rend="italic">Dob.</tei:hi> daran 25 fl (u. Stritzt. etwas weniger) zuvor verdient haben müsse, bevor<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  „zuvor ..., bevor”:„zu-„ and „vor“ added in right and left margins over line-break.</tei:note> ich 10 fl verdiene,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7">  For details of the proposed royalty deal, see OJ 1/5, p.19, September 13, 1906.  For the complete known sequence of references to this deal, select “Stritzko &amp; Co” under "Documents" in the user-interface and browse.  The <tei:hi rend="italic">Instrumentations-Tabelle</tei:hi> was eventually published by UE by October 29, 1908 (OC 52/398).  This first small-scale trial edition, sent out only to highschools and conservatories, is not listed in UE’s Verlagsdruckbuch: the first edition recorded there came off the press on January 12, 1909 in 2,000 copies (UE 1999). —It must be significant that the author-name over which it was published, “Niloff,” is a sonic anagram of “Violin.”</tei:note> also so viel, als ein <tei:hi rend="italic">Copist</tei:hi> für diese minutiöse<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn8">  = <tei:hi rend="italic">minuziöse</tei:hi>, i.e. minute, precise, exact.</tei:note> Arbeit sicher verlangt hätte.  Jedenfalls hast du, wie[ <tei:hi rend="italic">corr</tei:hi> ] du denken kannst, die erste <tei:hi rend="italic">Hypothek</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn9">  literally “mortgage.”</tei:note> auf das Geld, das kommt. Ich bin ganz am Rande —<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn10">  i.e. of disaster, penury, etc.  Alternatively, he could mean “I’m on the sidelines” or “It’s out of my hands.”</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>dein Untercopist.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn11">  This is presumably not meant literally, but as a humorous way of saying “Your obedient servant,” perhaps referring back to the allegation in the penultimate sentence that he would earn less than a professional copyist for the same work.</tei:note></tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Schenker to Moriz Violin, dated September 15 or 18,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/> 1906</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>September 15/18, 1906</tei:p><tei:p>Florizello!  As the old saying goes, „God’s help“ may be near: now it really <tei:hi rend="italic">must</tei:hi> be.  For:</tei:p><tei:p>on the 19th : 10 Florins for the cleaning lady</tei:p><tei:p>for the 19th (Jewish holidays)<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> : a few pennies for Mama, seats in the synagogue etc.</tei:p><tei:p>on the 16th : 10 Florins for accident insurance.</tei:p><tei:p>...and I'm left without a penny.  As far as I am concerned, promise 8–10o<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/>, but anything is better than going to H.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/>, who always behaves as if he must first offer financial support to all the aunts in his and Redlich’s family<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/> before he will cough up the few pennies.</tei:p><tei:p>Nor is there anything I can do about the catastrophe—Stritzko–Doblinger.  I had never for a moment dreamt that 55 copies would have to be sold and Doblinger would have to earn 25 Florins on the deal (and Stritzko a little less) before ever<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/> I might earn 10 Florins,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/> i.e. as much as a copyist would surely have demanded for work as precise and detailed<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn8"/> as this.  At any rate, you can take it that you have first claim<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn9"/> on the money that comes.  I’m on the brink—<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn10"/>
							Your assistant copyist.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn11"/></tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>