<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 13/22 : 3-10-13 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
©  Heirs of Rudolf Réti, permission being sought.
©  Transcription by Ian Bent, 2008
©  Translation by Ian Bent, 2008
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary Ian Bent, 2008
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>Permission to publish being sought.  Any claim to intellectual rights on this document should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1913-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1945) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1945-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: Heirs of Rudolf Réti; Image: University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary, Translation: Ian Bent</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 03/10/1913 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: &quot;R&#195;&#169;ti ~ HSchenker&quot; --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Réti to Schenker, dated March [10], 1913</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2008-07-13</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Réti regrets Schenker's absence from his lecture [on harmonic theory], agrees with Schenker's view of music history, but disagrees with the generalization of his musical laws.  

</dc:description><dc:subject>Réti, Rudolf;  Schenker, Heinrich</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">   - -</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Rudolf Réti to Schenker, dated March <tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn10">  "Jüngeren" (younger man):  underlined by Schenker in pencil, and "Wien!!" (Vienna!) written to left.</tei:note>, 1913</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">Schenker's hand:</tei:hi>]  <tei:hi rend="italic">Wiener</tei:hi> Productchen!
[<tei:hi rend="italic">stamped:</tei:hi>]  R. R.</tei:p><tei:p>Sehr verehter Herr Doktor!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  Receipt of this letter is recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 1/12, p. 322, March 10, 1913, in pungent form:  " Reply from Dr. Réti;  his only gift is that of arrogance—thus [he is] ungifted.  Reckoning will ensue, probably in the Preface, which is still to be taken care of, or in a letter to Hertzka."  The letter is one of five forwarded to Hertzka (UE) with WSLB 149, March 18, 1913, and Schenker comments on it further to Hertzka in WSLB 150, March 28, 1913.  It is transcribed also in Federhofer, <tei:hi rend="italic">Heinrich Schenker nach Tagebüchern …</tei:hi> (Hildesheim: Georg Olms, 1985), pp. 186–87.  Further diary entries regarding Réti are OJ 1/12, p. 334, April 14, 1913 and p. 364, June 12, 1913.  </tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Es tut mir leid, daß Sie bei meinem Vortrage<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  Réti's invitation to attend his lecture "on an attempt to explain the theory of harmony,"  and Schenker's rejection, are recorded in Schenker's diary at OJ 1/12, p. 320, March 4, 1913.  </tei:note> nicht zugegen waren, zumal hier offenbar ein Mißverständnis mitgespielt hat, Professor Adler<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  Click on <ref cRef="adler_guido">Guido Adler</ref>.</tei:note> ist nämlich nicht mehr Präsident d. Musikgesellschaft.</tei:p><tei:p>Ihrer Meinung, daß Musikgeschichte, wie sie heute gelehrt wird, fast wertlos ist, stimme ich bei, da auch ich glaube, daß eine Geschichte der Technik den Kern aller Musikgeschichte bilden müßte.</tei:p><tei:p>Was jedoch Ihre Behauptung betrifft, es gäbe nur ganze oder gar keine Wahrheit, so klingt dies wohl sehr reizvoll, <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> doch wäre es unaufrichtig, wenn ich bestimmen wollte.  Und indem ich darüber nachdenke, glaube ich, es ließe sich fast eher das Gegenteil behaupten: es gibt nur halbe Wahrheiten.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  "es … Wahrheiten" (there … half-truths): underlined by Schenker in pencil, with "(!!)" after the last word.  </tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Denken Sie, es schriebe jemand ein Buch über die menschliche Gesellschaft, da könnte doch der Fall eintreten, daß eine ausgezeichnete Schilderung oder Darstellung &lt;strike&gt;der&lt;/strike&gt; einer ganz begrenzten (zeitlich, örtlich und sozial begrenzt) Schicht der Gesellschaft gelänge, sagen wir beispielsweise<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  "beispielsweise" (for example): underlined by Schenker in pencil, with cue-mark to lower margin, where he has written "Schönbergs geistige 'Cigarette'" (Schoenberg's spiritual 'cigarette').  </tei:note> eine Art Soziologie der Wiener Bourgeoisie und nun glaubte der Betreffende, eine <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> allgemein, ewig gültige Lehre der Menschlichen Gesellschaft als solcher gegeben zu haben.  Sein Werk wird gewiß nicht wertlos sein und man könnte, man müßte es doch bekämpfen.</tei:p><tei:p>Aus unserem Fach.</tei:p><tei:p>Ich glaube beispielsweise (so viel ich mich erinnere sagen Sie Ähnliches)<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  "so … Ähnliches" (to … similar): underlined by Schenker in pencil, and in the space directly above it: "unverschämtes Wienertum!  Schönberg's 'ich habe blos geblättert!' (shameless Viennese way of doing things:  Schoenberg's "I have only leafed through [it]!") written with arrow.  </tei:note> daß das Verbot paralleler Quinten (ganz abgesehen von den zahlreichen Fällen wo es nicht gilt) auch in den Fällen, wo es zutrifft verschiedene Male auf gänzlich verschiedener Ursache beruht.  Denken Sie nun es hätte jemand, die richtige Ursache für einen Fall aufgedeckt (u. zwar nehmen wir an als Erster nach falschen Deutungen früherer) so wäre ihm, falls er der Meinung <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> wäre, das ^Problem des^ Quintenverbots als solches gelöst zu haben, teils zuzustimmen teils zu entgegnen.</tei:p><tei:p>Ähnliches ließe sich über das Problem der Diatonik (die ich jedesmal übrigens hier auch wie Sie<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7">  "übrigens … Sie" (which … you): underlined by Schenker in pencil, and "als hätte ich es [?]" (as if I had [?] it) written interlinearly above.  </tei:note> für etwas Anderes halte) zu sagen u.s.w.</tei:p><tei:p>Ich glaube, Sie haben die bisher beste Darstellung des klassischen Musikstils gegeben<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn8">  "die bisher ... gegeben" (have provided … style):  underlined by Schenker in pencil, and "na, also" (well, is that so) written interlinearly above.  </tei:note> u. Ihr Fehler besteht darin, dies für eine Darstellung der für alle Zeiten gültigen Musikgesetzte zu haben[<tei:hi rend="italic">corr</tei:hi>].<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn9">  No paragraph-break in original.  </tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Empfangen Sie, verehrter Herr Doktor, den Ausdruck aufrichtigster Wertschätzung von einem Jüngeren<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn10">  "Jüngeren" (younger man):  underlined by Schenker in pencil, and "Wien!!" (Vienna!) written to left.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] Rudolf Réti
Wien, im März 1913</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Rudolf Réti to Schenker, dated March <tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn10"/>, 1913</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">Schenker's hand:</tei:hi>]  Puny <tei:hi rend="italic">Viennese</tei:hi> product!
[<tei:hi rend="italic">stamped:</tei:hi>]  R. R.</tei:p><tei:p>Greatly honored Dr. [Schenker]<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/></tei:p><tei:p>I am sorry that you were not present at my lecture,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> especially since a misunderstanding evidently has played a part in this;  that is, Professor Adler<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> is no longer President of the Music Society.</tei:p><tei:p>I concur with your opinion that music history as it is taught today is nigh-on worthless, since I, too, believe that a history of the technique [of music] must form the kernel of all music history.</tei:p><tei:p>However, as regards your statement that there exist only the whole truth or no truth whatsoever, highly appealing as this admittedly sounds, <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> I would be dishonest if I were to go along with it.  And as I ponder this, I believe almost the opposite to be the case:  there exist only half-truths.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/></tei:p><tei:p>Imagine that someone were to write a book about human society, then it could happen that an excellent description or presentation of a strictly limited (temporarily, geographically, or socially limited) layer of society might result—let us say, for example,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/> a kind of sociology of the Viennese bourgeoisie, but then the person concerned believed that he had furnished a <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> general, eternally valid theory of human society as such.   His work would by no means be valueless, but one could, one would certainly have to contest it.</tei:p><tei:p>Now to apply this to our own discipline.</tei:p><tei:p>I believe, for example (to the best of my recollection, you say something similar),<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/> that the proscription of parallel 5ths (quite apart from the numerous cases in which it does not apply), even in cases where it applies, at different times rests on wholly different causes.  Imagine now that someone had discovered the correct cause for one instance (to be more precise, let us assume that at the outset according to false interpretations earlier[?]), then, if he were to be of the opinion <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> that he had solved the ^problem of^ parallel 5ths as such, we would have partly to agree with him, partly to contradict him.</tei:p><tei:p>Something similar could be said about the problem of diatonicism (which, incidentally, I too, like you,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/> consider to be something different on each occasion), etc.</tei:p><tei:p>I believe that you have provided the best presentation to date of the Classical musical style<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn8"/>, and your error consists in your having taken this to be a presentation of musical laws valid for all time.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn9"/></tei:p><tei:p>Please, honored Dr. [Schenker], accept this expression of [my] genuine esteem, from a younger man<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn10"/></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] Rudolf Réti
Vienna, in March 1913</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>