<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0" xml:id="entity-002417">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Israelitische Kultusgemeinde [IKG], Wien</title>
        <title type="sub">Jewish Religious Community, Vienna</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="israelitische_kultusgemeinde">Israelitische Kultusgemeinde, Wien</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>07/02/2009</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Organization</term>
          <term subtype="basename">israelitische_kultusgemeinde</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change><date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Israelitische Kultusgemeinde [IKG], Wien</head>
      <div>
        <p>Autonomous organization in which Viennese Jews themselves regulated all aspects of their
          life in the city.</p>
        <div>
          <head>Summary History</head>
          <p>The Israelitische Kultusgemeinde in Vienna was founded by provisional statute in 1849 –
            the year in which Emperor Franz Josef publicly used the phrase "Israelitische Gemeinde
            von Wien" (Jewish Community of Vienna) – and was confirmed in 1852. In 1867,
            emancipation was granted to Jews in Austria, and a constitutional framework was created
            for the Jewish population. The Israelitische Kultusgemeinde regulated all aspects of
            Jewish life in the city, notably synagogues, finances, schools and education, and
            philanthropic activities. In 1825, the cornerstone of the Vienna Synagogue had been set
            at <ref cRef="entity-002351">Seitenstettengasse</ref> 4, and when the Israelitische
            Kultusgemeinde came into existence, its secretariat was located on that site. </p>
          <p>Between the two world wars, the IKG faced increasing antisemitism; after the Anschluß
            in March 1938, its offices were ransacked, and in November 1938 other Jewish buildings
            were ravaged; only the central synagoguge survived this. The Kultusgemeinde was
            disbanded, and was re-established only after World War II. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>The Israelitische Kultusgemeinde and Schenker</head>
          <p>It is clear from the diary that Heinrich Schenker paid some taxes each year to the
            Kultusgemeinde as well as to the civic tax authorities (<hi rend="italic">Steuerbehörde</hi>). </p>
          <p>An incident in 1916 is of particular interest. On December 3 of that year, the
            Rothschild Artists' Foundation invited Schenker to serve on its college of jurors (OJ
            12/6, [2]). Evidently, the Kultusgemeinde wrote at the same time, for Schenker recorded
            in his diary on December 5: "Letter from the committee of the Kultusgemeinde: wishes me
            to undertake the honorary post of juror with <ref cRef="entity-000003">Adler</ref> as
            expert adviser and <ref cRef="entity-000310">Grünfeld</ref> as co-adviser"; and a day
            later he asked <ref cRef="entity-000913">Moriz Violin</ref> to meet him in order to bring
            him some "'ideas on how to say 'no' to the Kultusgemeinde" (OC 2/5, pp. 525, 526) – a
            phrase which suggests that he felt the need to handle the Community with care. Schenker
            wrote to the Kultusgemeinde on December 10 (letter non-extant), evidently stating his
            intention to decline, then wrote to the Rothschild Foundation on December 13 declining
            its invitation (diary, OC 2/5, p. 533), after which on December 17 the President of the
            Kultusgemeinde, Dr. Alfred Stern, wrote to Schenker (OJ 11/58, [1]) expressing "my
            regret that you have declined to undertake the duty of a juror on the Rothschild
            Artists' Foundation," and continuing: <cit>
              <q>Precisely the fact that you represent a trend in art that does not correspond with
                today's admittedly not common but nonetheless quite widely held views, would have
                made your participation in the jury college seem to me particularly desirable.</q>
            </cit></p>
          <p>The Kultusgemeinde also played a preliminary part in the marriage of Heinrich Schenker
            to Jeanette Kornfeld. Prior to that wedding on November 10, 1919, Schenker's diary
            records "Lie-Liechen to the Kultusgemeinde to gather information about procedures – no
            office hours," and the next day "Lie-Liechen to the Kultusgemeinde: picks up next
            directive" (OJ 3/1, pp. 2147, 2148, September 18 and 19, 1919); and a month later the
            couple went to the "rabbinate: Lie-Liechen receives certificate of refusal" (OJ 3/1, p.
            2162, October 26, 1919), this presumably indicating that her first husband had refused
            her a divorce in Jewish law, and that certification of this fact was required before a
            civil marriage could proceed. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>Correspondence between the Kultusgemeinde and Schenker</head>
          <p>Only one letter survives from the Kultusgemeinde to Schenker (OJ 11/58, [1]). In
            addition, a "remembrance" of Schenker and interment certification from the
            Kultusgemeinde dated January 14, 1935 survive as OJ 35/6, [2]. </p>
        </div>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Sources:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author>Czeike, Felix</author>, <title level="m">Historisches Lexikon Wien</title>
            (Vienna: Kremayr &amp; Scheriau, 1992–2004), vol. 3 (1994), p. 634</bibl>
          <bibl>Schenker's diaries and correspondence</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Contributors:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author>Ian Bent</author> and <author>Marko Deisinger</author></bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
