<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-002454">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Mannes Music School</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="mannes_music_school">Mannes Music School</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>19/01/2008</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Organization</term>
          <term subtype="basename">mannes_music_school</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Mannes Music School</head>

      <div>
        <p>Classical music conservatory in <ref cRef="entity-002873">New York City</ref>, founded by
            <ref cRef="entity-004633">David Mannes</ref> and <ref cRef="entity-004634">Clara
            Damrosch</ref> in 1916 as the David Mannes Music School.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>History of the College</head>
        <p>David's and Clara's aim in founding their new school was twofold: to offer, in the words
          of David Mannes (1938), "not only the intense development of the potential professional,
          but the efforts of those who wanted merely to enrich themselves through a better
          understanding or playing of music without the responsibilities of a career"; consequently
          no examinations were held and no diplomas awarded. Music theory was taught initially by
          Angela Diller, then in 1917‒19 by Ernest Bloch, after whom Rosario Scalero taught strict
          counterpoint for six years, and on his departure in 1926 David's and Clara's son Leopold
          took over theory until the arrival in 1931 of <ref cRef="entity-000951">Hans Weisse</ref>.
          ("Surely," wrote Mannes in 1938, "if the school had no other claims to favor, it has had
          three really important influences in its faculty history ‒ Bloch, Scalero and Weisse.")
          The school was initially located in a single private house, 154 East 70th Street, but in
          1919 moved to 157 East 74th Street (three brownstone houses remodeled into a single
          building). In the 1940s George Szell taught instrumentation and composition.</p>

        <p>After Clara's death in 1948, Leopold became co-director with his father (<ref
            cRef="entity-000754">Felix Salzer</ref> served as assistant director). Leopold was named
          the school's president in 1950, with Salzer as executive director, during which period
          Mannes was given accreditation by the City to award a college degree to its professional
          students, while the other side of the college's work was redefined as its extension
          division. In 1953 the name changed to Mannes College of Music. In 1959, with Leopold still
          at the helm, an attempt by the trustees to close the College was foiled by members of
          faculty, and in 1960 a merger with Chatham Square Music School solved some of the
          college's financial and enrollment problems. In 1979 a similar move by the trustees, this
          time to close the college and merge it with Manhattan School of Music was, in a landmark
          legal case, thwarted by faculty members.</p>

        <p>In 1984 the College moved to premises on the Upper West Side of Manhattan at 150 West
          85th Street, and its East Side building was demolished. In 1989 the College became a
          constituent of The New School for Social Research, and in 2005 was renamed The Mannes
          College the New School for Music. It left its Upper West Side premises in 2015, and is now
          located downtown at Arnhold Hall, 55 West 13th Street. Its name became Mannes School of
          Music, forming part of the College of Performing Arts within The New School. Its library
          became the Performing Arts Library (the name Scherman Library then being dropped), and its
          archives became part of The New School Archives &amp; Special Collections.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>The Mannes School and Schenker' Theory</head>
        <p>In the 1930s the David Mannes Music School became the focal point for the dissemination
          of Schenker's theory in the USA (thus by extension also in Europe, since World War II),
          and has played a crucial role in that ever since. (Though it is reported that as early as
          1925 <ref cRef="entity-000939">George A. Wedge</ref> was "lecturing on the Urlinie" at
          another New York school, the <ref cRef="entity-002437">Institute of Musical Art</ref>,
          founded by Mannes's brother-in-law, Frank Damrosch [Schenker's diary, October 8, 1925].)
          In 1931, Schenker's pupil <ref cRef="entity-000951">Hans Weisse</ref> was appointed ‒
          perhaps at the suggestion of <ref cRef="entity-000934">Gerald F. Warburg</ref> ‒ to the
          staff of the school to teach composition, theory, and analysis according to Schenker's
          theory, and taught there until his death in 1940. In 1932, the school sponsored the
          publication of Schenker's <ref cRef="entity-001755"><title level="m">Fünf
              Urlinie-Tafeln</title></ref> in conjunction with Universal Edition of Vienna. Weisse
          is known from his letters to Schenker to have taught classes on the analysis and graphs of
          Beethoven's "Eroica" Symphony in Schenker's <ref cRef="entity-001752"><title level="m">Das
              Meisterwerk in der Musik</title>, vol. III</ref>, and a seminar on <ref
            cRef="entity-001728"><title level="m">Der freie Satz</title></ref>, and to have used the
            <title level="m">Fünf Urlinie-Tafeln</title> as teaching material; and from the School's
          prospectuses it appears that he taught courses with titles such as "Creative Hearing," and
          "The Theory of Dr. Heinrich Schenker."</p>

        <p>Weisse was succeeded by <ref cRef="entity-000754">Felix Salzer</ref>, who had been
          Weisse's pupil in Vienna and subsequently <ref cRef="entity-002499">Schenker's
            seminar</ref> member and briefly his private pupil (1931–35). The foundational program
          at Mannes, "Techniques of Music," integrating musicianship, theory, and performance on the
          basis of Schenker's theory, was created by Salzer in 1953. Among those Schenkerian
          thinkers who have taught at Mannes are <ref cRef="entity-006967">Adele T. Katz</ref>
          (1936: at the Westchester Branch), Roy Travis (1952–57), Allen Forte (1957–60), William
          Mitchell (1957–68), Edward Laufer (1973–75), <ref cRef="entity-000649">Ernst Oster</ref>
          (1970–77), Eric Wen (2008‒13), and Mannes alumnus Carl Schachter (1956–), who may rightly
          be regarded as the doyen of Schenkerian theory in America, having devoted his entire
          career to the development and teaching of the discipline and influencing generations of
          outstanding scholars.</p>

        <p>In 1985, Mannes held the first International Schenker Symposium; subsequent symposia have
          taken place every seven years.</p>
      </div>
    </body>

    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Bibliography:</head>

        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author>Schenker, Heinrich</author>, <title level="m">Fünf Urlinie-Tafeln/Five
              Analyses in Sketchform</title> (New York: David Mannes Music School, 1932); repubd as
              <title level="m">Five Graphic Music Analyses (Fünf Urlinie-Tafeln)</title>, intro.
              <editor>Felix Salzer</editor>, New York, Dover, 1969)</bibl>

          <bibl>
            <author>Mannes. David</author>, <title level="m">Music is My Faith: An
              Autobiography</title> (New York: W. W. Norton, [1938]) </bibl>

          <bibl><author>Martin, George Whitney</author>, <title level="m">The Damrosch
              Dynasty</title> (Boston: Houghton Mifflin, 1983)</bibl>

          <bibl><author>Grünzweig, Werner</author>, <title level="a">Vom 'Schenkerismus' zum
              'Dahlhaus-Projekt': Einflüsse deutschsprachiger Musiker und Musikwissenschaftler in
              den Vereinigten Staaten—Anfänge und Ausblick,</title>
            <title level="j">Österreichische Musik Zeitschrift</title> 3–4 (1993), 161–70</bibl>

          <bibl><author>Berry, David Carson</author>, <title level="a">The Role of Adele T. Katz in
              the Early Expansion of the New York 'Schenker School',</title>
            <title level="j">Current Musicology</title> 74 (Fall 2002), 103–51</bibl>

          <bibl><author>Berry, David Carson</author>, <title level="a">Hans Weisse and the Dawn of
              American Schenkerism,</title>
            <title level="j">Journal of Musicology</title> 20/1 (Winter 2003), 104–56</bibl>

          <bibl>In <editor>Martin Eybl &amp; Evelyn Fink-Mennel</editor>, eds, <title level="m"
              >Schenker-Traditionen: Eine Wiener Schule der Musiktheorie und ihre internationale
              Verbreitung</title> (Vienna: Böhlau Verlag, 2006):–</bibl>

          <bibl>— <author>Berry, David Carson</author>, <title level="a">Hans Weisse
              (1892–1940)</title>, pp. 91–103<lb/>— <author>Carl Schachter</author>, <title
              level="a">Felix Salzer (1904–1986),</title> pp. 105–11<lb/>— <author>William
              Rothstein</author>, <title level="a">Ernst Oster (1908–1977),</title> pp. 121–35
            <lb/>— <author>Hedi Siegel</author>, <title level="a">The Pictures and Words of an
              Artist ('Von einem Künstler'): Heinrich Schenker's Fünf Urlinie-Tafeln,</title> pp.
            203–20</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Sources</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><title level="m">NGDM2</title> (2008)</bibl>
          <bibl>Berry (2002)</bibl>
          <bibl>Berry (2003)</bibl>
          <bibl><title level="m">Schenker-Traditionen</title> (2006)</bibl>
          <bibl>letters of Hans Weisse</bibl>
          <lb/>
          <bibl>Communications from Ed Scarcelle, University Librarian at The New School, Wendy
            Scheir, Director of Archives &amp; Special Collections at The New School, and Eric
            Wen</bibl>
          <bibl>Advice and guidance also from Hedi Siegel and William Drabkin</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Contributor</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author><hi rend="bold">Ian Bent</hi></author></bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>

    </back>

  </text>
</TEI>
