<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-000362">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Max Hesses Verlag</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="hesses_verlag_max">Hesses Verlag, Max</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>08/05/2008</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Organization</term>
          <term subtype="basename">hesses_verlag_max</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change><date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Max Hesses Verlag</head>
      <div>
        <p>Leipzig and Berlin publishing house of music books and periodicals.</p>

        <p>Max Hesses Verlag was founded in Leipzig in 1880 by Friedrich August Max Hesse
          (1858‒1907) initially for a range of works on literature, pedagogy, etc., but quickly
          focused on books and periodicals about music. In the press's first decade, <ref
            cRef="entity-000712">Hugo Riemann</ref> became an adviser, entrusting publication of the
          third edition of his <title level="m">Musiklexikon</title> to the house in 1887. With the
          launch of his pedagogical series of <title level="m">Illustrierte Katechismen</title>,
          Hesse became the chief vehicle for Riemann's practical music primers and analyses between
          1888 and 1902, continuing to publish them in expanded form as the series <title level="m"
            >Illustrierte Handbücher</title> up to and beyond Riemann's death in 1919. Hesse also
          published Riemann's <title level="m">Geschichte der Musiktheorie im IX. bis XIX.
            Jahrhundert</title> in 1898, the <title level="m">Riemann-Festschrift</title> in 1909,
          and Riemann's three-volume analyses of Beethoven piano sonatas (1917‒19). In 1915 the
          publishing house moved to Berlin. <ref cRef="entity-000013">Wilhelm Altmann</ref> and <ref
            cRef="entity-000195">Alfred Einstein</ref> became its advisers, and Einstein became the
          editor of the <title level="m">Musiklexikon</title>.</p>

        <p>Max Hesses Verlag also published the first editions of Ernst Kurth's <title level="m"
            >Bruckner</title> (1925) and <title level="m">Musikpsychologie</title> (1931), and seem
          to have taken over his <title level="m">Grundlagen des linearen Kontrapunkt</title> (1917)
          and <title level="m">Romantische Harmonik</title> (1920) from M. Drechsel/P. Haupt in the
          1920s. They also published the periodical <title level="j">Die Musik</title> from its
          launching in 1901/02.</p>

        <p>In 1883, with O. A. Becker, Hesse also founded a second publishing house, Hesse &amp;
          Becker for publication of works about art.</p>

        <p>After Max Hesse's death in 1907, its proprietor was Hesse's sole heir, the pianist Ella
          Pancera, and from 1911 <ref cRef="entity-000485">Johann Krill</ref> became joint
          proprietor, taking over as sole proprietor from 1927 until his death in 1946. The firm has
          continued into the 21st century.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Max Hesses Verlag and Schenker</head>
        <p>There is no known contact between Schenker and the publishing house, except for the
          pro-forma invitation of 1913 from Riemann to contribute autobiographical information for
          the entry on Schenker in the <title level="m">Musiklexikon</title> (<ref
            type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-13-23_1">OJ 13/23, [1]</ref>) and Schenker's response
            (<ref type="correspondence" cRef="BerkAE_1">BerkAE, [1]</ref>), and a form letter from
          Einstein on the revision of that entry for the tenth edition of 1922 (OJ 10/17, [1]).</p>
      </div>

    </body>

    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Source</head>

        <listBibl>
          <bibl><title level="m">MGG</title>
            <title level="a">Hesse, Friedrich August Max</title></bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Contributor:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author>Ian Bent</author></bibl><lb/>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
