<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-002408">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Universal Edition (UE)</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="universal_edition">Universal Edition</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>10/02/2009</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="tag">Hertzka ~ HSchenker</term>
          <term subtype="tag">Kalmus ~ HSchenker</term>
          <term subtype="tag">UE ~ H+JSchenker</term>
          <term subtype="tag">UE ~ HSchenker</term>
          <term subtype="category">Organization</term>
          <term subtype="basename">universal_edition</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change><date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Universal Edition (UE)</head>
      <div>
        <p>One of the foremost European music publishing companies of the 20th century, notable
          especially for its promotion of contemporary music; Schenker's principal publisher from
          1901 to 1924, and 1932 to 1935.</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>The Publishing House</head>
        <p>The cooperative creation in 1901 of three Viennese music publishers, Josef Weinberger,
          Bernhard Herzmansky (of Doblinger), and <ref cRef="entity-002439">Adolf Robitschek</ref>,
          Universal Edition was established, with finance from the <ref cRef="entity-002467"
            >Austrian Länderbank</ref> (source: <ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-14-23_7">OJ
            14/23, [7]</ref>, [1903]), to produce music for schools, and editions of the Classical
          composers, in which latter connection Schenker was first engaged in the founding year to
          edit keyboard works by C. P. E. Bach (1903), to which <title level="m">Beitrag zur
            Ornamentik</title> was the companion volume, and arrangements of Handel organ concertos
          (1905). After six years, the company was on the brink of failing when, in 1907, it brought
          in <ref cRef="entity-000356">Emil Hertzka</ref> as its Director. While maintaining the two
          original lines, Hertzka moved contemporary music to the center of UE's enterprise. By
          sound judgement, a keen sense of publishing politics, and skillful negotiation, he
          identified many of the leading progressive and avant-garde composers. By entering into
          agreements with other companies (e.g. Eberle, Josef Aibl, Fürstner, Bote &amp; Bock,
          Simrock) in the first few years, offering contracts to progressive composers (e.g. Mahler,
          Schoenberg, Schreker, Foerster, Bartók, Delius, Webern, Zemlinsky, Szymanovsky, Janácek),
          with many of whom he forged strong personal bonds, and adopting aggressive advertising
          strategies, Hertzka brought to UE the profile of leading publisher of contemporary
          music.</p>
        <p>UE also launched in-house journals--<ref cRef="musikpadagogische_z"><title level="j"
              >Musikpädagogische Zeitschrift</title></ref> (1911), <title level="j">Musica
            divina</title> (1913), <ref cRef="entity-002555"><title level="j">Musikblätter des
              Anbruch</title></ref> (1919), <title level="j">Pult und Taktstock</title> (1924), and
            <title level="j">Schrifttanz</title> (1927)--which offered publicity and forums for
          discussion of UE's catalog; and by acquiring the publishers A. J. Gutmann in 1920 and
          Philharmonischer Verlag in 1927, UE extended its range significantly. Hans Heinsheimer
          joined the company in 1923 to develop its opera catalog. At Hertzka's death in 1932, UE
          was directed jointly by <ref cRef="entity-000968">Hugo Winter</ref>, Heinsheimer, and <ref
            cRef="entity-000420">Alfred Kalmus</ref>, the latter emigrating to England and founding
          UE's London company in 1936.</p>
        <p>As a Jewish company, UE was aryanized during the Nazi period, and much of its stock was
          confiscated, including works by Schenker. After World War II, it resumed its dominant
          position in the publishing of contemporary music, with its influential Darmstadt-inspired
          journal <title level="j">Die Reihe</title>, and the music of Boulez, Stockhausen, Ligeti,
          Berio, Birtwistle, Kagel, Kurtág, Rihm, Schnittke, and others.</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Universal Edition and Schenker</head>
        <p>After his happy first five years with UE, and despite his antipathy toward UE's new
          Director after 1907, Schenker continued to publish with the company, producing the <ref
            cRef="entity-001729">
            <title level="m">Instrumentations-Tabelle</title>
          </ref> (pseudonymous author "Artur Niloff") (1908), the edition of J. S. Bach's <title
            level="m">Chromatic Fantasy &amp; Fugue</title> (1910), the monograph <title level="m"
            >Beethovens Neunte Sinfonie</title> (1912), and the <hi rend="italic"
            >Erläuteruntgsausgaben</hi> of Beethoven's piano sonatas Opp. 109, 110, 111, and 101
          (1913-20). UE also took over from <ref cRef="entity-002405">J. G. Cotta</ref> of Stuttgart
          the publication of Schenker's <title level="m">Harmonielehre</title> and <title level="m"
            >Kontrapunkt 1</title> in November 1921, publishing <title level="m">Kontrapunkt
            2</title> itself in 1922. The nine issues of <title level="j">Der Tonwille</title>
          (1921-24) were published by UE but at arms' length under the pseudonymous imprint of the
          Tonwille-Flugblätterverlag, marketed by <ref cRef="entity-002456">Albert J. Gutmann</ref>
          in Vienna and Hofmeister in Leipzig.</p>
        <p>An out-of-court settlement having been agreed in December 1925 in the face of threatened
          court proceedings, Schenker parted from the company and moved to Drei Masken Verlag of
          Munich, returning later for the <title level="m">Fünf Urlinie-Tafeln / Five Analyses in
            Sketchform</title>, printed by <ref cRef="entity-002402">Waldheim-Eberle</ref> for the
            <ref cRef="entity-002454">David Mannes School of Music</ref> in New York in a print-run
          of 1,000, of which 800 were for New York, 180 for UE to market in Europe, and 20 for
          Schenker and his close associates, <title level="m">Johannes Brahms, Oktaven und Quinten
            u.a.</title> in 1933, and his last work, <title level="m">Der freie Satz</title>,
          published posthumously in 1935.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Sources:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl>Nigel Simeone, "Universal Edition," <hi rend="italic">NGDM2</hi> (2008)</bibl>
          <bibl><title level="m">25 Jahre Neue Musik: Jahrbuch 1926 der Universal-Edition</title>,
            eds. <editor>H. Heinsheimer</editor> &amp; <editor>P. Stefan</editor> (Vienna: UE,
            1926)</bibl>
          <bibl><title level="m">UE: Universal Edition 1901-2001</title> (Vienna: UE, 2000)</bibl>
          <bibl><author>Federhofer, Hellmut</author>, <title level="m">Heinrich Schenker nach
              Tagebücher ...</title> (Hildesheim: Georg Olms, 1985), esp. pp. 31-4, 320-23
            ("Kaufmannsstand-Handel")</bibl>
          <bibl><author>Bent, Ian</author>, <title level="a">'That Bright New Light': Schenker,
              Universal Edition, and the Origins of the Erläuterung Series, 1901-1910,</title>
            <title level="j">Journal of the American Musicological Society</title> 58/1 (Spring
            2005), 69-138</bibl>
          <bibl>General Prefaces to <title level="j">Der Tonwille: Pamphlets in Witness ...</title>,
            ed. <editor>William Drabkin</editor> (New York: Oxford University Press, 2004, 2005), I,
            v-viii, II, v-xii [recounts conflict over <hi rend="italic">Tonwille</hi>]</bibl>
          <bibl><author>Hailey, Christopher</author>, <title level="a">Universal Edition - die
              Anfänge eines Welverlages,</title>
            <title level="j">Österreichische Musikzeitschrift</title> lvi/8-9 (2001), 8-14</bibl>
          <bibl><author>Hailey, Christopher</author>, <title level="a">'Anbruch' and 'Tonwille': the
              Verlagspolitik of Universal Edition,</title> in Eybl-Fink-Mennel (2006), pp.
            59-67</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Contributors:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author>Marko Deisinger and Ian Bent</author></bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
