<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-002405">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>J. G. Cotta'sche Buchhandlung</title>
        <title type="sub">J. G. Cotta's Book Dealership</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="cotta_j_g">Cotta, J. G.</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>27/10/2008</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Organization</term>
          <term subtype="basename">cotta_j_g</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>J. G. Cotta'sche Buchhandlung</head>

      <p>One of Germany's historically most renowned publishers, based since 1810 in Stuttgart.</p>

      <div>
        <head>The firm of J. G. Cotta</head>

        <p>Purchased in 1659 from the widow of a Tübingen bookdealer by Johann Georg Cotta
          (1631-92), the firm was established as "J. G. Cotta'sche Buchhandlung" (J. G. Cotta's Book
          Dealership). A publisher and retail book dealership combined, and from 1722 also a
          printing works, it was associated with Tübingen University until 1810, in which year it
          moved to Stuttgart under Johann Friedrich Cotta. An association with Friedrich Schiller
          and Johann Wolfgang Goethe going back to 1794, including the publication of Schiller's
          monthly philosophical/political journal <title level="j">Die Horen</title> 1795-97,
          brought the company to world-wide fame. Cotta produced a collected edition of Goethe's
          works (1806-10), and went on to publish the collected works of Herder, Schelling, and
          Pestalozzi, and works not only by Schiller, but also by Hölderlin, Hebel, Kerner, Kleist,
          Oehlenschäger, Fouqué, Immermann, Platen, Rückert, and Uhland.</p>

        <p>The company remained in the Cotta family until 1889, when it was acquired by <ref
            cRef="entity-006260">Adolf</ref> and Paul Kröner and given the name "J. G. Cotta'sche
          Buchhandlung Nachfolger" (Successors to J. G. Cotta's Book Dealership). In 1901, a branch
          was established in Berlin. At <ref cRef="entity-006260">Adolf Kröner</ref>'s death in 1911
          (see <ref type="correspondence" cRef="OJ-9-31_32">OJ 9/31, [32]</ref>, March 4, 1911), the
          firm was taken over by <ref cRef="entity-006261">Robert Kröner</ref> and Heinrich Beck. In
          1956, the company was taken over by the Ernst Klett Verlag as "Ernst Klett–J. G.
          Cotta'sche Buchhandlung Nachfolger," or "Klett–Cotta" for short.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Cotta, Schenker, and Music</head>

        <p>On the initial recommendation of <ref cRef="entity-000150">Eugen d'Albert</ref>, Cotta
          published Schenker's first two major theoretical books, <ref cRef="entity-001724"><title
              level="m">Harmonielehre</title></ref> (1906), and <ref cRef="entity-001726"><title
              level="m">Kontrapunkt</title>, first half-volume</ref> = <title level="m">Cantus
            Firmus und Zweistimmiger Satz</title> (1910), these being volumes I and II/1 of his
            <title level="s">Neue Musikalische Theorien und Phantasien</title>. The second
          half-volume of <title level="m">Kontrapunkt</title> was due also for publication by Cotta,
          but was taken over by <ref cRef="entity-002408">Universal Edition</ref>, Vienna in
          November 1921, which then back-published the first two items.</p>

        <p>Both of the works by Schenker were publishing in Cotta's "commissioning publishing house"
            (<hi rend="italic">Kommissionsverlag</hi>). By this arrangement, the publisher handled
          the printing, distribution, and advertising, and then presented the bill for these to the
          author (in Schenker's case, his patron <ref cRef="entity-000743">Baron Alphons
            Rothschild</ref>) for immediate payment; the author then received three-quarters of the
          receipts from sales.</p>

        <p>Cotta was involved in other musical publications, including a series, "Instruktive
          Ausgabe klassischer Klavierwerke," the team of co-editors being listed as "Hans von Bülow,
          Imanuel von Faisst, Ignaz Lachner, Franz von Liszt." In twelve divisions, it included
          works by J. S. Bach (edited by Eugen d'Albert), Beethoven, Chopin, Clementi, Dussek,
          Field, Haydn, Hummel, Mendelssohn, Mozart, Schubert, and Weber. (Information from the
          end-matter of Schenker's <title level="m">Harmonielehre</title>)</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Cotta–Schenker Correspondence</head>

        <p>The archives of the company were purchased in 1954 by the <title level="j">Stuttgarter
            Zeitung</title>, and are now preserved as the Cotta-Archiv at the
          Schiller-Nationalmuseum / Deutsches Literaturarchiv, in Marbach.</p>

        <p>The correspondence between Cotta and Schenker, comprising 325 physical items, is
          preserved in part at the University of California, Riverside, as OJ 5/6 (Schenker to
          Cotta, unsent draft letters, 5 items, 1908-10), OJ 9/31 (Cotta to Schenker originals, 50
          items, 1905-21), OJ 9/32 (41 royalty accounts, sales reports and postal receipts,
          1906-21), OJ 12/23 (Cotta/Kröner to Schenker original, 1 item, 1909), OJ 12/27 (Cotta/Kurz
          to Schenker originals, 15 items, 1906-13), and OJ 12/62 (Cotta/Neff to Schenker originals,
          4 items, 1917-20); and in part in the Cotta-Archiv (Schenker to Cotta originals, Cotta to
          Schenker carbon copies, 209 items, 1905-21).</p>

        <p>Unlike his dealings with his two other main publishers, <ref cRef="entity-002408"
            >Universal Edition</ref> and <ref cRef="entity-002627">Drei Masken Verlag</ref>,
          Schenker was always noticeably deferential to Cotta, doubtless in part because of the
          distinguished history of the company.</p>
      </div>
    </body>

    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Sources:</head>

        <listBibl>
          <bibl><title level="m">Lexikon des gesamten Buchwesens</title> (Stuttgart: Hiersemann,
            2/1987–), vol. II, pp. 187–88</bibl>

          <bibl><title level="m">Wikipedia</title> (<ref type="external"
              target="https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cotta%E2%80%99sche_Verlagsbuchhandlung"
              >"Cotta'sche Verlagbuchhandlung"</ref>)</bibl>
        </listBibl>

      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Contributor</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author><hi rend="bold">Ian Bent</hi></author></bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>

  </text>
</TEI>
