<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0" xml:id="entity-002422">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Edition Peters</title>
        <title type="sub">C. F. Peters Musikverlag</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="peters_edition">Peters, Edition</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>30/10/2008</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Organization</term>
          <term subtype="basename">peters_edition</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change><date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Edition Peters</head>
      <div>
        <p>Leading German publishing house, founded in 1800 in Leipzig, and acquired by Carl
          Friedrich Peters in 1814.</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Correspondence with Schenker</head>
        <p>Twenty-four physical items of correspondence are known to survive between Peters and
          Schenker, amounting to twenty-two distinct communications, not all of which were sent.
          These are preserved as OJ 5/28 (Schenker to Peters, 3 items, undated, 1913, 1934--all
          unsent); in the Sächsisches Archiv, Leipzig (Schenker to Peters, 5 items, 1913-30);
          OC 1 (Schenker to Peters, 18-23, 30-39: carbon copies of 2 Sächsisches Archiv items;
          65-66: carbon copy); OJ 13/17 (Peters to Schenker, 11 items, 1897-1928, cf. OJ 59/14,
          which contains a transcript of a non-extant item, thus bringing this sequence up to 12);
          OC B/278 (Peters to Schenker, 1 item, 1921).</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Dealings with Schenker</head>
        <p>On April 20, 1897, Schenker offered three of his compositions ("<title level="m">Fünf Klavierstücke</title>, Op. 1" and "<title level="m">Legende und zwei
            Scherzi</title>, Op. 2") to Peters for prospective publication. Peters asked to inspect
          them, but rejected them (described now as "<title level="m">Klavierstücke</title>,
          Op. 1-3") on April 27. Peters ultimately did not publish any of Schenker's compositions.</p>
        <p>On September 10, 1913, Schenker was approached by Peters with a view to his producing an
          edition of selected Beethoven piano sonatas, to which he sent a twelve-page reply on
          September 18 making stipulations about the commentaries to the putative editions, followed
          by a nineteen-page letter on October 29 proposing the "Moonlight," "Waldstein,"
          "Appassionata," and "Les Adieux" sonatas, and the E-minor sonata Op. 90, and proposing the
          honorarium. Two months later, communications were severed when it dawned on Peters that
          Schenker already had extensive dealings with <ref cRef="entity-002408">Universal
            Edition</ref>. This correspondence is reported in detail also in Schenker's diary.</p>
        <p>Seven years later, on March 25, 1920, Schenker wrote (and on the same day almost
          identically to <ref cRef="entity-002405">J. G. Cotta</ref> of Stuttgart, and Breitkopf &amp;
          Härtel of Leipzig) what amounts to a prospectus for his planned <ref cRef="entity-001758"><title level="m">Kleine Bibliothek</title></ref>, as well as
          seeking their interest in a complete edition of the Beethoven piano sonatas, only to
          receive an outright rejection of both plans six days later (and from the other two houses
          within the next few days).</p>
        <p>There were further exchanges of letters in 1930 regarding the scores of two concertos by
          J. C. Bach and in 1933-34 regarding an edition of J. S. Bach Inventions.</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Schenker's Attitude toward Peters</head>
        <p>In the 1913 correspondence, Schenker considered Peters' initial approach "inappropriately
          lordly," and its final letter full of "arrogance" and "charlatanerie." He later commented
          to Hertzka at UE:
        
          <cit><q>So you might ask yourself why I cheerfully forewent 12,000-15,000 Kronen
          from Peters, who asked me for some Beethoven sonatas replete with footnotes. Peters
          certainly did not understand me when I tried to make abundantly clear to him that I prefer
          to subject myself to hard work and the exaction of proof, rather than put together an
          edition on the level of Artur Schnabel, Carl Flesch and others that will already require a
          new edition in five-to-ten years' time. I would have been able effortlessly to have
          fashioned footnotes a thousand times better and more ample for the requested sonatas,
          given my intimate acquaintance with the material, and done it all within a year, and
          nevertheless I turned the proposal down. (draft letter, OJ 5/16, [2], May 1914; final
          letter, modified, WSLB 211)</q></cit></p>
        
        <p>And he later remarked: "If only Peters had had the intelligence to invite me to provide
          not just fingerings but '<hi rend="italic">elucidations</hi>'"! (letter to Hertzka, WSLB
          236, January 18, 1915). The same letter reveals Schenker's disillusionment with Austria
          and re-evaluation of Germany: "So why is it that the Austrian publishing companies up to
          now (notwithstanding Doblinger [and] Robitschek are certainly filthy rich businessmen)
          have none of the quality that the German ones do; why, I ask, if not the failure to
          recognize the material importance of great authors?" His estimate of the great Leipzig
          publishing houses rose steadily at the cost of UE.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Contributors:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author>Marko Deisinger and Ian Bent</author></bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
