<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-006149">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Josef Weinberger</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="weinberger_josef">Weinberger, Josef [company]</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>08/05/2008</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Organization</term>
          <term subtype="basename">weinberger_josef</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change><date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Josef Weinberger</head>
      <div>
        <p>Viennese music-publishing house from 1890 to the present day, publisher of Schenker's
            <title level="m">Syrian Dances</title>.</p>

        <div>
          <head>History of the Company</head>
          <p><ref cRef="entity-000946">Josef Weinberger</ref> founded a music-publishing firm in
            partnership with Carl Hofbauer on November 1, 1885 as Josef Weinberger &amp; Carl
            Hofbauer, Kunst- und Musikalienhandel [art and sheet-music dealers], Vienna I,
            Kärntnerstraße 34. At first it confined itself to light music for male-, female-, and
            mixed-voice chorus; but in 1887 it received a license to publish opera, operetta, and
            ballet music. In 1889, Weinberger set up a company in Leipzig with Carl Günther, owner
            of the Hofmeister Verlag. </p>

          <p>The partnership with Hofbauer eventually split up, and on January 1, 1890 Weinberger
            established his own Vienna company on the Kohlmarkt. In the 1890s, the firm acquired the
            rights to publish vocal scores of some of Smetana's operas with German translation. In
            the late 1890s it became the publisher of several works by Gustav Mahler including
            orchestral scores of Symphonies 1‒3. In 1894, Weinberger bought up the Austrian firm of
              <ref cRef="entity-002413">Artaria</ref>; in 1897 he took over the catalogue of Gustav
            Léwy, publisher of Johann Strauss II and others; and upon the death of Johann Strauss II
            in 1899 he acquired from Strauss's family the exclusive stage rights to his works. In
            1902, Weinberger procured the rights to works by Wolf-Ferrari. These events established
            Weinberger as a leading publisher of light theatrical music. In 1896, the firm opened a
            headquarters in Paris, and by 1900 its elaborately engraved letterhead was able to
            proclaim: <cit>
              <q>Josef Weinberger<lb/>Bühnen-Verlag [—]
                Musikalien-Verlags-Handlungen<lb/>[Theatrical Publisher [—] Publisher of Sheet
                Music]<lb/>Wien Kohlmarkt No. 8 / Leipzig Querstrasse No. 13 / Paris 78, Rue
                d'Anjou</q>
            </cit>
          </p>

          <p>In 1900, the firm outgrew its premises on the Kohlmarkt and established itself at
            Maximilianstraße (now Mahlerstraße) 11, across the road from the Opera House. This
            building became also the headquarters of the newly launched <ref cRef="entity-002408"
              >Universal Edition</ref> in 1901, a collaborative venture between Weinberger, <ref
                cRef="entity-000359">Bernhard Herzmansky</ref> (of Doblinger) and <ref cRef="entity-000720">Adolf
            Robitschek</ref>.</p>

          <p>The Weinberger firm continued independently of UE under Weinberger's control, and after
            his death in 1928 under that of Otto Blau (1893‒1980). In 1936, Blau established a
            headquarters in London under the management of Hugo Golwig. The Vienna firm was
            aryanized after the Anschluß in 1938 and the operation shifted to the Berlin branch,
            while Blau moved to London, then Australia. The firm was re-established in Vienna in
            1946, and the Maximilianstraße premises were re-occupied in 1947. The company regained
            its former standing, and continues to trade in the 21st century, with headquarters in
            Vienna, Frankfurt, and London.</p>
        </div>

      </div>

      <div>
        <head>The Josef Weinberger company and Schenker</head>
        <p>Weinberger published Schenker's <ref cRef="entity-001664"><title level="m">Syrian
              Dances</title></ref> [Syrische Tänze] for four hands two pianos, in two volumes in
          October 1899. Weinberger was involved again in 1903, overseeing the part-copying and
          marketing, when <ref cRef="entity-000798">Arnold Schoenberg</ref> orchestrated the <title
            level="m">Syrian Dances</title> for performance in Berlin in November of that year.</p>

        <p>Nine items of correspondence from Weinberger to Schenker survive: three undated calling
          cards as OJ 15/12, [1]‒[3] probably from the late 1890s; five letters with the Weinberger
          letterhead as OJ 15/12, [5] from 1900, and OJ 15/12, [6]‒[8] and [11] from 1903; and one
          letter with the UE letterhead as OC 52/11 from 1903. (The latter six all concern the
            <title level="m">Syrian Dances</title>). No correspondence from Schenker to Weinberger
          is known to survive.</p>
      </div>

    </body>

    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Sources</head>

        <listBibl>
          <bibl><title level="m">Grove Music Online</title> (<title level="a">Weinberger,
              Josef</title>)</bibl>

          <bibl><author>Johann Michel</author> and <author>Richard Toeman</author>, <title level="m"
              >100 Jahre Bühen- und Musikalienverlag Josef Weinberger 1885‒1985</title> (Vienna:
            Weinberger, 1985)</bibl>

          <bibl><title level="m">100 Years Remembered: A History of the Theatre and Music Publishers
              Josef Weinberger Vienna, Frankfurt am Main, London, 1885‒1985</title> (London:
            Weinberger, [1985])</bibl>

          <bibl><title level="m">Heinrich Schenker: Selected Correspondence</title>, ed. <editor>Ian
              Bent</editor>, <editor>David Bretherton</editor>, and <editor>William Drabkin</editor>
            (Woodbridge: The Boydell Press, 2015), esp. pp. 34, 41, 43, 59‒60, 62</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Contributor:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author>Ian Bent</author></bibl>
          <lb/>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
