<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-002499">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Seminar 1931‒34 (Schenker)</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="seminar_1931_34">Seminar 1931‒34 (Schenker)</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>08/05/2008</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Organization</term>
          <term subtype="basename">seminar_1931_34</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change><date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Seminar 1931‒34 (Schenker)</head>
      <div>
        <p>Informally constituted seminar conducted by Schenker with four members in 1931‒34.</p>

        <p>The seminar, conducted by Schenker, comprised four former members of a seminar taught by
            <ref cRef="entity-000951">Hans Weisse</ref>: <ref cRef="entity-000754">Felix
            Salzer</ref>, <ref cRef="entity-000473">Trude Kral</ref>, <ref cRef="entity-002498"
            >Greta Kraus</ref>, and <ref cRef="entity-000964">Manfred H. Willfort</ref> ‒ a group
          known familiarly as the "seminarists" (<hi rend="italic">Seminaristen</hi>). Its formation
          was suggested to Schenker by Weisse on April 12, 1931: <cit>
            <q>Weisse proposes that I take over four of the students in his seminar, who could also
              help with the preparation of the [Urlinie] folios . . . (diary, OJ 4/4, p. 3605)</q>
          </cit></p>

        <p>Schenker’s seminar first convened in the fall of 1931, after Weisse had left Vienna for
          New York on September 17. It met weekly on Fridays — thus was sometimes dubbed the "Friday
          Seminar" — throughout the teaching seasons of 1931/32, 1932/33, and 1933/34. Before the
          first meeting on October 9, Schenker issued a list of compositions to be analyzed
          (reproduced in Salzer, pp. 18‒19). The work of the group in 1931/32 resulted in the
          publication of five graphs as <ref cRef="entity-001755"><title level="m">Fünf
              Urlinie-Tafeln/Five Analyses in Sketchform</title></ref> (New York: David Mannes Music
          School, 1932). <cit>
            <q>Each of us was assigned a different composition; the work on the voice-leading graphs
              went through many stages until they represented Schenker's point of view. [...] I am
              in no position to state when Schenker himself had completed analytic work on these
              five compositions. It was my impression that it was done before our sessions began
              [...]" (Salzer, pp. 19‒20). </q>
          </cit></p>


        <p>Only Schenker's name appeared on the title-page, and Schenker made no mention of the
          students in his Foreword. The publication was planned as the first of a series of similar
          publications, but no further volumes were issued. Analyses for the second volume prepared
          in the seminar ‒ including graphs and sketches of Beethoven, Sonata Op. 27, No. 2; Mozart,
          Fantasy in D minor, K. 397; Chopin, Etude Op. 10, No. 3; Brahms, <title level="m">Auf dem
            Kirchhofe</title>, Op. 105, No. 4; and Brahms, Paganini Variations, Op. 3 ‒ are
          preserved in the Felix Salzer Papers, Music Division, New York Public Library (FS 28). </p>

        <p>Information about the activities of the seminar is given in Schenker's final set of
          lesson notes, those for the season 1931/32: OC 16/39 (Oct 9–Nov 20, 1931), 40 (Nov 27,
          1931–Feb 12, 1932), 41 (Feb 12–May 13, 1932), and 42 (May 19–23, 1932). Further
          information can be found in Schenker's correspondence, notably that with Felix Salzer and
          Oswald Jonas. </p>

        <p>Kral dropped out of the seminar after the first year. In June 1934 Schenker decided to
          let Kraus and Willfort go, and continue with Salzer as a private student (FS 40/1, [22],
          June 6, 1934, letter to Salzer). Thus the seminar was dissolved at the end of the 1933/34
          season after three years. </p>

        <p>Just before the publication of the <title level="j">Fünf Urlinie-Tafeln</title>, which
          took place in the last week of July 1932, Schenker debated offering the seminar to the
          public with the aim of producing further volumes. His diary for July 16 summarizes a
          non-extant letter to <ref cRef="entity-000164">Otto Erich Deutsch</ref>: <cit>
            <q>the first volume is – <hi rend="italic">quod erat demonstrandum</hi> – an achievement
              of the seminar and [brings in] 1,250 shillings; thus it is artistically and
              financially justified, if I can avail myself of a class (= seminar) and raise my fees,
              which are so low, in order to be able to publish more volumes.</q>
          </cit></p>

        <p>Deutsch’s response (<ref cRef="OJ-10-3_174">OJ 10/3, [174]</ref>, July 21, 1932) lists
          the topics Schenker had in mind, “Urlinie, thoroughbass, manuscript study, and
          performance”– questioned by Deutsch as perhaps too wide-ranging – and suggests newspapers
          and journals in which advertisements for the seminar could be posted. Whether Schenker
          pursued this further, the plan did not come to fruition.</p>


      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Sources:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author>Salzer, Felix</author>, <title level="a">Introduction,</title>
            <title level="m">Five Graphic Music Analyses (Fünf Urlinie-Tafeln)</title> (New York:
            Dover Publications, 1969), pp. 13‒21. </bibl>

          <bibl><author>Schenker, Heinrich</author>, <title level="a">Graphic Analysis of Brahms's
              Auf dem Kirchhofe, Op. 105, No. 4,</title> as prepared for publication by
              <editor>William J. Mitchell</editor> and <editor>Felix Salzer</editor>, with an
            introduction by <editor>Hedi Siegel</editor> and a commentary by <editor>Arthur
              Maisel</editor>, <title level="j">Theory and Practice</title> 13 (1989), pp. 1‒14.
          </bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Contributors:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author>Hedi Siegel</author> and <author>Ian Bent</author>
          </bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
