<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-002402">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Waldheim-Eberle</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="waldheimeberle">Waldheim-Eberle</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>08/05/2008</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Organization</term>
          <term subtype="basename">waldheimeberle</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change><date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Waldheim-Eberle</head>
      <div>
        <p>Viennese firm of printers, lithographers, and music engravers.</p>
        <p>The printing firm of R. v. Waldheim, involved in newspaper printing, was founded in 1892,
          and within a few years went into partnership with the lithography and music-engraving firm
          of Josef Eberle &amp; Co. By 1918, the joint firm of R. v. Waldheim, Josef Eberle &amp;
          Co., also known as Waldheim-Eberle, located at Vienna VII, Seidengasse 3-11, encompassed
          book printing, lithography, music engraving, music printing, book binding, and other types
          of printing. The Josef Eberle published works with its own imprint, including early works
          by Franz Schreker, e.g. the symphonic overture <title level="m">Ekkehard</title>, Op. 12,
          and choral-orchestral work <title level="m">Schwanengesang</title>, Op. 11 (1903). At the
          beginning of the Nazi era in Austria, the firm was taken over by the aryanized firm of M.
          Müller &amp; Sohn.</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Waldheim-Eberle and Schenker</head>
        <p>Schenker's <ref cRef="entity-001729">
            <hi rend="italic">Instrumentations-Tabelle</hi>
          </ref> (pseudonymously published under the name Artur Niloff) was initially to have been
            <hi rend="italic">published</hi> by Waldheim-Eberle, but negotiations in 1905 with its
          Director, Josef Stritzko, failed. Universal Edition, which used Waldheim-Eberle for much
          of its engraving and printing (notable cases being Mahler's <title level="m">Das Lied von
            der Erde</title>, Schoenberg's <title level="m">Pierrot lunaire</title>, and Janáček's
            <title level="m">Kát'a Kabanová</title>), took the work over and published it in 1909,
          the engraver being Waldheim-Eberle. Already in 1902/03, and in its second edition in 1908,
          Schenker's <title level="m">Beitrag zur Ornamentik</title> was produced for UE by
          Waldheim-Eberle, as was his edition of J. S. Bach's <title level="m">Chromatic Fantasy
            &amp; Fugue</title> (1910).</p>
        <p>The firm also engraved the complex graphs for the three yearbooks of <title level="j">Das
            Meisterwerk in der Musik</title> (1925, 1926, 1930), albeit they were published by <ref
            cRef="entity-002627">Drei Masken Verlag</ref> of Munich; and those of the <title
            level="m">Fünf Urlinie-Tafeln / Five Analyses in Sketchform</title>, published by the
            <ref cRef="entity-002454">David Mannes Music School</ref> of New York in conjunction
          with UE in 1932. Others of Schenker's UE publications may also have been engraved and/or
          printed by the firm.</p>
        <p>Waldheim-Eberle must have played an important ancillary role in the development of
          Schenker's analytic symbolic system.</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Correspondence with Schenker</head>
        <p>Fifty-two items of correspondence from Waldheim-Eberle and Georg Tomay to Schenker
          survive as OJ 15/8 (6 items: 1905–08), OC 32/107 (1925), OC 54/121 (1927), OC 54/195-217,
          221-223, 342-352 (1930), OC 54/355-362 (1932). </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
