<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0" xml:id="entity-002452">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Photogrammarchiv</title>
        <title type="sub">Archive of Photographic Images</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="photogrammarchiv">Photogrammarchiv</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>02/08/2006</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="tag">Hoboken ~ HSchenker</term>
<term subtype="category">Organization</term>
          <term subtype="basename">photogrammarchiv</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Photogrammarchiv</head>

      <div>
        <p> Archive of photographic images (negatives; photostatic prints at original size) of "the
          most important manuscripts of the great composers," housed in the Music Department of the
          Austrian National Library from 1927, located at Vienna I, Augustinerbastei 6, and donated
          to that Library in 1957.</p>

        <p>Its full original name was "Archiv für Photogramme musikalischer
          Meisterhandschriften" (Archive for Photographic Images of Musical Master Manuscripts), but
          was customarily abbreviated to "Photogrammarchiv" or to "Meister-Archiv" (Master Archive).</p>
      </div>
      
      <div>
        <head>Purpose of the Archive</head>
        <p>The primary purpose of the
          Photogrammarchiv was to place on public record the original autograph intentions of
          composers as a bulwark against faulty and wilfully altered editions. The Photogrammarchiv
          was to be accessible to scholars and devotees of music for study.</p>
        
        <p>The value of the Photogrammarchiv was enhanced by the fact that the original manuscripts
        of many of its photographic copies were lost or destroyed during World War II.</p>
        </div>

       <div>
         <head>History of the Archive</head>
         
        <p>The archive was founded in August 1927 (<title level="m">NGDM2</title>) and launched
          publicly in November of that year in the form of an "Appeal" (<ref cRef="entity-002418">Aufruf</ref>) issued by a curatorial board comprising <ref cRef="entity-000380">Anthony van Hoboken</ref>, Heinrich Schenker, and <ref cRef="entity-000320">Robert Haas</ref> (Director of the Music Division), and officially
          opened on November 25, 1928 (vC 21). The archive was assembled by Anthony van Hoboken at
          the instigation of his teacher, Heinrich Schenker. Its secretary in the 1930s was Julius
          Ritter von Kromer, with whom Schenker corresponded. Its initial target repertory
          comprised: "the most important works of J. S. Bach, Handel, Haydn, Mozart,
          Beethoven, Schubert and Chopin, as well as of Domenico Scarlatti, C. P. E. Bach, Brahms
          and perhaps also of François Couperin." Already by 1934, the
          collection numbered over 30,000 pages. The "Appeal" was directed at
          public and private collections, individual collectors, and antiquarian dealers to make the
          manuscripts in their possession available for photography.</p> 
       </div>
      
      <div>
        <head>Schenker's Rationale</head>

        <p>From early in his career, Schenker upheld the consultation of autograph manuscripts and
          early editions as essential not only for the editing of a work but also for its study and
          analysis. His study-editions of the <title level="m">Chromatic Fantasy &amp;
          Fugue</title> of J. S. Bach and the late piano sonatas of Beethoven are exemplary of this
          principle. His belief in the need for a photographic archive long predates the founding of
          the Photogrammarchiv; alluding to the sound archives founded by Sigmund Exner at the
          Austrian Academy Sciences in Vienna in 1899, and perhaps also that founded by Carl Stumpf
          in Berlin in 1900, for ethnographic materials, both called
          "Phonogrammarchiv," Schenker wrote a memorandum to the Austrian
          Ministry of Culture on July 19, 1913 stating:

          <cit><q>... that it is high time to preserve the originals from destruction, and to take
          official action [to this end]. If there are sound archives [<hi rend="italic">Phonogrammarchive</hi>] in the academies of sciences or arts that preserve those things
          worthy of being remembered, why not archives of autographs? (letter to Emil Hertzka: WSLB
          167, p.9)</q></cit></p>


        </div>
        
        <div>
          <head>Correspondence with Schenker</head>
        <p>Correspondence between Schenker and the Photogrammarchiv and its officials is preserved
          at OJ 9/10, also at OJ 11/32 and OC A/294 (Haas), OJ 11/54 and OJ 89 (Hoboken), OJ 12/24,
          OC 30/64 and 119, OC A/293 (Kromer), and there are numerous references to it in Schenker's
          other correspondence.</p>
        </div>
    </body>


        <back><div>
          <head>Sources:</head>

        <listBibl>
          <bibl><title level="m">NGMD2</title>: <title level="a">Hoboken</title>; <title level="a">Libraries:
            Berlin, Vienna</title>; <title level="a">Sound Archives: History, Europe-Austria</title></bibl>
          
        <bibl><author>Oswald Jonas</author>, <title level="a">Schenker's Editorial Work and the Vienna Photostat
          Archive,</title> Appendix B of <title level="m">Das Wesen des musikalischen
            Kunstwerks: Einführung in die Lehre Heinrich Schenkers</title> (Vienna;
          Saturn-Verlag, 1934; Eng. trans. John Rothgeb, New York: Longman, 1982, repr. Musicalia
          Press, 2006)</bibl>
        </listBibl>
        </div>
        </back>

  </text>
</TEI>
