<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-004002">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Doblinger</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="doblinger">Doblinger (Publishing House)</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>08/05/2008</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Organization</term>
          <term subtype="basename">doblinger</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change><date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Doblinger</head>
      <div>
        <p>Viennese music publishing house, music retail business, and lending library.</p>

        <p>The firm can be traced back to 1817 as a music library which from 1825 sold antiquarian
          music. In 1857, it was acquired by Ludwig Doblinger (1809‒76), and expanded into a retail
          shop, the Musikhaus Doblinger, in Vienna's first district at Dorotheegasse 10 (where it
          still operates today), and a publishing house (Verlag Doblinger), which quickly
          established itself as one of the leading publishers of Viennese operettas. In 1876, it
          passed to <ref cRef="entity-000359">Bernhard Herzmansky senior</ref> (1852‒1921), under
          whom it acquired the publishing rights for music by Bruckner (Symphonies Nos 1, 2, 5, 6,
          and 9) and other contemporary composers, including Dohnányi and Mahler (Symphony No. 4),
          in 1923 initiating in-house chamber concerts of music by composers such as Ernst Křenek,
          Arnold Schoenberg, and Anton Webern, and becoming one of Vienna's foremost music
          publishers. In 1921 the firm passed to his son Bernhard Herzmansky junior (1888‒1954). He
          was forbidden to work during the Nazi period, but the firm continued during and after
          World War II, in 1954 passing to his nephew Christian Wolf, and in 1980 to Helmuth
          Pany.</p>

        <p>Herzmansky senior collaborated with <ref cRef="entity-000946">Josef Weinberger</ref>,
            <ref cRef="entity-000720">Adolf Robitschek</ref> (of Rebay &amp; Robitschek), and Carl
          Stampel in 1901 to found <ref cRef="entity-002408">Universal Edition</ref>. Between 1903
          and 1910, substantial parts of Doblinger's catalog were incorporated into that of
          Universal Edition.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Doblinger and Schenker</head>
        <p>In 1892, Schenker's <title>Zwei Klavierstücke, Op. 1</title> were published by Doblinger;
          and in 1906 Schenker had a verbal agreement with Doblinger and Eberle (as recorded in
          Schenker's diary) to publish what was later published by Universal Edition as his <ref
            cRef="entity-001729"><title level="m">Instrumentations-Tabelle</title></ref> (1908).
          There is no known surviving correspondence between Schenker and the publishing house.</p>
      </div>

    </body>

    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Sources</head>

        <listBibl>
          <bibl><title level="m">OEM Lexikon</title> (online)</bibl>

          <bibl><title level="m">Grove's Dictionary Online</title> (2016)</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Contributor:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author>Ian Bent</author></bibl>
          <lb/>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
