<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-002451">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Neues Wiener Konservatorium</title>
        <title type="sub">New Vienna Conservatory</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="neues_wiener_konserv">Neues Wiener Konservatorium</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>03/08/2009</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Organization</term>
          <term subtype="basename">neues_wiener_konserv</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Neues Wiener Konservatorium</head>

      <div>
        <p>Private music school founded by Theobald Kretschmann (a court musician) in 1909, and
          existing until 1938. Its directors were Emerich Bénesi (1909-10), Franz Ondricek
          (1910-15), and Josef Reitler (1915-38).</p>

        <p>The school was known initially as the "Privatmusikschule Theobald Kretschmann," and was
          founded as a private institution at the same moment that the Vienna Conservatory,
          originally named Konservatorium der Gesellschaft der Musikfreunde, was transformed from a
          private institution into a state institution as the Akademie für Musik und darstellende
          Kunst. Application by the Kretschmann school to adopt the name "Neues Wiener
          Konservatorium" met with powerful opposition at that time and was repeatedly refused by
          the Ministry of Education on grounds that it would give rise to confusion in the public's
          mind between it and the Akademie, and unfair competition between its faculty and that of
          the latter. Although the sought-after name, and also "Neues Konservatorium für Musik,"
          were used unofficially, opposition was not dropped until 1932, after the school's
          reputation and standing had steadily increased during the 1920s.</p>

        <p>From the beginning, the school offered a more broadly based musical education than that
          of the Akademie, for amateurs as well as future professionals; its teaching was based on
          class instruction, to which specialist study of instruments, voice, chorus, theory,
          composition, etc. were regarded as "supplementary studies." Its teaching was to a great
          extent complementary to that of the professionally-oriented Akademie.</p>

        <p>As early as 1912, the school was in financial trouble. It moved its premises from
          Jakobergasse 5 to Strauchgasse 4 (both in Vienna I), and the curriculum underwent
          expansion. An association (Verein) to support the school was founded then. In 1921, an
          opera school was set up. In the 1930s, the school instituted courses for operetta and
          cabaret, jazz orchestra, film, radio, and other subjects. The Gesellschaft der
          Musikfreunde eventually made space available to it within the Musikverein Building, Vienna
          I, Bösendorferstraße 12, and the school later opened additional premises at
          Himmelpfortgasse 11.</p>

        <p>Its teachers over the years included many well-known names, such as Ernst Décsey
          (theory), Hans Gál (composition), Alfred Grünfeld (piano), Josef Labor (organ), Carl
          Lafite (theory), Rudolf Nilius (conducting), Robert Pollak (violin), Richard Specht
          (aesthetics), Karl Weigl (theory), Egon Wellesz (theory), and Paul Wittgenstein
          (piano).</p>

        <p>In 1938, after the Anschluß, many teachers were dismissed or pensioned off on racial
          grounds, and the school was closed in the Fall of that year. Some of the remaining
          teachers were then appointed to the faculty of a new institution, the Musikschule der
          Stadt Wien.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>The Schenker Institute</head>

        <p>A Schenker-Institut was established within the Neues Wiener Konservatorium months after
          Schenker's death in 1935: see the opening anouncement by Carl Bamberger (1936). Although
          not officially recognized in the school's statutes, it existed <hi rend="italic">de
            facto</hi> for three years and its surviving classbooks and lists provide evidence of
          the courses taught and personnel involved. Felix Salzer, Oswald Jonas, and also Moriz
          Violin were its teachers, working at the Himmelpfortgasse premises and hiring rooms at the
          Musikverein Building. Its students included some who had studied with Schenker until his
          death (notably Eveline Pairamall, Käthe Pollak, Hilde Rubinraut, and Hans Wolf), one
          sister of a former Schenker pupil (Gerty Bamberger, later wife of former Schenker pupil
          Viktor Zuckerkandl), one future wife of a Schenker pupil (Lotte Hammerschlag), and other
          students including most notably Erwin Ratz and Helmuth Federhofer.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Correspondence</head>

        <p>No correspondence is known to exist between the Neues Wiener Konservatorium and Schenker,
          nor is there any among the Jonas or Violin papers, nor the Felix Salzer papers.</p>
      </div>
    </body>

    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Sources:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><title level="m">NGDM2</title></bibl>

          <bibl><author>Bamberger, Carl</author>, <title level="a">Das Schenker-Institut am Neuen
              Wiener Konservatorium,</title>
            <title level="j">Musikblättter des Anbruch</title> 18/1 (1936), pp. 7–8 [opening
            announcement]</bibl>

          <bibl><author>Fink, Evelyn</author>, <title level="a">Analyse nach Heinrich Schenker an
              Wiener Musiklehranstalten: Ein Beitrag zur Schenker-Rezeption in Wien,</title> in
              <editor>Fink, E.</editor>, ed., <title level="m">Rebell und Visionär: Heinrich
              Schenker in Wien</title> (Vienna: Lafite, 2003), pp. 18-35</bibl>

          <bibl><author>Fink-Mennel, Evelyn</author>, <title level="a">Das Schenker-Institut und der
              Lehrgang für Tonsatz nach Heinrich Schenker: Zur Wiener Schenker-Tradition,</title> in
              <title level="m">Schenker-Traditionen</title>, ed. <editor>Martin Eybl</editor> &amp;
              <editor>Evelyn Fink-Mennel</editor> (Vienna: Böhlau Verlag, 2006), pp. 155–68)</bibl>

          <bibl>website: http://www.levwien.at/?site=st20070521191053 (Landes Eltern Vertretung der
            Musikschülerinnen in Wien)</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>


  </text>
</TEI>
