<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0" xml:id="entity-002421">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Bösendorfer</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="bosendorfer">Bösendorfer</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>16/07/2008</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="tag">Bösendorfer ~ HSchenker</term>
          <term subtype="category">Organization</term>
          <term subtype="basename">bosendorfer</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change><date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Bösendorfer</head>
      <div>
        <p>Austrian piano manufacturing firm based in Vienna.</p>
        <p>The firm was founded in 1828 by Ignaz Bösendorfer (1796-1859). Liszt's approval of its
          instruments brought it international fame, and in 1830 the firm was granted the title
          kaiserlicher und königlicher Hof- und Kammerklavierverfertiger (Imperial and Royal Court
          and Chamber Piano Manufacturer). Ignaz's son, <ref cRef="entity-000090">Ludwig
            Bösendorfer</ref> (1835-1919), took over the business in 1859, bringing the company to
          its highest point of achievement with the distinctive Viennese action of its (largely
          grand) pianos, and resisting the mass-production methods of other manufacturers.</p>
        <p>The firm moved to its new factory in the Türkenstraße, in the 9th district of Vienna
          (Alsergrund), in 1860, which had a concert hall attached. In 1870, the manufacturing side
          of the business relocated to Graf Starhemberggasse 14, in Vienna's 4th district (Wieden),
          and the retail side to the Palais Liechtenstein, in the Herrengasse, in the 1st district
          (Innere Stadt). The riding school of the latter premises was converted to a concert hall,
          which as the Bösendorfer-Saal was one of Vienna's most highly-prized halls for solo
          recitals and chamber music from 1872 until demolished in 1913 to make way for a larger
          building project. </p>
        <p>Ludwig sold the firm to Carl Hutterstrasser in 1909, whose sons, Alexander and Wolfgang,
          succeeded Carl in 1931. The company was purchased by the parent company of Kimbell Pianos
          in 1966, and since 2007 has been a wholly owned subsidiary of Yamaha. The current
          Bösendorfer-Saal is on the Graf Starhemberggasse site.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Sources:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><title level="m">NGDM1</title> and <title level="m">2</title></bibl>
          <bibl>
            <title level="m">OeML Online</title>
          </bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Links:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl>
            <ref target="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/B%C3%B6sendorfer" type="external"><title level="m">Wikipedia</title> ("Bösendorfer")</ref>
          </bibl>
          <bibl>
            <ref target="http://www.rodoni.ch/busoni/cronologia/Note/boesendorfer.html" type="external">Bösendorfer: History of the Grand Piano</ref>
          </bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
