<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0" xml:id="entity-002430">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Gesellschaft der Musikfreunde</title>
        <title type="sub">Society for the Friends of Music</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="gesellschaft_der_mus">Gesellschaft der Musikfreunde</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>11/08/2008</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="tag">Gesellschaft der Musikfreunde ~ HSchenker</term>
          <term subtype="tag">Lafite ~ HSchenker</term>
          <term subtype="tag">Marchet ~ HSchenker</term>
<term subtype="category">Organization</term>
          <term subtype="basename">gesellschaft_der_mus</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change><date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Gesellschaft der Musikfreunde</head>
      <div>
        <p>Association of musical amateurs, of central importance to the musical life of Vienna
          since the early 19th century.</p>
        <p>The Gesellschaft der Musikfreunde was founded in 1812 as an association of noble and
          middle-class music amateurs in Vienna. It devoted itself primarily to three major tasks:
          the organizing of <hi rend="italic">concerts</hi>, the collecting of <hi rend="italic">documentary materials</hi> of all types relating to music and musical life, and the
          administering of a <hi rend="italic">conservatory</hi>. The last of these, officially
          named the Konservatorium der Gesellschaft der Musikfreunde, developed into the foremost
          music-educational center of the Austrian–Hungarian monarchy, and devolved into a
          state institution in 1909.</p>
        <p>The principal instigators of the Gesellschaft were Franziska von Arnstein, the brothers
          Joseph and Ignaz Sonnleithner, Ignaz Franz von Mosel and Joseph Franz Prince Lobkowitz.
          Its protector was the Archduke Rudolf, and the members of its administration over the
          course of its history included such notable personalities as Antonio Salieri, Johannes
          Brahms, Ludwig Bösendorfer, Wilhelm Furtwängler, Richard Strauss and Nikolaus
          Dumba.</p>
        <p>The concerts organized by the Gesellschaft took place mostly in the Redouten halls of the
          Vienna Hofburg and in the old Musikverein Building („Haus zum roten Igel“
          Unter den Tuchlauben), up to the time that the new Musikverein Building, designed by
          Theophil Hansen, was built and ceremonially opened in 1870.</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Archive</head>
        <p>The documentary and scholarly aims of the Gesellschaft der Musikfreunde were embodied in
          its Archive, which was subdivided as follows, according to contents:</p>
        <p>1. <hi rend="italic">Archive:</hi> autographs of music and letters, music manuscripts,
          the archival records of the Gesellschaft itself and of the Conservatory;</p>
        <p>2. <hi rend="italic">Library:</hi> manuscripts and printed books (including medieval
          music manuscripts and tabulatures), songbooks, newspapers and other periodicals, libretti,
          and printed documents of various sorts;</p>
        <p>3. <hi rend="italic">Collections:</hi> early and non-European music instruments, musical
          memorabilia, collections of portraits and pictures, busts, statuettes, reliefs and medals.</p>
        <p>The Archive of the Gesellschaft is one of the most important and valuable music
          collections in Austria. Among the libraries and personal papers acquired by the Archive
          are those of Johann Gottfried Walther, Antonio Caldara, Ernst Ludwig Gerber, Antonio
          Salieri, Simon Sechter, Carl Czerny, Ludwig Ritter von Köchel, Johannes Brahms, and
          Ludwig Bösendorfer.</p>
        <p>The Archive was accommodated in the erstwhile Conservatory of the Gesellschaft in the
          Bösendorferstraße 12, in Vienna's first district. After the Conservatory was
          taken over by the state, and under its new name of Akademie für Musik und
          darstellende Kunst acquired its own building in the Lothringerstraße in 1913, the
          Gesellschaft acquired extra space in its own premises and was able to move the Archive
          from its restricted quarters on the ground floor to the second storey, where it remains to
          the present day.</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>The Gesellschaft and Heinrich Schenker</head>
        <p>Schenker was a regular attender of the concerts organized by the Gesellschaft, and
          recorded comments on them in his diaries over many years. He also made frequent use of the
          Archive's resources, his first recorded visit being on April 12, 1907: "In the Archive of
          the Conservatory; Mr. Mandyczewski shows me sketches, letters, and autograph manuscripts
          by Beethoven, Mozart, etc, and plays the "Kielflügel with the Jalousieschweller
          [Venetian swells]." (OJ 1/6, p. 38). In 1908, he sent the Gesellschaft complimentary
          copies of his <hi rend="italic">Beitrag zur Ornamentik</hi>, 2nd edn, and <hi rend="italic">Harmonielehre</hi> (WSLB 14; CA 76), both at the request of Mandyczewsky
          (diary, OJ 1/7, pp. 89a, 94). From 1913, Schenker made particularly intensive use of the
          Archive while working on his <hi rend="italic">Die letzten fünf Sonaten von
          Beethoven</hi> (1913–20).</p>
        <p>Invited in June 1912 to contribute a lecture or group of lectures to a popular centenary
          series promoted by the Gesellschaft, Schenker's offer of a yearlong course on harmonic
          theory led to months of acrimony between him and the Society's officials, further fuelling
          his animosity toward Viennese officialdom. In May 1933, Schenker attended the opening
          ceremony and at least one concert of the Brahms centenary festival in the Musikverein
          Building at the invitation of the Gesellschaft.</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Schenker's correspondence with the Gesellschaft</head>
        <p>The officials with whom Schenker had dealings were Gustav Marchet (President
          1912–16), Ernst Kraus (Vice-President 1908–38), Carl Lafite (General
          Secretary 1912–21), and Friedrich Dlabač (General Secretary 1921–38).
          Schenker's correspondence with the Gesellschaft is preserved as OJ 5/14 (1912: 2 items)
          and 11/22 (1912, 1916, 1932/33: 7 items), that with Lafite as OJ 5/23 (1912: 2 items) and
          12/29 (1912: 5 items, plus 3 items from 1902–04 unrelated to Gesellschaft
          business), and that with Ernst Kraus as OJ 12/20 (1925, 1935: 2 items); there are eight
          items in the Gesellschaft Archive (Akten: 5 items; Briefe: 3 items); some of these items,
          however, duplicate each other, the total number of items being twenty-one.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Sources:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author>Biba, Otto</author>, <title level="a">Gesellschaft der Musikfreunde in
            Wien,</title> in: <title level="m">oeML</title>, vol. 1, ed. Rudolf Flotzinger (Vienna
            2002)</bibl>
          <bibl><author>Perger, Richard von &amp; Robert Hirschfeld</author>, <title level="m">Geschichte der k. k. Gesellschaft der Musikfreunde in Wien</title> (Vienna:
            Holzhausen, 1912)</bibl>
          <bibl><author>Tittel, Ernst</author>, <title level="m">Die Wiener Musikhochschule: vom
              Konservatorium der Gesellschaft der Musikfreunde zur staatlichen Akademie fur Musik
              und darstellende Kunst</title> (Vienna: Elisabeth Lafite, 1967)</bibl>
          <bibl>Home page of the Gesellschaft der Musikfreunde in Wien:
            http://www.musikverein.at/startseite.asp</bibl>
          <bibl>Home page of the Archive of the Gesellschaft der Musikfreunde in Wien:
            http://www.a-wgm.com/</bibl>
          <bibl><title level="m">MGG</title>, "Wien"</bibl>
        </listBibl>
        </div>
      <div>
        <head>Contributor:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author>Marko Deisinger</author></bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
