<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-007565">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Musikhistorisches Institut, Wien</title>
        <title type="sub">Music-Historical Institute, Vienna</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="musikhistorisches_institut">Musikhistorisches Institut, Wien</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>08/05/2008</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Organization</term>
          <term subtype="basename">musikhistorisches_institut</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change><date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Musikhistorisches Institut, Wien</head>
      <div>
        <p>Institute, part of the University of Vienna, the head of which in Schenker’s lifetime was
            <ref cRef="entity-000003">Guido Adler</ref>, whose seminar several of Schenker’s pupils
          attended.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Historical Summary</head>
        <p>A chair in the History and Aesthetics of Music was founded at the University of Vienna in
          1870, its first occupant being <ref cRef="entity-000331">Eduard Hanslick</ref>, who had
          been lecturing at the University in that subject since 1856. In 1882 <ref
            cRef="entity-000003">Guido Adler</ref> (1855–1941) earned his habilitation there with a
          dissertation entitled <title level="m">Studie zur Geschichte der Harmonie</title> (Study
          in the History of Harmony, 1881); and in 1893‒94 Adler founded the historical edition
            <title level="m">Denkmäler der Tonkunst in Österreich</title> (Monuments of Music in
          Austria) under his own general editorship. Upon Hanslick's retirement in 1898, Adler
          succeeded to the chair in musicology, which he held until 1927. Also in 1898 he founded
          the Musikhistorische Lehrmittelsammlung (Music-Historical Collection of Teaching
          Materials), which in 1901 was redesignated the Musikhistorisches Institut
          (Music-Historical Institute), with Adler at its head. </p>

        <p>Already in 1885 Adler had published an article "Umfang, Methode und Ziel der
          Musikwissenschaft" ("Scope, Method, and Aim of Musicology"), which established the
          distinction between the historical and systematic fields of musicology. This taxonomy was
          later amplified in his books <title level="m">Der Stil in der Musik</title> (Style in
          Music, 1911) and <title level="m">Methode der Musikgeschichte</title> (Method in the
          Historical Study of Music, 1919), the latter codifying all the sub-fields of the
          discipline and providing the underlying principles of the Institute itself. In 1913 the
          Institute was incorporated into the main building of the University, and in the same year
          Adler founded the journal <title level="j">Studien zur Musikwissenschaft</title>, which
          served as a vehicle for the research of his students. The Institute became not only the
          central focus of all Austrian musicology but the leading center internationally, and
          Adler's pupils came to be dubbed the "Vienna School" of musicology.</p>

        <p>Adler took retirement in 1927. Despite fierce resistance on his part, Robert Lach
          (1874–1958), a comparative musicologist, was appointed to succeed him. Lach’s elevation
          was engineered at the instigation of an anti-Semitic professorial cartel to which Lach
          himself belonged. Moreover, in 1933 Lach became a member of the Nazi Party. From the
          moment Lach took up his post at the Institute, Adler’s so-called style-critical school,
          which had striven to depict a historically developmental relationship between the
          constituent musical artworks of music history, was inexorably suppressed. Soon the most
          renowned Adler pupils, <ref cRef="entity-000230">Wilhelm Fischer</ref> (1886–1962) und
            <ref cRef="entity-003150">Rudolf von Ficker</ref> (1886–1954), left the Institute, which
          was downgraded to Musicological Seminar in 1928, in which year Adler moved the operation
          of the <title level="m">Denkmäler</title> out of the institution.</p>

        <p>Lachs retired in 1939. He was succeeded – to the surprise of many – by the young music
          historian Erich Schenk (1902–1974), backed by the personal and political influence of the
          Nazi Party. Although Schenk never joined the Party, he belonged to several organizations
          allied to it and participated in initiatives of Nazi cultural politics. In 1941 he
          instigated the expropriation (aryanisation) of Adler’s surviving scholarly materials, as
          part of which the contents of Adler’s voluminous private library were dispersed among
          various libraries, including that of the Musicological Seminar itself. After World War II,
          only begrudingly and in part very belatedly was restitution granted to Adler’s heirs.</p>

        <p>Schenk was able to remain in post after Nazi rule, and even to expand his influence over
          Austrian musicology by means of the successive taking over of high offices and activities
          inside and outside of the University. He exerted a marked influence, for example on the
          appointment of personel, at the Musicological Institute, which he continued to direct
          until 1971. The first faculty member to be appointed after Schenk’s retirement not
          directly a Schenk pupil was Gernot Gruber in 1995.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>The Institute and Heinrich Schenker's Pupils</head>
        <p>The first of Schenker’s pupils known to be associated with Adler’s Seminar was <ref
            cRef="entity-000951">Hans Weisse</ref>, who in 1913/14 was taking three lessons a week
          with Schenker while also attending the Seminar. The earliest of Weisse’s many reports from
          inside the Seminar appears in Schenker’s 1913/14 lessonbook on March 23, 26, and 30, 1914,
          when Weisse consulted Schenker “on the music doctorate” and spoke of “Adler’s shifty
          attitude in the Seminar”; and in Schenker’s diary for April 27, 1914, which showed Adler
          already reshaping the scope of Weisse’s doctoral dissertation (suggesting that Weisse’s
          membership must date back at least to October 1913). Thereafter, Weisse reported comments
          by Adler that were subjected to Schenker’s ridicule. Apparently, none of Schenker’s
          publications were available in the Seminar library; and Schenker’s concept of music
          analysis conflicted with Adler’s belief that it must always be governed by
          historical-stylistic criteria. Evidently, Weisse’s interactions with Adler were colored by
          the latter’s sense of rivaly with Schenker.</p>

        <p>The seminar course included written examinations and its goal was the writing of a
          dissertation. Weisse, after a long interruption for wartime service, not only resumed
          study with Schenker but also returned to complete his thesis on the “artistic waltz,” of
          which much must have been written by 1914, for a typescript of <title level="m">Der
            Kunstwalzer und seine bedeutendsten Vertreter,</title> (The Artist Waltz and its Most
          Important Exponents), inscribed to Schenker and dated February 1915, is preserved in the
          Oster Collection (OC 47). In 1914 and again in 1919, Schenker tried to persuade Universal
          Edition to publish it (WSLB 235, 302). Weisse was awarded the Ph.D. degree in 1919.</p>

        <p><ref cRef="entity-000224">Richard Figdor</ref> was a pupil of Schenker’s between the end
          of the 1918/19 season and some time in that of 1920/21. There are indirect references in
          Schenker’s diary for December 15, 1919 and February 9, 1921 suggesting that he was a
          member of Adler’s seminar. None of his lesson notes contain allusion to the Seminar or to
          Adler.</p>

        <p><ref cRef="entity-000437">Klammerth, jnr</ref> (first name unknown) was a pupil of
          Schenker’s in the two seasons 1919/20 and 1920/21. There are reported comments by
          Klammerth in Schenker’s diary alluding, some indirectly, to Adler’s seminar, on March 22
          (“Klammerth recounts that Adler spoke to him about me, acknowledged my merits, indeed, but
          held the "infallibility" against me. He also thought it strange that I derive
          "everything," for example, in the <ref cRef="001731"><title level="m">Ninth
              Symphony</title></ref>, from a thirty-second note.”) and November 3, 1920 and February
          9 and May 4 (“Klammerth recounts some Adleriana …”), 1921.</p>

        <p>Two further Schenker pupils were also students of Adler, but in each case the two periods
          of study were widely separated in time. <ref cRef="entity-000989">Victor Zuckerkandl</ref>
          (1896–1965) studied with Schenker in the season 1914/15, before being called up for
          wartime service, after which he did not resume study with Schenker. He subsequently wrote
          a dissertation entitled <title level="m">Prinzipien und Methoden der Instrumentation in
            Mozarts Werken</title> (Principles and Methods of Instrumentation in Mozart’s Works)
          under Adler’s supervision, earning the Ph.D. from the University of Vienna in 1927. <ref
            cRef="entity-000754">Felix Salzer</ref> (1904–86) took lessons in piano and theory for
          many years from <ref cRef="entity-000951">Hans Weisse</ref>. When the latter emigrated to
          New York in 1931, Salzer became a member of the <ref cRef="entity-002499">Friday
            seminar</ref> that Schenker gave for former Weisse pupils throughout the years 1931/32
          to 1933/34; and when the seminar was dissolved in June 1934, Salzer continued as a private
          student. Salzer’s membership of Adler’s Seminar long preceded his time with Schenker, and
          must have coincided with, or preceded, his period of study with Weisse, for he was awarded
          the Ph.D. of the University of Vienna in 1926 with a dissertation on <title level="m">Die
            Sonatenform bei Franz Schubert</title> (Sonata Form in the Works of Franz Schubert).</p>
      </div>

    </body>

    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Sources</head>

        <listBibl>
          <bibl>https://musikwissenschaft.univie.ac.at/ Institut für Musikwissenschaft der
            Universität Wien</bibl>

          <bibl>https://musikwissenschaft.univie.ac.at/ueber-uns/institutsgeschichte/chronik/
            Chronik des Instituts für Musikwissenschaft (1856–2017)</bibl>

          <bibl>Die Musik in Geschichte und Gegenwart (1949‒69), "Guido Adler" (1949), "Wien" (1968)
            The New Grove Dictionary of Music (1980), "Guido Adler," "Musicology" </bibl>

          <bibl>Boisits, Barbara, “Guido Adler und die Gründung der Bibliothek am
            musikwissenschaftlichen Institut in Wien,” in Musikwissenschaft als Kulturwissenschaft:
            damals und heute. Internationales Symposion (1998) zum Jubiläum der Institutsgründung an
            der Universität Wien vor 100 Jahren, ed. Theophil Antonicek and Gernot Gruber (Tutzing:
            Schneider, 2005), pp. 69–88</bibl>

          <bibl>Boisits, Barbara, “Musikwissenschaft im Ersten Weltkrieg. Der Fall Guido Adler,” in
            Musik und Erinnern. Festschrift für Cornelia Szabó-Knotik, ed. Christian Glanz and Anita
            Mayer-Hirzberger (Vienna: Hollitzer, 2014), pp. 123–141</bibl>

          <bibl>Gruber, Gernot, “Tradition und Herausforderung. Historische Musikwissenschaft an der
            Wiener Universität,“ in Weite des Musikwissens. 100 Jahre Musikwissenschaft in Wien, in
            Österreichische Musikzeitschrift 53/10 (1998), pp. 8–19</bibl>

          <bibl>Hilscher, Elisabeth Theresa, “Chronik des Instituts für Musikwissenschaft,“ in Weite
            des Musikwissens. 100 Jahre Musikwissenschaft in Wien, in Österreichische
            Musikzeitschrift 53/10 (1998), pp. 4–7</bibl>

          <bibl>Stumpf, Markus, “Raub und Rückgabe der Bibliothek und des Nachlasses Guido Adlers –
            Anmerkungen und Aktualisierungen,” in Guido Adlers Erbe: Restitution und Erinnerung an
            der Universität Wien, ed. Markus Stumpf, Herbert Posch, and Oliver Rathkolb (=
            Bibliothek im Kontext 1; Göttingen: V&amp;R unipress, Vienna: Vienna University Press,
            2017), pp. 83–202</bibl>

          <bibl>Zoidl, Clemens, “Die Geschichte des Instituts für Musikwissenschaft an der
            Universität Wien nach Guido Adler. Forschung – Ergebnisse – Aufgaben,” in Guido Adlers
            Erbe: Restitution und Erinnerung an der Universität Wien, ed. Markus Stumpf, Herbert
            Posch, and Oliver Rathkolb (= Bibliothek im Kontext 1; Göttingen: V&amp;R unipress,
            Vienna: Vienna University Press, 2017), pp. 45–64</bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Contributors</head>

        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author><hi rend="bold">Ian Bent</hi></author> and <author><hi rend="bold">Marko
                Deisinger</hi></author></bibl>
          <lb/>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
