<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-002890">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Breitkopf &amp; Härtel</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="breitkopf_hartel">Breitkopf &amp; Härtel</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>08/05/2008</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Organization</term>
          <term subtype="basename">breitkopf_hartel</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change><date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Breitkopf &amp; Härtel</head>
      <div>
        <p>Major German music publisher and printer.</p>

        <p>The firm of Breitkopf was founded in 1719 and in the course of the 18th century
          established itself as one of Europe's leading publishing houses. It had both a publishing
          arm and a printing works in Leipzig. It was responsible for several innovations in music
          typography, most notably its devising in 1754‒55 of a system of movable type for music,
          which permitted the printing of music in far larger editions than had hitherto been
          possible. In 1796 the firm became Breitkopf &amp; Härtel.</p>

        <p>At the outset of the 19th century it began publishing "complete editions" of the works of
          composers such as Mozart and Haydn, and soon thereafter first editions of works by
          Beethoven. In 1862‒65 it published the complete works of J. S. Bach in 61 volumes, and in
          the later part of the century the complete editions of many other major composers,
          including Beethoven, Schumann, Schubert, and Liszt. It also published many books about
          music. The firm continues to the present day.</p>

      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Breitkopf &amp; Härtel</head>
        <p>Schenker contacted Breitkopf in 1894 with a view to publishing an article (letter from
          Maximilian Harden, OJ 11/42, [19]), apparently abortively. The firm, at the prompting of
          Ferruccio Busoni, published Schenker's <title level="m">Fantasy</title>, Op. 2,
            <title>Five Piano Pieces</title>, Op. 4, and <title>Two-voice Inventions</title>, Op. 5,
          all for piano, in 1898, and also his <title>Six Songs</title>, Op. 3 in 1898‒1901.
          They declined his <title>Six Songs for Mixed Chorus</title>, Op. 7 and <title level="m"
            >Ländler</title>, Op. 10, for piano in 1898, his <title level="m">Syrian Dances</title>
          for piano duet in 1899, and his Three <title>Songs</title>, Op. 6 in 1902.</p>

        <p>He offered his <ref cRef="entity-001724"><title level="m">Harmonielehre</title></ref> to
          the firm in 1905, but this was declined on the grounds that "the published works of
          Riemann along the same lines cast doubts on the sure success of your work" (OJ 9/20,
          [36]). He corresponded with the firm between 1913 and 1916 regarding photographs of
          Chopin's Etudes Op. 10 and Op. 25 (OC B/206‒214). In 1920, he offered them his <ref
            cRef="entity-001758"><title level="j">Kleine Bibliothek</title></ref> (later to become
            <title level="j">Der Tonwille</title>) and his complete edition of the Beethoven piano
          sonatas, but these were declined.</p>

        <p>In 1911‒12, it was Breitkopf who printed Schenker's monograph on Beethoven's Ninth
          Symphony (published by Universal Edition). As Schenker's disillusionment with UE's
          director <ref cRef="entity-000356">Emil Hertzka</ref> increased, <ref cRef="entity-000268"
            >Wilhelm Furtwängler</ref> offered in 1922 to inquire at Edition Peters and Breitkopf
          &amp; Härtel with a view to Schenker's moving away from UE. In 1929 and 1930, Furtwängler
          (OJ 6/7, [4]) and <ref cRef="entity-000866">Karl Straube</ref> (OC 54/218, 298) sought,
          but without success, to procure either Peters or Breitkopf for the publication of
          Schenker's analytical study of the "Eroica" Symphony. Later in 1930, <ref
            cRef="entity-000380">Anthony van Hoboken</ref> unsuccessfully tried to persuade
          Breitkopf to undertake a complete edition of the works of C. P. E. Bach with which
          Schenker was to be involved in conjunction with the <ref cRef="entity-002452"
            >Photogrammarchiv</ref> (PhA/Ar 36, [1]).</p>

        <p>There are also numerous references to the firm in Schenker's diaries.</p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Correspondence between Breitkopf &amp; Härtel and Schenker</head>
        <p>Correspondence between Breitkopf &amp; Härtel and Schenker survives as OJ 9/20 (33
          letters and postcards from Breitkopf dating between 1894 and 1920, with copies of
          statements of account and contracts), OC B/206‒214 (eight letters and postcards and one
          invoice from Breitkopf dating from 1913‒16), and Sbb 55 Nachl. 12, [1], from Schenker to
          Breitkopf of 1930.</p>
      </div>

    </body>

    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Contributor:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author>Ian Bent</author></bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
