<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0" xml:id="entity-002444">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Deutscher Sprachverein</title>
        <title type="sub">German Language Society</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="deutscher_sprachvere">Deutscher Sprachverein</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>21/06/2006</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Organization</term>
          <term subtype="basename">deutscher_sprachvere</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change><date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Deutscher Sprachverein</head>
      <div>
        <p>Society for the purification and cultivation of the German language, established in 1885
          by the art historian and museum director Hermann Riegel. The DSV’s stated
          objectives were:
          
          <cit><q>1. to promote the purification of the German language [and rid it] of unnecessary
          foreign components, – 2. to cultivate the preservation and restoration of the true
          spirit and essential nature of the German language, and 3. to strengthen general national
          consciousness in the German people by this means.</q></cit></p>
        
        <p>The DSV had many critics, and fell foul of the Hitler regime, its activities being
          limited by the latter from 1940 on, and the journal ceasing publication in 1943. It was
          refounded in 1947 as the Gesellschaft für deutsche Sprache.</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>The Society and Schenker</head>
        <p>Schenker is presumed to have been sympathetic to its aims from the fact that in 1927 and
          1928 he sent postcards to Felix-Eberhard von Cube with the DSV's emblem (the double eagle)
          and panel of stated objectives, which reads:
          
          <cit><q>The German Language Society, founded in 1885, numbers 40,000 members and 285 local
          chapters. It is dedicated to protecting and cultivating the German language, to inspiring
          love for it, to preserving its purity and beauty, to deepening the understanding of it, to
          sharpening the feeling for language and thereby to serving the German people and the
          German future. The annual subscription is [<hi rend="italic">blank</hi>] Marks. For that,
          members receive the journal. The German Language Society is not a learned society. It is
          intended for all Germans who love their rich, beautiful mother tongue, men and women,
          scholars and non-scholars. The sister societies accept applications, for individual
          members the office of the German Language Society is Berlin W 30, Nollendorfstraße
          13/14; postal check office Berlin No. 20894. (vC11, Sept 27, 1927; vC18, June 9, 1928)</q></cit></p>
        
        <p>Postcards with the DSV emblem and stated objectives are:</p>
      </div>
    </body>
    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Source:</head>
        <p><ref target="http://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Allgemeiner_Deutscher_Sprachverein" type="external">Wikipedia: Allgemeine Deutsche Sprachverein</ref></p>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
