<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-003006">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Ansorge-Verein für Kunst und Kultur</title>
        <title type="sub">Ansorge Society for Art and Culture</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="ansorge-verein">Ansorge-Verein</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>08/05/2008</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Organization</term>
          <term subtype="basename">ansorge-verein</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change><date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Ansorge-Verein für Kunst und Kultur</head>
      <div>
        <p>Society founded in Vienna in 1903 by the music critic Paul Stefan (1879‒1943) and the
          writer and theater director Wilhelm von Wymetal (1862‒1937), and continuing independently
          until 1911. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>The Society</head>
        <p>Named after the composer and pianist Conrad Ansorge (1862‒1930), a pupil of Liszt and
          noted supporter of contemporary music and literature, the objective proclaimed in its
          motto was to promote all great art, both old and new ("Jeder grosse Kunst alter und neue
          zu pflegen"). <ref cRef="entity-000798">Arnold Schoenberg</ref>'s friend, teacher, and
          brother-in law <ref cRef="entity-003005">Alexander von Zemlinsky</ref>, who had joined the
          conducting team at the Theater an der Wien in September 1903, and had become disillusioned
          with Vienna's relatively conservative Tonkünstlerverein, was a founder member; according
          to Moskovitz "he was recruited to serve as the organization's pianist." </p>

        <p>Songs by both Zemlinsky and Schoenberg were performed at early concerts sponsored by the
          Society, and a review of the Society's inaugural event on November 29, 1903 praised
          Zemlinsky as "the excellent vocal accompanist" (<title level="j">Neue musikalische
            Presse</title> 13 (1904), No. 2, 29‒30). The Society also arranged lectures, given by
          such notable figures as Hermann Bahr, Adolf Loos and Franz Wedekind. However, it soon
          became clear to Zemlinsky that the Ansorge-Verein was more concerned to focus on poetry
          and literature than on music, and in 1904 he was involved with Schoenberg, Franz Schmidt
          and others in forming the Vereinigung schaffender Tonkünstler (Society for Creative
          Musicians). This was focused entirely on modern music, and Mahler agreed to become its
          honorary president. </p>

        <p>The Society was eventually merged in 1911 with the Akademischer Verband für Kunst und
          Literatur (Academic Union for Art and Literature). </p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Ansorge-Verein and Schenker</head>
        <p>The Ansorge-Verein is mentioned in two items of correspondence to Schenker: OJ 14/15,
          [8], January 1904, from Zemlinsky, Gutheil, and Schoenberg, citing the Society as a model
          for establishing a new society for the promotion of new music; and OJ 14/15, [9], an
          invitation to attend an event of the Ansorge-Verein, described as an
          "Ansorge‒Gruber‒Schoenberg evening," on February 11, 1904, which Schenker did not take up.
          (Schoenberg strove to involve Schenker in the planned new society, but to no avail.)</p>
      </div>
    </body>

    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Source:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl>
            <author>Moskovitz, Marc D.</author>, <title level="m">Alexander Zemlinsky. A Lyric
              Symphony</title> (Boydell Press, 2010), p.90 </bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>


      <div>
        <head>Contributor:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl>
            <author>Arnold Whittall</author>
          </bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
