<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0"
  xml:id="entity-002627">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Drei Masken Verlag</title>
        <title type="sub">Three Masks Publishing House</title>
        <title type="file">
          <term sortKey="drei_masken_verlag">Drei Masken Verlag</term>
        </title>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>published in Movable Type<date>08/05/2008</date></resp>
          <name>ianbent</name>
        </respStmt>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Schenker Documents Online in association with the Centre for Computing in the
          Humanities</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>http://www.schenkerdocumentsonline.org</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <textClass>
        <keywords scheme="MT">
          <term subtype="category">Organization</term>
          <term subtype="basename">drei_masken_verlag</term>
        </keywords>
        <keywords scheme="EATS">
          <term key="nNNNNNNN"/>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change><date>21/08/2009</date>
        <desc>Automatic Conversion from Movable Type</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Drei Masken Verlag</head>
      <div>
        <p>Publishing house based in Munich; publisher of Schenker's periodical <title level="j">Das
            Meisterwerk in der Musik</title>.</p>

        <div>
          <head>Drei Masken Verlag: history </head>
          <p>Drei Masken Verlag was established in <ref cRef="entity-002286">Munich</ref>, at
            Karolinenplatz 3, in November 1910 exclusively to publish theatrical works (hence "three
            masks") and music, especially music for the theater. In 1912, its founder, Ludwig
            Friedmann, opened an office in Berlin, at Friedrichstraße 129, and in 1922 in Vienna, at
            Wallnerstraße 4. In 1920 he launched a publishing division for music literature; the
            1920s also saw an ambitious expansion of its range of interests, including politics
            (including works by Max Weber), memoirs, and expressionist literature, which helped to
            make Drei Masken Verlag among the top 10% of the 177 publishing houses in Munich ‒ a
            significantly larger publishing center than Vienna. </p>

          <p>As a Jewish firm, Drei Masken Verlag was confiscated by the Nazis, and in 1934 its
            music division was separated (as Dreiklang‒Drei Masken) from its theater and book
            divisions. Shortly after the end of World War II, permission was granted by the Soviet
            authorities to resume publication of theatrical works in Berlin; this operation was
            moved to Munich in 1951. The music branch survives today, in Berlin, as part of the
            Dreiklang-Dreimasken Bühnen- und Musikverlag. </p>
        </div>

        <div>
          <head>Drei Masken Verlag and music </head>
          <p>Drei Masken Verlag developed a sizeable music catalog. This included: </p>

          <p><hi rend="bold">Facsimiles:</hi> high-quality reproductions of the autograph
            manuscripts of the J. S. Bach "Kreuzstab" Cantata, Beethoven piano sonatas Op. 78 and
            Op. 111, Brahms <title level="m">Four Serious Songs</title>, Handel duet "Qual fior,"
            Mozart Piano Trio in E-flat major, Schubert "Unfinished" Symphony, and Wagner scores of
              <title level="m">Meistersinger</title>, <title level="m">Parsifal</title>, <title
              level="m">Tristan und Isolde</title>, the <title level="m">Siegfried Idyll</title>,
            and the Prelude to <title level="m">Meistersinger</title>. </p>

          <p><hi rend="bold">Monographs:</hi> the second edition of <ref cRef="entity-000003">Guido
              Adler</ref>'s <title level="m">Richard Wagner: Vorlesungen</title> (1923), <title
              level="m">Gesammelte Aufsätze zur Musikgeschichte</title>, edited by <ref
              cRef="entity-003134">Adolf Sandberger</ref>, and the series <title level="m"
              >Musikalische Stillehre in Einzeldarstellungen</title>, edited by <ref
              cRef="entity-003152">Hermann Waltershausen</ref>, <title level="m">Monographien zur
              Russischen Musik</title>, edited by Oskar von Riesemann, and <title level="m"
              >Zeitgenössische Komponisten</title>, edited Waltershausen (monographs on Klose,
            Debussy, Bittner, Pfitzner, Reger, Schilling, Schmid, Schreker, Strauss, Thuille, and
            Zilcher). </p>

          <p><hi rend="bold">Journals</hi>: <title level="j">Mozart-Jahrbuch</title> (1923‒29),
            edited by Hermann Abert; four volumes of the <title level="j">Sammelbände für
              vergleichende Musikwissenschaft</title> (1922‒23), edited by Carl Stumpf and E. M. von
            Hornbostel, vol. 4 of which was Béla Bartók, <title level="m">Volksmusik der Rumänen von
              Maramures</title>. </p>
        </div>

      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Drei Masken Verlag and Schenker</head>
        <p>As a consequence of a rancorous dispute with his principal publisher, <ref
            cRef="entity-002408">Universal Edition</ref>, Schenker turned to Drei Masken Verlag in
          November 1924 through the agency of his former pupil <ref cRef="entity-000922">Otto
            Vrieslander</ref>, who lived in Munich, with a view to its taking over publication of
          his journal <ref cRef="entity-001739"><title level="j">Der Tonwille</title></ref> (see OC
          54/2, 4, 5‒7). Drei Masken Verlag chose to distance itself from UE and <title level="j"
            >Tonwille</title>, and opted for a different title and annual publication. By June 1925
          negotiations were complete, the elected title being <title level="j">Das Meisterwerk in
            der Musik</title>. </p>

        <p>The complex typography and unusual music examples in the acoustics and ethnomusicological
          transcriptions of the <title level="j">Sammelbände</title> perhaps allowed the publishing
          house to feel it could handle the intricacies of Schenker's work ‒ there are similarities
          in layout and formatting between the Bartók volume and <title level="j"
            >Meisterwerk</title>; and with Schenker's agreement the publisher modeled <title
            level="j">Meisterwerk</title> directly on the typography and layout of the <title
            level="j">Mozart-Jahrbuch</title> (OC 54/23 and 25). </p>

        <p>From November 1924 to January 1927, the musicologist <ref cRef="entity-000195">Alfred
            Einstein</ref> was a major correspondent on behalf of Drei Masken Verlag, the
          musicologist and bibliographer <ref cRef="entity-000164">Otto Erich Deutsch</ref> serving
          a similar role from January 1927 to July 1932; and <ref cRef="entity-000922">Otto
            Vrieslander</ref> acted as the in-house editor for music examples and voice-leading
          graphs. By December 1926, with the failure of the second volume to appear, the parties
          were threatening to resort to the courts (OC 54/109), and relations continued to be
          difficult thereafter. Each of the three volumes was published in the summer of the year
          following that given on the title-page, i.e. in 1926, 1927, and 1931, respectively. </p>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Drei Masken Verlag correspondence </head>
        <p>One of the largest correspondences among the Schenker papers, the bulk of the material is
          preserved in OC 54, which numbers 384 items (not all correspondence). That file includes
          approximately 120 letters, postcards, and telegrams from Drei Masken Verlag to Schenker,
          mostly under the publisher's Munich or Vienna letterhead, many of them with the signature
          "Demblin" (possibly August Demblin, whose <title level="m">Czernin und die
            Sixtus-affaire</title> was published by Drei Masken Verlag in 1920), often cosigned with
          another official of the publishing house or Alfred Einstein. </p>

        <p>OC 54 also includes approximately ten drafts or copies of letters from Schenker to the
          publisher; the finished letters are not known to survive. Numerous postal receipts survive
          for items dispatched in both directions, many of them for items not known to survive.
          There are also many letters and postcards from <ref cRef="entity-000164">Otto Erich
            Deutsch</ref>, <ref cRef="entity-000922">Otto Vrieslander</ref>, the letterpress printer
            <ref cRef="entity-003129">Mandruck</ref>, the engraving firm <ref cRef="entity-002402"
            >Waldheim-Eberle</ref>, and the engraver <ref cRef="entity-000894">Georg Tomay</ref>
          concerning Drei Masken Verlag business. </p>

        <p>Seven items from the Berlin office of Drei Masken Verlag to Heinrich and Jeanette
          Schenker are preserved as OJ 10/11 (1932‒39), and OJ 35/8 contains 57 leaves of financial
          transactions between Heinrich and Moriz Schenker, Anny Wollner, and Drei Masken Verlag
          (1922‒31). </p>
      </div>
    </body>

    <back>
      <div>
        <head>Sources:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author>Wittmann, Reinhard</author>, <title level="m">Hundert Jahre Buchkultur in
              München</title> (Munich: Hugendubel, 1993) </bibl>
          <bibl>Drei Masken Verlag website: www.dreimaskenverlag.de/verlag/verlagsgeschichte/
            (accessed Dec 29, 2011) </bibl>
          <bibl>Drei Masken Verlag catalog 1926 (OC 54/190) </bibl>
          <bibl>Finding aids for OC and OJ </bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>

      <div>
        <head>Contributor:</head>
        <listBibl>
          <bibl><author>Ian Bent</author> with <author>William Drabkin</author></bibl>
        </listBibl>
      </div>
    </back>
  </text>
</TEI>
