<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:vC 2 : 9-13-25 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© In the public domain.
© Transcription William Drabkin, 2006.
© Translation by William Drabkin 2006.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary William Drabkin 2006.
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license> This document is deemed to be in the public domain as of January 1, 2006.  Any claim to intellectual rights should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance> Felix-Eberhard von Cube (1925-87)—Heirs of F.-E. von Cube (1987-present day)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: In the public domain; Image: Heirs of Felix-Eberhard von Cube; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary William Drabkin.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 09/13/1925 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Cube ~ HSchenker","CubeG ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Schenker to Cube, dated September 13, 1925</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-05-29</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>S explains to C's father why his first teaching assignment went awry, but promises to continue to help him;  he suggests Anthony van Hoboken may be able to assist him. 

</dc:description><dc:subject>Schenker, Heinrich;  Cube, Felix-Eberhard von;  pupil;  teaching;  difficulty;  Hoboken, Anthony van</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">   - -</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Schenker to Gustav von Cube, dated September 13, 1925</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">upper left corner, in Felix-Eberhard von Cube’s hand:</tei:hi>] an meinen Vater</tei:p><tei:p>Sehr verehrter Herr Professor!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  The addressee is Cube’s father, Gustav von Cube, a professional architect.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Angesichts der trefflichen Eigenschaften Ihres H. <tei:hi rend="italic">Felix</tei:hi>, in muskalischer u. sonstiger Hinsicht, habe ich schon im Vorjahre davon gedacht, ihn als Lehrer hier einzuführen, zum Teil aus Gründen wirtschaftlicher Natur, zum Teil auch aus künstlerichen Gründen.</tei:p><tei:p>Ein kleines Lüftchen zeigt sich am Horizont, aber die Angst vor der Überlegenheit des H. <tei:hi rend="italic">Felix</tei:hi>, die in der Hauptlehre&lt;strike&gt;n&lt;/strike&gt;rin der in Frage kommenden Schülerin platzgegriffen hat, brachte ihn zu Schaden.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  A year earlier, Schenker had recommended Cube as a theory teacher for a sixteen- or seventeen-year-old pupil of a former pupil; see vC1, October 19, 1924. </tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Wollen Sie es glauben, daß ich auch ohne Ihre Erinnerung die wichtige Frage im Auge behalten hätte. Wenn mir die Sache etwas leichter wäre!  Die Gründung einer Existenz ist ja immer eine schwere Aufgabe, zumal in so jungen Jahren, in so verworrenen Zeitläuften wie die heutigen, u. Glück u. Zufall wollen auch dabei sein, . . Kurz[,] H. <tei:hi rend="italic">Felix</tei:hi> hat es nicht leicht. Dass er immerfort daran denkt, sich selbstständig zu machen, weiß ich u. <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> bestätige ich gern. Und daß ich das Möglichste aufbieten werde, ihm behilflich zu sein, davon wollen Sie überzeugt sein. Der Weg eines älteren Schülers, der ähnlich dem des H. <tei:hi rend="italic">Felix</tei:hi> lief, gestaltete sich mit der Zeit glänzend, er ist heute ein vielumworbener, gutgezahlter Lehrer,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4"> Possibly Hans Weisse (1892–1940), one of Schenker’s most gifted pupils, eleven years Cube’s senior.  Click on <ref cRef="weisse_hans">Hans Weisse</ref>.</tei:note> warum sollte H. <tei:hi rend="italic">Felix</tei:hi> nicht vorwärtskommen, Schritt um Schritt?</tei:p><tei:p>Vielleicht fördert ihn sozusagen gesellschaftlich-mittelbar H. <tei:hi rend="italic">van Hoboken</tei:hi>,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5"> Click on <ref cRef="hoboken_anthony_van">Anthony van Hoboken</ref>.</tei:note> der zum Herbst bei mir eintrifft. Und wer kennt sonst die Wege der Zufälle, die hier eine solche Rolle spielen!</tei:p><tei:p>H. <tei:hi rend="italic">Felix</tei:hi> vor dem Ohr des Vaters zu loben scheint mir etwas unzart. Dennoch möchte ich sagen, daß er sich zu einem maßgebenden musikalischen <tei:hi rend="italic">Praeceptor</tei:hi> zu entwickeln alle Eignung hat (des Ohres, des Intellektes, der Sprache u. des Humors) – augenblicklich ringt er ja noch mit den Jünglings-Nerven, bis die Nerven fester geworden sind, treten dann alle Eigenschaften deutlicher vor.</tei:p><tei:p>Noch einmal, ich werde gewiß an Ihren H. Sohn <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> denken.</tei:p><tei:p>Mit besten Grüßen
Ihr sehr ergebener 
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] <tei:hi rend="italic">H Schenker</tei:hi>
13.IX.1925</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Schenker to Gustav von Cube, dated September 13, 1925</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">upper left corner, in Felix-Eberhard von Cube’s hand:</tei:hi>] to my father</tei:p><tei:p>Most esteemed Professor!<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/></tei:p><tei:p>With regard to the excellent qualities of your [son] Felix, in musical and other respects, I have considered – as early as last year – introducing him as a teacher here, partly for reasons of a financial nature, partly also for artistic reasons.</tei:p><tei:p>A gentle breeze appears on the horizon, but Felix’s fear of superiority, which took root in the principal teacher of the pupil<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> in question, proved injurious to him.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/></tei:p><tei:p>Believe me, I had kept an eye on this important matter without your reminding me. If only things were somewhat easier! To establish an existence is indeed always a difficult task, all the more so when one is young, and living in such confused times as those of today; and luck and circumstance also have to be on one’s side . . . . In short, Felix is not having an easy time. That he is forever thinking of making himself independent is something that I know and <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> happily endorse. And please be assured that I shall do all that I can to be helpful to him. The path of an older pupil, which ran similarly to that of Felix’s, worked out magnificently in the course of time, and now he is a much sought after, well paid teacher;<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> why should Felix not progress [likewise], step by step?</tei:p><tei:p>Perhaps Mr. van Hoboken,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/> who will be meeting me when he arrives in the fall, can assist him in social matters, so to speak. And who, moreover, knows the paths of fortune, which play such an important role here!</tei:p><tei:p>To praise Felix before his father’s ear seems to me somewhat indelicate. Nevertheless, I should like to say that he has all the qualities needed to develop into a respectable music teacher: ear, intellect, speech and humor. For the moment he is wrestling with the nerves of a youth; once his nerves have firmed up, all these qualities will come more clearly to the fore.</tei:p><tei:p>Once again, I shall certainly <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> think about your son.</tei:p><tei:p>With best wishes, 
Yours faithfully,
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] H. Schenker
September 13, 1925</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>