<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:vC 31 : 11-1-30 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
©  In the public domain.
© Transcription William Drabkin 2006.
© Translation William Drabkin 2006.
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license> This document is deemed to be in the public domain as of January 1, 2006.  Any claim to intellectual rights should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance> Felix-Eberhard von Cube (1930-87)—Heirs of F.-E. von Cube (1987-present day)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: In the public domain; Image: Heirs of Felix-Eberhard von Cube; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary William Drabkin.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 11/01/1930 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Cube ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Schenker to Cube, dated November 1, 1930</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-11-03</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description /><dc:subject>Schenker, Heinrich;  Cube, Felix-Eberhard von;  Weisse, Hans;  Kestenberg, Leo;  Prussian Ministry of Education;  Furtwängler, Wilhelm;  lectures;  Berlin;  Jöde, Fritz;  Halm, August;  Albersheim, Gerhard;  Der freie Satz;  Free Composition;  Rheinische Theater- und Musikzeitung;  Das Meisterwerk in der Musik;  Masterwork in Music;  Jahrbuch;  Yearbook </dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">   - -</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Schenker to Cube, dated November 1, 1930</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Lieber Herr Prof v. <tei:hi rend="italic">Cube</tei:hi>!</tei:p><tei:p>Im August erhielt ich (nach Galtür) von H <tei:hi rend="italic">Weisse</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1"> Click on <ref cRef="weisse_hans">Hans Weisse</ref>.</tei:note> einen Bf mit Beilagen, der mir sehr viel Freude machte. Über “dringende Empfehlung” Dr Furtwänglers<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  Wilhelm Furtwängler [create biogfile and link].</tei:note> hat sich der vielgenannte Ministerialrat D^r^ <tei:hi rend="italic">Leo Kestenberg</tei:hi> (<tei:hi rend="italic">preuss.</tei:hi> <tei:hi rend="italic">Unterrichtsministerium</tei:hi>)<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  Leo Kestenberg (1882-1962), who taught at both the Stern Conservatory and the Klindworth-Scharwenka Conservatory in Berlin, and was appointed to the Ministry of Science, Art, and Education in 1918, rising to a high position in the division of Art.  His name frequently comes up in the correspondence as someone favorably disposed toward the dissemination of Schenker’s ideas by German educators. </tei:note> mit eine&lt;del&gt;m&lt;/del&gt;^r^ -Briefchen- ^Einladung^ an <tei:hi rend="italic">Weisse</tei:hi> gewandt, Vorlesungen in <tei:hi rend="italic">Berlin</tei:hi> abzuhalten.  Selbstverständlich ging es Beiden schon vornherein um meine Lehre. <tei:hi rend="italic">Weisse</tei:hi> erklärte seinen <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> Standpunkt (<tei:hi rend="italic">Schenker</tei:hi>) u. schlug 10 Themen vor, da es um 3 Vorlesungen geht.  Prof. Kestenberg anwortete in Worten, die eine verblüffende Erkenntnis von der Bedeutung meiner Lebensarbeit enthüllen.  Gerade <tei:hi rend="italic">Schenker</tei:hi> berühre ihn sehr sympathisch, gerade er sei zeitgemäß geworden, da man <tei:hi rend="italic">die klassischen Grund</tei:hi>^ge^<tei:hi rend="italic">setze zurückzugewinnen sucht</tei:hi>, gerade seine Theorie stehe “<tei:hi rend="italic">in engster Verbindung mit der Praxis</tei:hi>”(!)  Nicht einmal Musiker konnten sich bis heute zu dieser entscheidenden Erkenntnis emporschwingen, erst ein offizieller Ton eines <tei:hi rend="italic">Berliner</tei:hi> Ministerialrates bringt die Wende. <tei:hi rend="italic">Weisse</tei:hi> wird am 6 Dez. die <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> erste Vorlesung ^vor Lehrern^ in <tei:hi rend="italic">Berlin</tei:hi> halten u. dann 2–3 mal an anderen Stellen.</tei:p><tei:p>Ich teile Ihnen das freudige Ereignis mit, damit Sie gegebenfalls, wann die Zerstörungswüterische um Sie herum gar zu arg toben, Schutz u. Zuflucht bei den Worten u. den Taten Kestenbergs finden mögen.  Prof. Jöhde[<tei:hi rend="italic">sic</tei:hi>]<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4"> Fritz Jöde (1887-1970), German music pedagogue, especially important in youth music. In the 1920s he was active in Berlin, where he founded (1923) the first state-run youth music school. He wrote numerous books on music pedagogy and edited several collections of songs, including the popular <tei:hi rend="italic">Der Kanon</tei:hi> (1925).</tei:note> scheint ausgespielt zu haben, <tei:hi rend="italic">Halm</tei:hi>|<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5"> August Halm (1869–1929), music theorist and long-time friend of Schenker’s.  Halm’s death was noted in the brief discussion of the secondary literature on the <tei:hi rend="italic">Eroica</tei:hi> Symphony.</tei:note> ist schon gestorben, so scheint denn ^Kestenberg^, wohl auch sehr unter dem Einfluß Furtwänglers, eine Wendung zu mir zu machen.  Freilich aber, meine Sache ist schwieriger.  Erst bis der “fr. S.” herausgekommen sein wird, dann mag der Selbstunterricht beginnen u. <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> sich im Schulunterricht fortsetzen.</tei:p><tei:p>Haben Sie Nº 15 u. 16 der “Rheinischen Theater u. Musikztg” gesehen u. darin den Aufsatz <tei:hi rend="italic">Albersheims</tei:hi>’ über mich?<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6"> Gerhard Albersheim, “Heinrich Schenker: Grundlagen und Bedeutung seines Werkes.” A copy is preserved in Schenker’s Scrapbook (OC 2/p. 80) and also as OJ 12/23.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Mein “Jb. III”<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7"> <tei:hi rend="italic">Das Meisterwerk in Der Musik</tei:hi>, vol. 3, which bears the publication date 1930 but was not actually brought out until early 1931. The volume, which is shorter than either of the previous “yearbooks” in the series, is dominated by the analysis of Beethoven’s <tei:hi rend="italic">Eroica</tei:hi> Symphony. </tei:note> erscheint in höchstens 3 Wochen!</tei:p><tei:p>Mit bestem Gruß
Ihr
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] <tei:hi rend="italic">H Schenker</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>1.11.30</tei:p><tei:p>Was treiben Sie? Wie werden Sie getrieben?</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Schenker to Cube, dated November 1, 1930</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Dear Professor von Cube,</tei:p><tei:p>In August I received (in Galtür) a letter from Mr. Weisse<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/> with enclosures that gave me great joy. As a result of “an urgent recommendation” from Dr. Furtwängler,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> Dr Leo Kestenberg (Prussian <tei:hi rend="italic">Ministry of Education</tei:hi>),<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> whose name I have often mentioned, approached Weisse with an -note- ^invitation^ to give lectures in Berlin.  Naturally it was understood from the outset by both that the subject would be my theory. Weisse explained his <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> standpoint (Schenker) and suggested ten topics, as there are to be three lectures.  Prof. Kestenberg replied in terms that revealed an asstonishing understanding of the significance of my life’s work. Schenker in particular is supposed to have struck him as very agreeable, he in particular has become the man of the hour, since we are <tei:hi rend="italic">trying to regain the basic classical principles</tei:hi>; his theory in particular stands "<tei:hi rend="italic">in the closest relationship with musical practice</tei:hi>”(!)  Until now, not even musicians could rise up to this most critical recognition;  it took the official tone of a government minister in Berlin to bring about this turn of events. On December 6 Weisse will give his <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> first lecture in Berlin ^before an audience of teachers^ and then [repeat it] two or three times elsewhere.</tei:p><tei:p>I am communicating this happy event so that, when the viciously destructive people all around you are making things too difficult for you, you may find protection and comfort in Kestenberg’s words and deeds. Professor Jöde<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> seems to have done all he could, Halm is now dead,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/> thus ^Kestenberg^—almost certainly under Furtwängler’s influence, too—seems to be making an approach to me. Admittedly, however, my subject is more difficult: not until <tei:hi rend="italic">Der freie Satz</tei:hi> is published can self-study begin and <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> continue in the school curriculum.</tei:p><tei:p>Have you seen issues 15 and 16 of the <tei:hi rend="italic">Rheinische Theater- u. Musikzeitung</tei:hi>, which includes Albersheim’s article about me?<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/></tei:p><tei:p>Volume 3 of my Yearbook<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/> will appear in three weeks, at most!</tei:p><tei:p>With best greetings
Yours,
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ]  H. Schenker</tei:p><tei:p>November 1, 1930</tei:p><tei:p>What are you working on?  What is keeping you going?</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>