<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:vC 30 : 7-10-30 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
©  In the public domain.  
© Transcription William Drabkin, 2006.
© Translation William Drabkin, 2006.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary William Drabkin 2006.
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license> This document is deemed to be in the public domain as of January 1, 2006.  Any claim to intellectual rights should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance> Felix-Eberhard von Cube (1930-87)—Heirs of F.-E. von Cube (1987-present day)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: In the public domain; Image: Heirs of Felix-Eberhard von Cube; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary William Drabkin.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 07/10/1930 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Cube ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten postcard from Schenker to Cube, dated July 10, 1930</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-10-20</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>Comparison of Otto Vrieslander with Hans Weisse. — Weisse's Octet impressed Furtwängler. — Meisterwerk III due out in October (reports contents); is now revising Der freie Satz.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Schenker, Heinrich;  Cube, Felix-Eberhard von;  Vrieslander, Otto;  Weisse, Hans;  Furtwängler, Wilhelm;  Urlinie;  Lytle, Victor Vaughn;  Galtür;  Jahrbuch III;  Yearbook III;  Das Meisterwerk in der Musik;  Masterwork in Music;  Beethoven;  Eroica Symphony;  Der freie Satz;  Free Composition;  Deutsche Tonkünstlerzeitung;  Vienna;  Berlin</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN"> Galtür, Tirol </marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN"> Duisburg (Rhineland), Pulvergasse 41</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten postcard from Schenker to Cube, dated July 10, 1930</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{<tei:hi rend="italic">recto</tei:hi>}</tei:hi>
Postkarte</tei:p><tei:p>Absender: <tei:hi rend="italic">Schenker</tei:hi>
<tei:hi rend="italic">Galtür, Tirol</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[An:] H [/] Prof. [/] <tei:hi rend="italic">Felix v. Cube</tei:hi>
<tei:hi rend="italic">Duisburg (Rhl.)</tei:hi>
<tei:hi rend="italic">Pulvergasse 41</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">postmark:</tei:hi>] || GALTÜR | 10. VII. 30. 16 | <tei:hi rend="bold"> </tei:hi> * ||</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">for message-continuation, see below</tei:hi>]</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{<tei:hi rend="italic">verso</tei:hi>}</tei:hi>
Galtür, 10.7.1930</tei:p><tei:p>Mein lieber <tei:hi rend="italic">Prof. v Cube</tei:hi>!</tei:p><tei:p>Ihre Darstellung des “Onkels <tei:hi rend="italic">Otto</tei:hi>”<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1"> Cube’s portrayal of <ref cRef="vrieslander_otto">Otto Vrieslander</ref> at the start of his previous letter.  </tei:note> ist sehr zutreffend, bedauerlich ist es nur, daß er sich damit einen nie gutzumachenden Schaden für sein Leben selbst zugefügt hat.  Was hat sich doch <tei:hi rend="italic">D^r^ Weisse</tei:hi>,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  Click on <ref cRef="weisse_hans">Hans Weisse</ref>.</tei:note> im Gegensatz zu <tei:hi rend="italic">Vr.</tei:hi>, für eine Stellung in Wien herausschlagen gerade dadurch, daß er privat u. in seinem Seminar die “Url.” lehrte, ja, es gelang ihm sogar das Kunststück, einen amerikanischen Theorie-Professor so zu zähmen, daß er bei ihm Winters u. Sommers über 2 Jahre lang verblieben ist.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3"> This is almost certainly Victor Vaughn Lytle, a theory teacher at the Oberlin Conservatory, Oberlin, Ohio. The dates of Lytle’s tuition with Weisse tally precisely with the recollections of one of Lytle’s pupils from the 1930s, Robert A. Melcher. See David Carson Berry, “Victor Vaughn Lytle and the Early Proselytism of Schenkerian Ideas in the U.S.,” <tei:hi rend="italic">Journal of Schenker Studies</tei:hi> I (Fall 2005), pp.92-117 (especially p. 97).  No paragraph-break at this point.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="italic">Ad vocem Weisse</tei:hi>: er hat ein sehr schönes +Oktett+ zuletzt aufführen lassen mit einem gar schönen u. triftigen <tei:hi rend="italic">passacaglia</tei:hi> am Schluß, ein Werk, wie es heute gewiß sonst Niemand schreibt.  <tei:hi rend="italic">Furtwängler</tei:hi> war derart erstaunt u. entzückt davon, das er sich leidenschaftlich dafür bei <tei:hi rend="italic">Br. &amp; H.</tei:hi> eingesetzt hat, unglaublicherweise: leider ohne Erfolg, so verzweifelt sind die Verlagsverhältnisse heute. (Nebenbei: <tei:hi rend="italic">Furtw.</tei:hi> war so lieb, mir hier in Galtür <tei:hi rend="bold">{<tei:hi rend="italic">recto</tei:hi>}</tei:hi> seinen Besuch anzukündigen).<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4"> No paragraph-break at this point.  Galtür:  The Schenkers’ usual summer holiday resort.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Anfangs Oktober dürfte das Jb III des “Meisterw. i. d. M.“ erscheinen, dessen ersten Aufsatz ich Ihnen sehr ans Herz lege (folgt die „<tei:hi rend="italic">Eroica</tei:hi>“ in einer sehr heroischen Darstellung!).<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  The review copies of <tei:hi rend="italic">Das Meisterwerk in der Musik</tei:hi> III were sent out on December 13, 1930 (OC 54/253).  The first article is “Rameau oder Beethoven? Erstarrung oder geistiges Leben in der Musik?”, pp. 11–24 (Eng. trans., pp. 1–9);  following that is „Beethovens Dritte Sinfonie zum erstenmal in ihrem wahren Inhalt dargestellt,“ pp. 29–101 and Urlinietafeln (Eng. trans., pp. 10–68, 80–115); <tei:hi rend="italic">heroische Darstellung</tei:hi> is an allusion to the dedication of the <tei:hi rend="italic">Eroica</tei:hi> score to <tei:hi rend="italic">Beethoven dem Helden</tei:hi> (Beethoven the hero).   </tei:note>  Nun redigiere ich auch schon zum letzten Mal den „fr. S.“  Die Kritik in der „d. T.Z.“, für deren Einsendung ich bestens danke, macht mir gar nichts, dagegen stehen Erfolge, von denen sich der Rezensent gewiß kein Bild macht, sonst wäre er vorsichtiger.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  This review was pasted into Cube's letter OJ 9/34, [21], June 25, 1930: see &lt;a href="../../../review/guttmannmeisterwerk.html"&gt;Review&lt;/a&gt;.  It is cited by Jeanette S in S's scrap book, OC 2/p. 80.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Mit besten Grüßen von uns beiden Ihr
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] <tei:hi rend="italic">H Sch</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{<tei:hi rend="italic">verso, along left margin</tei:hi>}</tei:hi> 
Wien komme für Ihre Existenzbestrebungen an letzter Stelle!<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7"> This is in direct response to Cube’s enquiry, in the previous letter, about whether there might be an opportunity for him to teach in Vienna.</tei:note>  Eher Berlin, trotzdem ich diese Stadt nicht mag – “<tei:hi rend="italic">Produktio</tei:hi>” ist Triumpf.</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten postcard from Schenker to Cube, dated July 10, 1930</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{<tei:hi rend="italic">recto</tei:hi>}</tei:hi>
Postcard</tei:p><tei:p>From: Schenker
Galtür, Tirol</tei:p><tei:p>[To:] Prof. Felix v. Cube
Duisburg (Rhineland)
Pulvergasse 41</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">postmark:</tei:hi>] || GALTÜR | 10. VII. 30. 16 | <tei:hi rend="bold"> </tei:hi> * ||</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">for message-continuation, see below</tei:hi>]</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{<tei:hi rend="italic">verso</tei:hi>}</tei:hi>
Galtür, July 10, 1930
My dear Professor von Cube,</tei:p><tei:p>Your portrayal of “Uncle Otto” hits the mark well;<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/> it is just a pity that he has thus done irreparable damage to his life. By contrast with Vrieslander, just look at the position that Dr. Weisse<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> has carved out for himself in Vienna, preceisely because he taught the “Urlinie” privately and in his seminar. Indeed he succeeded in the miraculous feat of taming an American professor of theory, to the extent that he remained with him through both the winter and the summer for two years.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/></tei:p><tei:p>In support of Weisse: he has recently had a very attractive +octet+  performed, with a quite beautiful and apposite passacaglia as finale: the sort of work that certainly no one is writing today. Furtwängler was so amazed and charmed by it that, unbelievably, he took up its cause fervently at Breitkopf &amp; Härtel – unfortunately to no avail, as today’s financial circumstances are so doubtful for [music] publishers. (In passing: Furtwängler was so kind as to announce to me here in Galtür <tei:hi rend="bold">{<tei:hi rend="italic">recto</tei:hi>}</tei:hi> his visit.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/></tei:p><tei:p>Yearbook III of the <tei:hi rend="italic">Masterwork in Music</tei:hi>, the first article of which I offer you from the bottom of my heart (the <tei:hi rend="italic">Eroica</tei:hi> [Symphony analysis] in a heroic presentation follows it), should appear at the beginning of October.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/>  Now I am already revising <tei:hi rend="italic">Free Composition</tei:hi> for the last time.  The review in the <tei:hi rend="italic">Deutsche Tonkünstlerzeitung</tei:hi>, which I am most grateful to you for sending me, does not bother me in the slightest:  my successes—of which the reviewer certainly has no inkling, otherwise he would have been more careful—stand as his refutation.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/></tei:p><tei:p>With best wishes from both us us,
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] H. Schenker</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{<tei:hi rend="italic">verso, along left edge margin</tei:hi>}</tei:hi> 
Vienna would be the last place you would try to eke out an existence.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/>  Berlin would be better, in spite of the fact that I don’t like this city—Productivity triumphs.</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>