<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:vC 35 : 3-28-31 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
©  In the public domain.
© Transcription William Drabkin 2006.
© Translation William Drabkin 2006
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary William Drabkin 2006.
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license> This document is deemed to be in the public domain as of January 1, 2006.  Any claim to intellectual rights should be addressed to the Schenker Correspondence Project, Faculty of Music, University of Cambridge, at schenkercorrespondence@mus.cam.ac.uk.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance> Felix-Eberhard von Cube (1931-87)—Heirs of F.-E. von Cube (1987-present day)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: In the public domain; Image: Heirs of Felix-Eberhard von Cube; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary William Drabkin.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 03/28/1931 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Cube ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Schenker to Cube, dated March 28, 1931</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-11-05</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>S put C's Cologne Highschool proposal to van Hoboken, and now reports on the reaction, discussing the latter's character in so doing.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Schenker, Heinrich;  Cube, Felix-Eberhard von;  Hoboken, Anthony van;  Köln;  Cologne;  Braunfels, Walter;  Bach, C. P. E.;  Gesamtausgabe;  collected edition;  Berlin</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">   - -</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Schenker to Cube, dated March 28, 1931</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Lieber Prof. <tei:hi rend="italic">v. Cube</tei:hi>!</tei:p><tei:p>Nun sollen Sie den wahren Hergang erfahren.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  Click on <ref cRef="hoboken_anthony_van">Anthony van Hoboken</ref>.</tei:note></tei:p><tei:p>Nachdem Sie mir den ersten Brief in der Angelegenheit Köln geschrieben haben, habe ich sofort Hob. mitgeteilt, daß ich von Ihnen einen wichtigen Bf erhalten habe,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2"> The entire letter is concerned with Anthony van Hoboken’s response to a proposal set out in Cube’s previous letter, OJ 9/34, [23], February 10, 1931.</tei:note> dessen Inhalt -ich- schon jetzt zu verraten ^ich aber^ für überflüssig halte, da möglicherweise Sie nichts weiter unternehmen.  Daß wir Beide Geheimniskrämerei treiben, -wo der- ^wäre^ für ihn das Unerträglichste, wenn es durch Zufall ihm bekannt geworden wäre.  Nun schreiben Sie, das Spiel lag also offen da.  Die ersten Worte, die über <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> seine Lippen sprangen, nachdem er mir den Inhalt Ihres Briefes mitteilte, lauteten: “<tei:hi rend="italic">Wie komme ich dazu</tei:hi>? Wenn Braunfels<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3"> Walter Braunfels, professor of theory at the Cologne Hochschule für Musik, who had given support to Cube’s efforts to promote Schenkerian theory in northern Germany.</tei:note> will, kann er ja Andere abbauen u. Cube einsetzen.” Da ich ^zu^ dieser Äußerung nichts sagte – sie gieng ja +wissentlich+ an Allem vorbei –, verfiel der kleinliche Mann auf folgendes:  “Darf ich Sie um einen Rat bitten”? Ich durchschaute den Gesellen: ihm genügte zur Befriedigung seines Snobismus, seines Geldgefühls schon die Tatsache des Angerufenwordenseins, diese Befriedigung steht ihm, wie wir es hier Alle schaudernd[<tei:hi rend="italic">corr</tei:hi>] miterlebten, für die Ausführung: er sagt dann meinetwegen auch zu, läßt dann aber alle ^auf^sitzen, – <tei:hi rend="italic">ohne sich sogar zu entschuldigen</tei:hi>.</tei:p><tei:p>So hat er die Gesamt-Ausg. von Em. Bach auf <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> sich genommen, zahllose Personen durcheinander gefegt[?], Reisen zu Verlegern, zu Anwälten machen lassen, (ich wurde zu den Konferenzen aus dem Krankenbett geholt!), plötzlich schreibt er an Prof. Dr Haas:<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4"> Robert Haas (1886–1960) was the Director of the Music Division at the Austrian National Library 1920–45, and was in charge of the <ref cRef="photogrammarchiv">Photogrammarchiv</ref> there from its establishment in 1927. Plans to issue the collected works of C. P. E. Bach in twenty volumes over a ten-year period, under the general editorship of Ernst Fritz Schmid, and to publish a yearbook devoted to Bach research, are mentioned several times in the diaries;  see Federhofer, <tei:hi rend="italic">Heinrich Schenker, nach Tagebüchern ...</tei:hi> (Hildesheim: Olms, 1985), p. 155.</tei:note> “Em. Bach ist ein +deutscher+ Meister, wie komme <tei:hi rend="italic">ich</tei:hi>, <tei:hi rend="italic">ein Ausländer</tei:hi>, dazu, die G.A. zu machen??”  Entsetzen Sie sich nicht?<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5"> <tei:hi rend="italic">Entsetzen Sie sich nicht?</tei:hi> A variant on a common German play on words: “setzen Sie sich!” (sit down.) &amp;#8594; “entsetzen Sie sich!” (be outraged).</tei:note>  Nicht einmal hat er sich bei Verlegern, ^bei^ uns Allen entschuldigt – ein Lausbub! Und ähnliche Erfahrungen haben wir Alle zuhause zu verzeichnen.  Er ist -ein- völlig unerläßlich, schäbig, wucherisch, lügt schauderhaft, kurz er bewacht sein Geld wie 10 Drachen, nur daß er es nicht lassen kann, sich überall anzubiedern, <tei:hi rend="italic">Allen nachzulaufen, um</tei:hi> ^ein bischen^ <tei:hi rend="italic">Ehre für sich zu hausen</tei:hi>!</tei:p><tei:p>Ich erwiderte dem Filou:  “Sie wissen, daß ich <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> <tei:hi rend="italic">Cube</tei:hi> jede Hilfe Ihrerseits vergönne, tun Sie’s also, nur bitte ich Sie, diese Hilfeleistung ^nicht^ als eine Zuwendung ^auch^ an +mein+ Lebenswerk zu werten.  Es wäre ja grotesk, ^daß,^ wenn Sie sich mir gegenüber abseits stellen, ich Ihnen <tei:hi rend="italic">v. Cube</tei:hi> empfehle.”  Er hätte gern Sie u. mich verpflichtet, eine “Geste” getan, ohne auch nur eine Mark auszulegen.  Wir kennen ihn schon.  Nach Sekunden sagte er:  “Ich werde mich mit meiner Frau beraten”(!) (sie ist in Berlin) – na also, der Rückgang aus der Geste war schon da . .  In der nächsten Stunde vollzog er ihn ganz, da er plötzlich (wohlvorbereitet seit Langem, denn tückisch ist er über alle Maßen) erklärte:  “Nein, ich werde <tei:hi rend="italic">C.</tei:hi> Empfehlungen schicken u.s.w.”  Seine ersten Worte behielten Recht.  Heute rasselt er in <tei:hi rend="italic">Berlin</tei:hi> mit Geld, er spielt mit den Menschen, die er ^an^ sich lockt, denen er Alles mögliche vortäuscht, dann [<tei:hi rend="italic">in upper margin, inverted:</tei:hi>] verrät er sie alle, nachdem er sie ausgerechnet hat, u. – rasselt mit dem Geld wo anders, das genügt ihm.</tei:p><tei:p>Mit besten Grüßen von mir u. meiner Frau – 
Ihr
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] H Schenker
28.3.31</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Schenker to Cube, dated March 28, 1931</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Dear Professor von Cube,</tei:p><tei:p>Now you should learn the true sequence of events.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/></tei:p><tei:p>After you wrote me your first letter about the opportunity in Cologne, I informed Hoboken immediately that I had received an important letter from you;<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/>  ^but I^ thought it unnecessary to reveal its content just then, since you might possibly not undertake anything further. For us to engage in a secret deal^ would have been^ the most unbearable thing for him, if by some chance he gained knowledge about it.  Now you write that the matter is thus [still] open.  The first words that <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> sprang to his lips, after he communicated to me the content of your letter [to him] were:  “<tei:hi rend="italic">What am <tei:hi rend="italic">I</tei:hi> supposed to do about this</tei:hi>?  If Braunfels<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> wants, he can certainly get rid of others and employ Cube.”  As I said nothing in response to this statement—it +deliberately+ avoided the entire matter—the small-minded man came up with the following:  “Might I ask you for some advice?”  I saw straight through the scoundrel: merely the fact that he had been called upon was enough to satisfy his snobism, his materialism.  For him, this satisfaction—as we have all experienced here, to our horror—takes the place of doing something.  He will even agree,  for my sake;  but then lets everyone wait—<tei:hi rend="italic">without even so much as apologizing</tei:hi>.</tei:p><tei:p>This is how he took the collected edition of the works of C. P. E. Bach <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> upon himself, bringing countless people together, arranging trips to publishers, to solicitors (I was summoned from my sick-bed to the meetings!); finally he writes to Professor Haas:<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/>  “Emanuel Bach is a +German+ master, why should <tei:hi rend="italic">I</tei:hi>, +a foreigner+, be involved in the collected edition?”  Is that not an outrageous thing to say?<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/>  Not once did he apologize to the publishers, ^to^ any of us—the rascall!  And we all have similar private experiences to recount.  He is completely untrustworthy, shabby, usorious, a fiendish liar; in short, he guards his money like ten dragons, except that he cannot help ingratiating himself everywhere, <tei:hi rend="italic">running after everyone in order to accrue</tei:hi> ^a little^ <tei:hi rend="italic">honour for himself</tei:hi>!</tei:p><tei:p>I replied to the rogue:  “You know that I <tei:hi rend="bold">{4}</tei:hi> agree to any help that you can give Cube; do it, then;  I merely ask you ^not^ to assess this offer of help as a gesture ^also^ in respect of +my+ life’s work.  It would indeed by grotesque for me to recommend Cube if you stood in opposition to me.”  He would have gladly obliged you and me, made a “gesture,” without coughing up a single mark.  We know what he is like.  After some moments he said, “I’ll talk the matter over with my wife”(!)—she is in Berlin—there you have it, the retreat from the gesture was already on the way . . .  Within the hour he had withdrawn it entirely, for suddenly (though he had prepared for it long before, for he is a sly one beyond all measure) he explained:  “No, I shall write recommendations for Cube, etc.  His first words contained the truth.  Today he rattles his money in Berlin, he plays with the people to whom he becomes attached, giving them the illusion that everything is possible, then, [<tei:hi rend="italic">in upper margin, inverted:</tei:hi>] having sized them up, he betrays them all and goes off elsewhere, rattling his money; that satisfies him.</tei:p><tei:p>With best greetings from me and my wife,
Yours,
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi>] H. Schenker
March 28, 1931</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>