<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="home"
  xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Schenker Documents Online</title>
        <title type="sub">Home Page</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Centre for Computing in the Humanities, King's College London</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Strand, London WC2R 2LS, England, United Kingdom. Tel:+44 (0) 20 7836 5454</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines at http://abc.org</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>2009-08-04</date>
        <name>EP</name>
        <desc>CCHLite encoding</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>

      <div xml:id="heinrich_schenker"><p>Viennese musician and teacher Heinrich Schenker (1868-1935), the
        twentieth century's leading theorist of tonal music, produced a series of innovative studies
        and editions between 1903 and 1935, while exerting a powerful and sustained influence,
        directly and through his pupils, on the teaching of music from the 1930s onward in the USA,
        and since the 1970s in Europe and elsewhere. Today, Schenkerian theory and analysis
        constitutes a large and ever-growing field of vital academic study, with its own body of
        scholars, journals, book literature, institutions, and courses of instruction. (For a more
        detailed study of Schenker's life and work, see "Heinrich Schenker.")</p></div>

      <div xml:id="schenker_documents"><p>Schenker left behind approximately 130,000 manuscript and typescript leaves comprising
        unpublished works, preparatory materials, and personal documents, preserved in two dedicated
        archives, numerous libraries, and private possession. (For more information on these
        collections, see "Major Collections.") In addition, the archived papers of several other
        scholars, among them Guido Adler, Oswald Jonas, Moriz Violin, and Arnold Schoenberg,
        preserve correspondence and other documents relating to Schenker and his circle.</p>

      <p>Of the personal documents, Schenker maintained a vigorous correspondence over nearly half a
        century, kept a meticulously detailed diary over 40 years, and recorded precise notes on
        lessons that he gave over a period of twenty years. It is these three collections of
        personal documents that constitute the core of Schenker Documents Online.</p></div>



    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
