<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../schema/tei/xmod_web.rnc" type="compact"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="home"
  xmlns:xmt="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/xmod/tei/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Schenker Documents Online</title>
        <title type="sub">Home Page</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Centre for Computing in the Humanities, King's College London</publisher>
        <address>
          <addrLine>Strand, London WC2R 2LS, England, United Kingdom. Tel:+44 (0) 20 7836 5454</addrLine>
          <addrLine>http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch/</addrLine>
        </address>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>No source: created in electronic format.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <p>Encoding according to the CCH TEI Guidelines at http://abc.org</p>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>2009-08-04</date>
        <name>EP</name>
        <desc>CCHLite encoding</desc>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Schenker Documents Online</head>
      <div>
        <div>
          <head>Important User Announcement</head>
          <p><hi rend="italic">Schenker Documents Online</hi> is in a transitional phase during
            which materials are split between this new site and the original <ref
              target="http://mt.ccnmtl.columbia.edu/schenker/" type="external">Columbia
              website</ref>. All materials will eventually be moved to this site, but in the
            meantime our finding guidelines are:</p>

          <p><hi rend="bold">Diaries:</hi> Use only this site.</p>

          <p><hi rend="bold">Lessonbooks:</hi> Use only this site.</p>

          <p><hi rend="bold">Correspondence:</hi> Broadly, items from <hi rend="bold">1918 to
              1930</hi> are on this new site; items <hi rend="bold">pre-1918</hi> and <hi
              rend="bold">post-1930</hi> are on the Columbia site. Where correspondence temporarily
            exists on both sites, you should refer to the more up-to-date version on this new site. </p>

          <p><hi rend="bold">Profiles:</hi> Use this site: profiles are more up-to-date, and there
            are many more of them. </p>

          <p><hi rend="bold">Pages of general information:</hi> Use only this site.</p>

        </div>

        <div>
          <head>The Collections</head>
          <p><figure>
              <graphic url="OJ-72-14-10.jpg" rend="left" width="320px" height="432px"
                mimeType="image/jpeg" xmt:type="full"/>
              <figDesc>Heinrich Schenker: von Cube 1927</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <hi rend="italic">Schenker Documents Online</hi> is a digital edition of three large
            collections of documents — the voluminous <hi rend="bolditalic">correspondence</hi>
            between Heinrich Schenker and the members of his circle, together with the theorist's
              <hi rend="bolditalic">diaries</hi> and <hi rend="bolditalic">lessonbooks</hi>; these
            are supported by additional documents relating to his life, and a set of "<hi
              rend="bold">profiles</hi>" of people, places, and organizations with which he came
            into contact, the newspapers and journals that he read, and his own works. </p>
          <p><hi rend="italic">SDO</hi> does not provide facsimiles; it is thus in no sense a
            digitization project, nor is it an archive in the strict sense. Rather, it is a
            scholarly edition, which aims to present near-diplomatic transcriptions of original
            texts, together with English translations, summaries, supporting commentary, and such
            interpretation as is necessary to relate these documents to Schenker's personal
            development and those of his correspondents. </p>
          <p>Because it is digital, it provides direct hyperlinks between documents, facilitating
            rapid movement from document to document; and it offers the end-user a range of tools
            with which to search and browse documents, thus facilitating the task of understanding
            and contextualization. </p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>Heinrich Schenker</head>
          <p>Viennese musician and teacher Heinrich Schenker (1868–1935) was the twentieth century's
            leading theorist of tonal music, producing a series of innovative studies and editions
            between 1903 and 1935, while exerting a powerful and sustained influence, directly and
            through his pupils, on the teaching of music from the 1930s onward in the USA, and since
            the 1970s in Europe and elsewhere. Today, Schenkerian theory and analysis constitutes a
            large and ever-growing field of vital academic study, with its own body of scholars,
            journals, book literature, institutions, and courses of instruction. </p>

          <p>In addition to his published work, Schenker left behind approximately 130,000
            manuscript and typescript leaves comprising unpublished works, preparatory materials,
            and personal documents, preserved in two dedicated archives, numerous libraries, and
            private possession. (For more information on these collections, see <ref
              cRef="major_collections">"Major Collections."</ref>) Of the personal documents,
            Schenker maintained a vigorous correspondence over nearly half a century, kept a
            meticulously detailed diary over 40 years, and recorded precise notes on the lessons
            that he gave over 20 years. It is these three collections of personal documents that
            constitute the core of <hi rend="italic">SDO</hi>. (For a more detailed study of
            Schenker's life and work, see <ref cRef="heinrich_schenker">"Heinrich
            Schenker."</ref>)</p>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div>
        <p><ref cRef="correspondence">correspondence</ref> — <ref cRef="diaries">diaries</ref> —
            <ref cRef="lessonbooks">lessonbooks</ref> — <ref cRef="other_material">other
            material</ref></p>
        <p> </p>
      </div>


      <div type="logos">
        <list type="logo">
          <item>
            <ref target="http://www.ahrc.ac.uk">
              <figure>
                <graphic url="ahrc.png" mimeType="image/jpg" width="169px" height="40px"/>
              </figure>
            </ref>
          </item>

          <item>
            <ref target="http://www.leverhulme_logo">
              <figure>
                <graphic url="leverhulme.png" mimeType="image/png" width="102px" height="60px"/>
              </figure>
            </ref>
          </item>

          <item>
            <ref target="http://www.kcl.ac.uk/cch">
              <figure>
                <graphic url="cch.png" mimeType="image/png" width="81px" height="40px"/>
              </figure>
            </ref>
          </item>

          <item>
            <ref target="http://www.kcl.ac.uk">
              <figure>
                <graphic url="kcl.png" mimeType="image/png" height="40px" width="61px"/>
              </figure>
            </ref>
          </item>

          <item>
            <ref target="http://www.logo_ccnmtl">
              <figure>
                <graphic url="columbia.png" mimeType="image/gif" width="122px" height="55px"/>
              </figure>
            </ref>
          </item>

          <item>
            <ref target="http://www.soton.ac.uk/">
              <figure>
                <graphic url="southampton_logo.png" mimeType="image/png" width="161px" height="40px"
                />
              </figure>
            </ref>
          </item>
        </list>
      </div>


    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
