<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 11/35,19 : 7-28-21 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© In the public domain; published with the permission of the heirs of August Halm, March 2006.
© Transcription Lee Rothfarb, 2006.
© Translation Lee Rothfarb, 2006.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary Lee Rothfarb 2006
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license> This document is deemed to be in the public domain as of January 1, 2000, and is published with the permission of the heirs of August Halm, March 2006.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1921-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1955) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1955-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: In the public domain; Image: University of California, Riverside; Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: Lee Rothfarb.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 07/28/1921 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Halm ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Halm to Schenker, dated July 28, 1921</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2006-05-12</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>H discusses an "intended gift," and the merits of M. Hanz and K. T. Schmid to receive it.  H reports that he has moved from Esslingen to Wickersdorf, and that his Concerto for Large Orchestra has been performed by Fritz Busch in Stuttgart, and comments on Cotta's hand-over of Kontrapunkt.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Halm, August; Schenker, Heinrich;  gift;  Hanz, M.;  Ganz, M.;  Schmid, Karl Theodor;  Esslingen;  Wickersdorf;  Heilbronn;  Nagold;  C major Concerto;  Busch, Fritz;  performance;  Stuttgart;  Ulm;  Freie Schulgemeinde;  Free School Community;  Cotta, J. G.;  Kontrapunkt;  Counterpoint;  </dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Halm to Schenker, dated July 28, 1921</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>28.VII.21</tei:p><tei:p>Lieber u. verehrter Herr Professor!</tei:p><tei:p>Zuerst auf Ihre Werke, u. zwar auf die Beethoven-Sonaten-Einzelausg.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  Schenker’s complete edition of the Beethoven piano sonatas was published 1921–23, so presumably Halm is talking here of the <tei:hi rend="italic">Die letzten fünf Sonaten Beethovens</tei:hi>, i.e. the <tei:hi rend="italic">Erläuterungsausgabe</tei:hi> of Opp. 109, 110, 111, and 101, which were published individually (1913–20).</tei:note> aufmerksam gemacht hat mich ein Herr M. Henz<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  A Matthäus Hentz, a teacher at the Heilbronn teachers’ college (Lehrerseminar), appears in the Heilbronn address books  for 1923, 1925, and 1929.  (Thanks are due to Werner Föll of the Stadtarchiv Heilbronn for this information in an email exchange, June 15, 2007.)</tei:note>, jetzt Oberlehrer (Titel wahrscheinlich “Studienrat”) am Lehrerseminar in Heilbronn am Neckar.  Er ist -eigentlich- Naturwissenschaftler u. Mathematiker von Beruf; sicher wird er sich über die zugedachte Gabe<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  „intended gift“: no letter survives from S for eighteen months prior to this letter, hence it is unclear to what this refers.</tei:note> außerordentlich freuen; doch glaube ich, daß sie bei m. Freund Schmid,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  Theodor Karl Schmid:  long-time friend of Halm's, who wrote an essay "Tonsetzer der Gegenwart, August Halm," <tei:hi rend="italic">Neue Musikzeitung</tei:hi> 31 [1910], 469-74, in which he proclaimed Halm the "most modern composer" after Bruckner.  He was a Senior Lecturer (Oberlehrer) at the Nagold</tei:note> Oberlehrer u. Musikdirektor in Nagold (Württemberg) musikalische fruchtbarer angelegt wäre.</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> Von den genannten Sachen ist noch nichts an mich gelangt.  Ich wohne nicht mehr in Eßlingen, sondern in Wickersdorf bei Saalfeld a. d. Saale, Thüringen.  Habe ich Ihnen geschrieben, daß ich im Mai m. großes C dur Konzert,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn5">  Halm’s <tei:hi rend="italic">Concerto in C Major for Large Orchestra with Obligato Piano</tei:hi> (Stuttgart: G.A. Zumsteeg, 1913), published under the auspices of the Society for the Publication of the Works of August Halm (Gesellschaft zur Veröffentlichung der Werke August Halms), founded in July 1910 at the instigation of Gustav Wyneken, Halm’s close friend, fellow teacher, and eventually brother-in-law when he married Wyneken’s sister, Hilda, in April 1913.</tei:note> von F. Busch<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn6">  Fritz Busch [create biogfile and link].</tei:note> aufgeführt, in Stuttgart gehört habe?  Erfolg im Konzert sehr gut; in den Zeitungen verschieden, meist flau oder noch weniger!  Im Oktober wurde es zum erstenmal aufgeführt in Ulm, wobei ich die Klavierstimme gespielt habe, (so daß ich zu wenig vom Ganzen hörte).  Ich bin gern hier (in der Freien Schulgemeinde).  Daß Cotta den Kp. weggibt,<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn7">  S informed Cotta on January 23, 1921 (CA 188) that Hertzka had indicated his readiness to “cover the costs” not only of the second half-volume of <tei:hi rend="italic">Kontrapunkt</tei:hi> but also of further volumes.  Cotta signified its readiness to cancel the binding contract between them and surrended stocks of previous publications on February 5 (OJ 9/31, [46]), and the details are discussed betwee Cotta and UE during that month.  </tei:note> ist mir insofern leid, als ich mich gefreut hatte, daß der alte schwäb. Verlag wieder etwas Wichtiges von großem Stil herausbringt.</tei:p><tei:p>[ <tei:hi rend="italic">remainder written vertically on the left, top to bottom:</tei:hi> ]</tei:p><tei:p>Aber wenn es für Sie so vorteilhafter ist, so ist mir es natürlich auch lieber.  Den Winter war ich zieml. fleißig; vielleicht finde ich auch bald einen Verleger.</tei:p><tei:p>Herzliche Grüße von Ihrem
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] A. Halm</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Halm to Schenker, dated July 28, 1921</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>July 28, 1921</tei:p><tei:p>Dear Professor!</tei:p><tei:p>A Mr. M. Henz<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/>, now a senior teacher (title is probably “lecturer”) in the teacher’s college in Heilbronn on the Neckar, first made me aware of your works, specifically of the Beethoven sonatas, individual editions.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/>  He is -actually- a scientist and mathematician by profession.  He will surely be extraordinarily happy about the intended gift.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/>  But I believe that it would be musically more fruitfully placed with my friend Schmid,<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/> senior teacher and music director [at the teacher’s college] in Nagold (Württemberg).</tei:p><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> Nothing of the mentioned items has yet reached me.  I no longer live in Esslingen but in Wickersdorf near Saalfeld on the Saale, Thuringia.  Did I write you that in May I heard my large C-major concerto<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn5"/> performed by Fritz Busch<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn6"/> in Stuttgart?  The success at the concerto was very good; in the newspapers, mixed and mostly dull or even less!  It was performed in October for the first time in Ulm, where I played the piano part (so that I heard too little of the whole).  I am happily here (in the Free School Community).  That Cotta is giving up <tei:hi rend="italic">Counterpoint</tei:hi>|<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn7"/> makes me sorry insofar as it made me happy that the old Swabian publisher was issuing something important and of grand style.</tei:p><tei:p>[<tei:hi rend="italic">remainder written vertically on the left, top to bottom:</tei:hi> ]</tei:p><tei:p>But if it is so much more advantageous for you, then it is naturally also preferable to me.  I was rather productive in winter.  Maybe I will also find a publisher soon.</tei:p><tei:p>Cordial greetings from Your 
[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ]  A. Halm</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>