<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="../../../../../css/sdo_oxygen.css" type="text/css"?>
<sdo:recordCollection xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:dcterms="http://purl.org/dc/terms/" xmlns:marcrel="http://www.loc.gov/loc.terms/relators/" xmlns:sdo="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.cch.kcl.ac.uk/schenker ../../../../../schema/schenker.xsd"><sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:source><!-- MovableType Shelfmark:OJ 11/46 : 9-22-03 --><sdo:correspondence shelfmark="TEST-SHELFMARK1" /></sdo:source><tei:handNotes><tei:handNote><!-- Please populate at least one handNote.  Remember to include an xml:id attribute and the scope of the work --></tei:handNote></tei:handNotes><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary statements of responsiblity as needed below --><tei:respStmt xml:id="IB"><tei:persName>Ian Bent</tei:persName><!-- Add additional or remove unnecessary specific responsibility notes. --><tei:resp>Transcription</tei:resp><tei:resp>XML Encoding</tei:resp><tei:resp>Translation</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><tei:respStmt xml:id="BOT"><tei:name>Automated Script</tei:name><tei:resp>Conversion from MovableType syntax to TEI</tei:resp></tei:respStmt><!-- Add additional change elements below to note major changes to the document --><tei:revisionDesc><tei:change when="2010-01-21" who="#BOT">Template Generated</tei:change></tei:revisionDesc></sdo:collectionDesc><sdo:record ID="r0001"><!-- 
© Deemed to be in the public domain.
© Transcription Christoph Hust, 2006.
© Translation Ian Bent, 2007.
© Commentary, Footnotes, Summary Christoph Hust &amp; Ian Bent 2006
 --><!-- 
<dcterms:license>In the public domain.</dcterms:license>
<dcterms:provenance>Schenker, Heinrich (1903-1935) - -Schenker, Jeanette (1935-c.1942) - -Ratz, Erwin (c.1942-c.1955) - -Jonas, Oswald (c.1955-1978) - -University of California, Riverside (1978 - -)</dcterms:provenance>
<dcterms:rightsHolder>IPR: Deemed to be in the public domain; Image:  University of California, Riverside;  Transcription, Translation, Commentary, Footnotes, and Summary: Christoph Hust &amp; Ian Bent.</dcterms:rightsHolder>
 --><sdo:itemDesc><!-- Date Created: 09/22/1903 01:00:00 AM --><!-- MT Tags: "Hellmesberger ~ HSchenker" --><dc:title>Handwritten letter from Josef Hellmesberger jun. to Schenker, dated September 22, [1903]</dc:title><dcterms:dateSubmitted>2007-03-26</dcterms:dateSubmitted><dc:description>The VPO's try-out of new compositions has been fixed for September 28. He hopes S's work will be accepted.

</dc:description><dc:subject>Hellmesberger, Joseph; Schenker, Heinrich;  Wiener Philharmonker;  Vienna Philharmonic Orchestra;  compositions;  rehearsal;  Grosser Musikvereinsaal;  Gesellschaft der Musikfreunde</dc:subject><!-- Add the EATS key attribute value to indicate the sender of the letter --><marcrel:correspondent key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:correspondent><!-- Add the key attribute to indicate the recipient of the letter --><marcrel:recipient key="EATS_nNNNNNN">  - -</marcrel:recipient></sdo:itemDesc><tei:transcription><!-- BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Josef Hellmesberger jun. to Schenker, dated September 22, [1903]</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Wien 22/9 [1903]</tei:p><tei:p>Sehr geehrter Herr Doctor!</tei:p><tei:p>Die Novitätenprobe<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn1">  From 1900 to 1903, Joseph Hellmesberger jun. (1855-1907) conducted the Vienna Philharmonic Orchestra as successor to Gustav Mahler.  H is referring to a session (“Probe” is literally “rehearsal”) when new works are played through by the orchestra with a view to possible adoption into the program. </tei:note> müßte vorläufig für Montag den 28^t^ d. M. angesetzt werden weil Anfangs October täglich Proben in der Oper angesetzt sind daher für die Novitätenprobe keine Zeit bliebe.  Die Probe für den 28. d. M. ist auch noch nicht sicher weil der große Musikvereinssaal<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn2">  The “große Musikvereinssal“ is the Large (or Golden) Hall of the Gesellschaft der Musikfreunde in Vienna.  </tei:note> zu diesem Zwecke erst gemiethet werden muß.  Wenn der Saal für diesen Tag frei ist so findet die Probe <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> am 28^t^ d. M. statt.  Ich bitte nun Sorge zu tragen daß ich das Notenmaterial bis zu jenem Tage habe damit ich das Werk<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn3">  In a diary entry of September 30, 1903 (OJ 1/4, p. 10), S wrote “My female choruses are advertised in the Gesellschaft [der Musikfreunde] concerts” (Meine Frauenchöre werden in den Programmen der Gesellsch. Conz. angekündigt).  The only known work corresponding to this designation is S’s <tei:hi rend="italic">Drei</tei:hi> [recte: <tei:hi rend="italic">Vier</tei:hi>] <tei:hi rend="italic">Gesänge für Frauenstimmen a cappella</tei:hi>, Op.8, undated and unpublished, which seems an unlikely choice for the VPO (Benjamin McKay Ayotte, <tei:hi rend="italic">Heinrich Schenker: A Guide to Research</tei:hi> (London: Routledge, 2004), pp. 16–18).  There are no documents in the Wiener Philharmoniker archives relating to this.  (Coincidentally, this is the time at which Schoenberg’s orchestration of S’s <tei:hi rend="italic">Syrische Tänze</tei:hi> was being prepared for performance in Berlin.)  </tei:note> bei der Probe durchnehmen kann.</tei:p><tei:p>Ich selbst bringe +jeder+ Novität das größte Interesse entgegen von wem sie immer sei also auch diesem Werke.  Die Annahme zur Aufführung hängt jedoch nicht von mir sondern vom Plenum der Philharmoniker ab.<tei:note xml:id="r0001-fn4">  The orchestra was famous for its democratic structures.  </tei:note> Wenn ich das Werk zur Novitätenprobe bringe so zeigt <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> dieß schon von großer[<tei:hi rend="italic">sic</tei:hi>] Interesse da ich nicht alle 28 eingereichten Novitäten in einer einzigen 2stündigen Probe durchspielen lassen kann.  Also an mir liegt es nicht allein.  Indem ich hoffe daß ihr[<tei:hi rend="italic">sic</tei:hi>] Werk angenommen wird bitte ich nochmals Sorge zu tragen daß das Stimmenmaterial rechtzeitig eintrifft.</tei:p><tei:p>Hochachtungsvollst</tei:p><tei:p>[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] Josef Hellmesberger</tei:p></tei:transcription><tei:translation><!-- EXTENDED BODY: --><tei:p><tei:hi rend="bold">Handwritten letter from Josef Hellmesberger jun. to Schenker, dated September 22, [1903]</tei:hi></tei:p><tei:p>Vienna, September 22, [1903]</tei:p><tei:p>Dear Doctor,</tei:p><tei:p>The tryout of new works<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn1"/> has had to be fixed provisionally for Monday the 28th of the month because at the beginning of October rehearsals have been fixed each day in the Opera House, leaving no time for the tryout of new works.  The tryout for the 28th of the month is, even so, still not definite, because the Großer Musikvereinsaal<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn2"/> must first be rented for this purpose.  If the hall is free for this day, then the tryout <tei:hi rend="bold">{2}</tei:hi> will take place on the 28th.  Please ensure that I have the music materials by that day so that I can run through the work<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn3"/> at the tryout.</tei:p><tei:p>I myself take the keenest interest in +every+ new work, whoever it may be by; thus [I do so] for this work, too.  Acceptance for performance, however, depends not on me but on the staff of the Philharmonic.<tei:ptr target="#r0001-fn4"/>  If I put the work forward for the tryout of new works, <tei:hi rend="bold">{3}</tei:hi> this already shows keen interest, since I cannot play through in the one two-hour rehearsal all of the twenty-eight new works that have been received.  So it is not up to me alone.  In hoping that your work will be accepted, I ask you again to ensure that the parts arrive punctually.</tei:p><tei:p>With kind regards,</tei:p><tei:p>[ <tei:hi rend="italic">signed:</tei:hi> ] Josef Hellmesberger</tei:p></tei:translation></sdo:record></sdo:recordCollection>